<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons viz. Davids tears for his rebellious son Absalom, Israels tears for Abners fall by bloudy Joab, infants tears for Athaliahs treason, / preached by S.L. a true lover of the church, his king, and country, in his country-cure.</title>
            <author>S. L.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L66</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2129_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869068</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 242:E2129[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons viz. Davids tears for his rebellious son Absalom, Israels tears for Abners fall by bloudy Joab, infants tears for Athaliahs treason, / preached by S.L. a true lover of the church, his king, and country, in his country-cure.</title>
                  <author>S. L.</author>
                  <author>T. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.C. and L.P. for Robert Crofts, at the Crown in Chancery-lane, under Serjeants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A4v signed: T.L.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Abners fall by the hands of bloody Joab -- Absalom's unnatural rebellion against his father -- Athaliah's detestable treason.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  II Samuel --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  II Kings --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121429:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>THREE SERMONS,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IZ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Davids</hi> Tears for his Rebellious Son <hi>Abſalom, Iſraels</hi> Tears for <hi>Abners</hi> Fall by blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Joab,</hi> Infants Tears for <hi>Athaliahs</hi> Treaſon, <hi>PREACHED By</hi> S. L. <hi>a true Lover of the Church, his King, and Country, in his Country-cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>In <hi>Rhama</hi> was a voyce heard, mourning, and weeping, and great howling: <hi>Rachel</hi> weeping for her Children, and would not be comforted, becauſe they were not. <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 28.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>They have taken away my Lord, and I know not where to find him. <bibl>
                  <hi>John</hi> 28. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Be ſure that your Sin will find you out. <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 32. 23.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> T. C. <hi>and</hi> L. P. <hi>for</hi> Robert Crofts, <hi>at the</hi> Crown <hi>in</hi> Chancery-lane, <hi>under Serjeants Inne.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121429:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121429:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM Lord PETRE, Grace, Mercie, and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the <hi>Ilienſes</hi> viſited <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> ſomewhat out of ſeaſon to condole with him the death of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> he ſmiling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered, <hi>Et ego doleo Hectore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veſtrum,</hi> and I am ſorry for the loſs of your <hi>Hector:</hi> who was dead many years before. Even ſo, perhaps, it may be my portion, (if not by you, for your goodneſs ſake,) yet by ſome others out of malignity, and evil diſpoſition, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a hard cenſure, if not a ſcornfull flout, with the <hi>Trojans,</hi> that I preſent to you, and the world, an Embrio of my brain, born out of due time, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb facs="tcp:121429:3"/>
ſaid of himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 8. But give me leave to anſwer for my ſelf, and that ſtinking vapour will eaſily be ſhaken off from the skirts of my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For firſt, I did appear in ſeaſon, and offered to the Preſs ſome of them, within a few dayes after the fall of our good <hi>Joſiah:</hi> but was diſſwaded to the contrary, for ſome reaſons best known to my ſelf. Secondly, it is Gods promiſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 7. <hi>The name of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall rott; But the righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, Pſal.</hi> 112. 6. And that our good King may ever live, and live in the living pictures of himſelf, and in the hearts of his people, and never be forgotten (like <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Magdalen)</hi> for the good d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed ſhe had done, <hi>Mar</hi> 14. 9. I conceive it not unſeaſonable to ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:121429:3"/>
ſomething of his life and fall. <hi>Vivit poſt funera virtus.</hi> Thirdly, although it may be counted civil policie to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yet my inward prompter tells me, it is uncivil duty, not to anoint the dead with the oyntment of my deareſt love and honour. <hi>Dum ſpiritus hos regit artus.</hi> To love the living, may be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſitical, as more, <hi>propter ſua,</hi> than <hi>ſe:</hi> but to love the dead, when they can do neither good, nor harm, is <hi>verus amor,</hi> true love indeed: and ſuch is mine, and ſo I am free from the aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ambitiouſneſs, covetouſneſs, and vain-glory. The firſt text speaks of an unnatural rebellion, and a civil, or rather uncivil War, raiſed by a child againſt his father, and King father. The ſecond of a deadly treachery and conſpiracy, to bring down to the ground
<pb facs="tcp:121429:4"/>
a Prince, and a great man, whereof the World was not worthy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 38. The third of a horrid treaſon, not only againſt the father, the King fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but even againſt his children, that as the Husbandmen ſpake one to another, <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 7. the Inheritance might be theirs. So that as <hi>Protoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> in his abſence, finding at his return a line drawn upon his board in his ſhop, with much exquiſiteneſs, preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>Apelles</hi> had been there: Even ſo, by the monſtrous conception, birth, and carriage of all, or either of them, it may be imagined (without an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) who was the father of them, <hi>Jo.</hi> 8. 44. and he that ſet them on work, will, or hath paid them the wages of <hi>Balaam,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 15. If you will be pleaſed to over-look with a Candid eye
<pb facs="tcp:121429:4"/>
the following Treatiſes, you ſhall find the condition of the Church of God, to be as a Lillie among Thorns, <hi>Can.</hi> 2. 2. and her greateſt enemies to be of her own houſhold, as Chriſt fore-told, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 36. <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> (like <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> and <hi>Pilate)</hi> will combine againſt Christ, and his Members, to dethrone, and extirpate them; but ſuch is Gods over-ruling providence, that, <hi>Sanguis Martyrum, ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves her from falling into aſhes, and after a black Cloud, and waterie tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, ſends forth the brighteſt, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt beames of his favour, and never-dying love, to warm her, refreſh her, and make her laſt daies better than the firſt, like <hi>Jobs,</hi> 42. 12. Here again you ſhall find, with what a Goſpel-face, rebellion and treaſon are painted, able
<pb facs="tcp:121429:5"/>
to deceive the very elect, <hi>Mark</hi> 13. 22. but being unmasked, how mort deformed, more ugly do they look than <hi>Pharaohs</hi> lean kine, when they had devoured the fat, the full, the fair, the well fleſhed of the Land? But leſt it be ſaid of me, as once a flout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Critick</hi> ſaid unto the Citizens of <hi>Mindus,</hi> who having great gates to a little Citie, he bade them to ſhut the gates, leſt the Citie run out: even ſo, leſt the bead ſeem bigger than the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the Proem larger than the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I ſhall only deſire, that God may be Glorified, your ſelf Contented, and confirmed in thoſe Principles which you have hitherto profeſſed with zeal and courage, I conclude,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant in Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-work for Chriſt, <hi>T. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121429:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED The next Sabbath after the fall of our good <hi>Ioſiah.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 Sam. 3 38.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>And the King ſaid unto his Servants, Know ye not that there is a Prince, and a great man this day fallen in</hi> Iſrael?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Hiſtory makes mention of a ſtrong, long, and ſharp diſpute between the Houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> for precedency of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, for the Scepter, and Regal Throne: the <hi>Generaliſsimo</hi> on the one ſide was <hi>Abner,</hi> and on the other <hi>Joab,</hi> men of might, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121429:6"/>
and renown, like thoſe of old, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 4. who maintained their Arguments, not with ſmooth words, like Sophiſters in the Schools, but with rugged Blows, and point of ſwords: and therefore no wiſe man could expect, but the concluſion thereof would end, and be drawn up in bloud. For as it is written of thoſe two gallant <hi>Romans,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non tulit</hi> Caeſar, Pompeiuſve <hi>Parem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> could never tollerate an equal, a Copartner, or Coſharer with them in earthly glory, no more than can Wedlock in the ſame Bed: Even ſo, theſe Worthies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> fomenting their ſtrife, and whetting on their anger (as the Lion is ſaid to beat himſelf with his tayl, to make him the more fierce on his prey<hi>:)</hi> ſometimes by publick ambition, that they might ſit neareſt to the Crown<hi>:</hi> ſometimes by Popular applauſe, that ſilly, ſimple, and weak Reed, or Spiders webb, that deceives all that truſt in it, <hi>Job</hi> 8. 14. and ſometimes for private ſiniſter ends of their own, (although far different,) they contrive and plot each others overthrow; and what the one cannot act by open force, he will effect by ſecret treaſon. <hi>Joabs</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121429:6"/>
for the death of his Brother <hi>Aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel,</hi> may not, muſt not, ſhall not be miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, but by <hi>Abners</hi> fall, and <hi>Abners</hi> fall cannot be without <hi>Davids,</hi> without <hi>Iſraels</hi> tears: for <hi>David</hi> weeps, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> weeps, and weeps again, as it is <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. <hi>that as a man falleth before wicked men, ſo</hi> Abner <hi>ſhall fall. And the King ſaid unto his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Know ye not, that there is a Prince, and a great man this day fallen in</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>No man as yet, (no not the Son of God himſelf as man) be he never ſo potent and mighty, was privileged from death, or from taſting of Deaths cup, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 48. for the decree is paſt, the doom is irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable, <hi>decretum est omnibus mori,</hi> there is an appointed time for all men to dye, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27. But to fall immaturely (like Fruit before it be ripe) but to be cropped like the Roſe in the bud; but to be nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Spring, like the flower of the field; but to be chaſed up and down, like a Fox fleeing to the Mountains; but to be wearied and worried to death, <hi>(Acte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-like)</hi> by his own Hounds, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Currs, thirſting to fill themſelves full with the fleſh and blood of their loving Maſter; but to be cheated and gull'd of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121429:7"/>
life, and that after many Proteſtations, Vows, and lifting up of hands to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; but to be betrayed with a Kiſſe, as <hi>Judas</hi> ſerved his Lord; but to be ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed up root and branch in time of peace, and that under colour of a fair treaty and parley, as <hi>Joab</hi> did <hi>Abner, verſ.</hi> 26, 27. <hi>Hinc illae lachryme, Niobe</hi> herſelf will weep at this. This cannot but cauſe the moſt ſtony heart to melt, this cannot but cauſe all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to hang down their heads like Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhes, and to wring their hands, and to water their couches with tears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 6. and this cannot but move <hi>Iſrael</hi> to curſe, with <hi>David,</hi> the Author and Authors of <hi>Iſraels</hi> woe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. that <hi>Abner,</hi> a Prince, a great man, ſhould fall, and thus fall, and in <hi>Iſrael</hi> too, where was the Law, and the Prophets, where the word was taught and preached; and where a reformation, a goodly reformation, a general reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is pretended. But although <hi>(horret me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſſe) David</hi> is aſhamed, is ſtartled and trembles at ſo horrid, ſo cruel, ſo unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a Fact, that he would not have it publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor proclamed in <hi>Askalon,</hi> leſt the Heathen, the uncircumciſed, the Philiſtines, the Papiſts, the Jeſuites try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121429:7"/>
and rejoyce in <hi>Iſraels</hi> wonderfull, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable, invaluable loſſe, wherein the light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is quenched as it is, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 17. Yet he declareth and broacheth this ſad news, and heavy tidings to his Servants, that they might take notice what a rich Jewel was fallen from the Crown: ſaying, <hi>Know ye not, that a Prince, and a great man is this day fallen in</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>There is no innocent blood ſpilt and ſhed upon the ground, but hath a tongue to cry unto Heaven for vengeance. So ſaith God to <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4. 10. <hi>The voice of tby bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood crieth to me from the Earth:</hi> and therefore that the Land might be found guiltleſſe of ſo foul crime, for,
<q>
                  <l>Clamitat in Coelum vox ſanguinis, &amp; Sodomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</l>
                  <l>Vox oppreſſorum, merces retenta laborum,</l>
               </q>
and ſo acquitted of the imminent, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent judgements following it, from the great Tribunal above, the Law requires the Coroner to ſit and make enquiry, after the death of the meaneſt Peaſant, (for ſaith the Statute in that caſe provided) <hi>the King hath loſt a Subject, and muſt have an account thereof.</hi> How much more then, when an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121429:8"/>
a Prince, a great man falles, ought whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the ſame bond of love, to ſtand u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as one man, and require ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his death? that as it is, ver. 28. <hi>The Kingdom may be guiltleſſe before the Lord for ever, concerning the blood of</hi> Abner. <hi>David</hi> fore-ſees a black ſtorm comming, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labours to make his peace with God and Men, laying open unto them, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, &amp; nature of <hi>Abners</hi> fall, in theſe words, ver. 33. <hi>Died</hi> Abner <hi>as a fool dieth?</hi> and prayeth unto the Lord to reward the evil doer, according to his wickedneſſe, ver. 39. and <hi>(digito monstrat hominem)</hi> points out with his finger to the eyes of all the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in <hi>Iſrael, Joabs</hi> evil and wickedneſſe, like <hi>Cains</hi> brand-mark on his forehead, to be the ſhedding of bloud, innocent bloud, Princes bloud: for ſaith the King to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>Know ye not, that there is a Prince, and a great man, this day fallen in Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scelus aliquis tutum, nullus ſecurum tulit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> a man may commit theft, rape, murther, &amp;c. ſo ſecretly, that neither the Sun, <hi>oculus mundi,</hi> the worlds great eye, nor mans eye ſeeth it not: <hi>But all things are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and open unto his eyes, with whom we have to do,</hi> Heb. 4. 13. but that, <hi>Erynnis conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:121429:8"/>
the Worm of conſcience will be alwaies checking, and gnawing, and griping of him for them, with pangs as bitter as Hell. Let <hi>Richard the third</hi> deny this if he could ſpeak but once again, was not his hand ſtill upon his Dagger, being afraid that every one met and found him, would ſlay him? did not the bloud of the harmleſſe infants he cauſed to be ſlain, that they might be a foot-ſtool to mount him into their throne, ſo trouble him, ſo diſquiet him, that either ſleep departed from his eyes, as it did from <hi>Ahaſuerus, Esth.</hi> 1. or he was ſo frighted in his ſleep, with dreadfull apparitions of ugly Devils, haling and tearing of him into pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that his life was burthenſome unto him? Let <hi>Joab</hi> ſpeak what one comfortable day or night he enjoyed, after the ſlaughter of a good Prince, I had almoſt ſaid the beſt of Princes. In the day time, <hi>trepidat ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundinis umbram,</hi> he is afraid of his own ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; in the night, the cracking of a few Cheſt-nuts in the fire terrifie him: So that herein is the Prophecie fulfilled, Iſa. 57. 21. <hi>non est pax impiis, there is no peace unto the wicked, ſaith my God;</hi> or otherwiſe perhaps, <hi>Joab</hi> may vaunt it for ſome few years, or daies over his prey, in great Gallantry, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121429:9"/>
Pomp, magnificence, and ſtatelineſſe, but ſo ſure as the Lord lives, his end ſhall not be peace, <hi>neither ſhall he go to the grave in a full age, as a rick of Corn commeth in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into the barn,</hi> Job 5. 26. and to this effect ſpeaks <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 37. 35, 36. <hi>I have ſeen the wicked ſtrong, and ſpreading himſelf like a green Bay-tree: Yet be paſſed away, and to be was gone, and I ſought him, but could not find him;</hi> and no wonder, for evil ſhall hunt the cruel man to deſtruction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140. 11. and ſuch is the juſtice of the Almighty, that commonly, that as he made a pit, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, ſo he ſhould fall into the pit that he made, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 15. and,
<q>
                  <l>Neque enim Lex juſtior ulla eſt,</l>
                  <l>Quam necis artifices arte perire ſua.</l>
               </q>
then evil watch, evil catch. As <hi>Tomyris</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Cyrus</hi> who had formerly ſlain hir ſon, cutting off his head, and caſting it into a Tub of bloud: <hi>ſanguinem ſitisti, ſanguinem habes,</hi> bloud thou thirſtedſt, drink thy fill, and <hi>as I have done,</hi> ſaith Adonibezek, Judg. 1. 7. <hi>ſo God hath rewarded me.</hi> Even ſo, us our <hi>Abnor,</hi> our great man in the Text, falls by the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of <hi>Joab,</hi> ſo <hi>Joab</hi> muſt look to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121429:9"/>
have his fall too, although it be many years after, by <hi>Benaiah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 31, 32, 33, 34. and the curſe of <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſhall follow him to his grave, Jer. 22. 18. <hi>There ſhall be none to lament him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Ah my Brother, or ah Lord, or ah his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> And let all true hearted <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpeak as <hi>Cuſhi</hi> did to <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 32. So let all the Enemies of the Lord, their King periſh, and be as <hi>Joab</hi> is.</p>
            <p>The Text is a vindication of <hi>Davids</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie in, and a lively deſcription of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> death, wherein let us conſider theſe five particulars.</p>
            <p>1. His qualities and ſo he was no mean man ſprung from the dunghil, or Ale-tap, no broken Citizen, or bankerout Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, no Mechanick, or Artificer, none of the baſe condition of <hi>Davids</hi> followers, when he fled from <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 2. but he was <hi>Iſhboſheths</hi> ſtaff, the ſupporter of <hi>Sauls</hi> houſe, and the glory of that Diadem, and ſo the Pen-man ſets him out two waies,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As a Prince.</item>
               <item>2. As a great man.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. As a Prince; unto which the Latine word hath a near relation, <hi>Princeps,</hi> the which ſignifies a chief head or ruler<hi>:</hi> ſecretly inſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121429:10"/>
that as of a head he ought to be defended and made much of, becauſe life conſiſts ſo well in the head as in the heart; then as a Ruler he ought to be obeyed and feared, according to Saint <hi>Paul's</hi> rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher Powers:</hi> but <hi>Joab</hi> had learned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Obſta principiis, Obsta Principibus,</hi> withſtand the beginnings of ſin, ſtifling the firſt conception of murther in his heart, to promote it, and give life unto it by the fall of a Prince; and ſo hath received to himſelf condemnation, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>2ly, The <hi>Hebrews</hi> uſe many words, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifying a Prince, but I ſhall make uſe but of one, and that is <hi>Naghidh,</hi> carrying this ſence, <hi>Dux, Princeps,</hi> a Captain and chief Commander, ordering, diſpoſing, and giving rules to Souldiers, to go out and come in, to draw and to ſheath their ſwords: and ſuch a Prince was <hi>Abner,</hi> and a valiant Prince: but whom <hi>Ajax</hi> cannot conquer, <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> will undermine by trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>For know ye not that a Prince, and a great man is fallen?</hi> And ſo I paſſe to the ſecond Branch.</p>
            <p>2. As a great man. As when <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſpake, there was trembling, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 1.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121429:10"/>
               <hi>As when the Lion roars, who will not be afraid?</hi> Amos 3. 8. even ſo, when this great man ſpeaks, not onely the inferiour beaſts of the Foreſt, but even the Lion himſelf coucheth, as is clear in the 11 verſe, before the Text; and if a bare hand upon the wall, did ſo ſtarcle <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in his cups, when men are moſt Pot-valiant, and in the Guard of his Princes, and making metry with his wives and concubines, that his countenance chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the joints of his loins were looſed, and his knees ſmote one againſt another, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 6. How will <hi>Joab</hi> look? How will <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab</hi> ſtand? How will he ſhift when the great God ſhall make inquiſition for this great mans blood? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 12. <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him for cutting off but the Lap of <hi>Saul</hi>'s garment, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 5, 6. How then deeply may they be touched, that had a hand in cutting off the head of the Lords anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? for the greater the perſon, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the ſin in them that conſpire his death. Kings and Princes, and great man in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, are termed gods by Gods own mouth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 6 and to act Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch, is to be treacherous to God himſelf, for which cauſe God ſpared not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121429:11"/>
the Angels that had finned, but caſt them down into hell, and delivered them into chains of darkneſſe to be kept unto damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. What Chriſt ſpake in another kind, holds true in this, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 40. <hi>In as much as ye have done it unto them, ye have done it unto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another particular is, the manner of this great Princes death, &amp; ſo he is not threatned a fall, as God told <hi>Adam,</hi> that if he ſhould eat of the tree of knowledge of good and evil, in that day he ſhould die the death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17. for then he would have looked about him, either to prevent his fall, or to make a good preparation for his ſoul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his fall; as the wiſe Steward did for his body, <hi>Duke</hi> 26. 4. but in the preſent tenſe, <hi>occidit,</hi> is fallen, noting the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his death, and his unprovideneſſe for his grave, <hi>Joab</hi> not onely labouring to kill his body, but ſo far as he could his ſoul too, like as the <hi>Italian</hi> I read of endevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſerve his enemy overcome in duel; wherein we may obſerve,</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>The mercies of the wicked are truel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly, The uncertainty of our death, we have one way into the world, but many out.
<q>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:121429:11"/>
                  <l>Ferro, peſte, fame, vinclis, algore, calore,</l>
                  <l>Mille modis miſeros mors rapit una viros.</l>
               </q>
as ſometimes by fire, famine, plague, water, ſword, like <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Joab.</hi> And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ſhould move us to look for that in every place, which every where looks for us. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> taſted of deaths Cup in the deep Sea. <hi>Herod</hi> upon his throne <hi>Eglon</hi> ſunning himſelf in his Summer Parlour. <hi>Amnon</hi> when his heart was merry with wine. <hi>Ahab</hi> in the battel. <hi>Zenecharib</hi> in the houſe of his God. And who amongſt us <hi>can coaſt of to morrow, for we know not what a day may bring forth?</hi> Prov. 27. 1. Let it be our wiſedom then,</p>
            <p>1. So to live, as if we were alwaies dying, and giving up our accounts to the great judge of Heaven and Earth of our ſeveral ſtewardſhips.</p>
            <p>2ly. With <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the time of famine; with <hi>Solomons</hi> Piſmire in the harveſt time; and with the wiſe Virgins, in the acceptable time, to provide oyl for our Lamps, that we may be found a people ready prepared for our God, when he ſhall knock at our door, and call us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121429:12"/>
3ly. To pray alwaies as the Church hath taught us, From ſudden death, Good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>3ly. The next particular is, the time of <hi>Abners</hi> fall, and that is ſaid to be, <hi>hoc die,</hi> this day, <hi>Know ye not, that there is a Prince, and a great man, this day fallen in Iſrael?</hi> This was a day of darkneſſe, and of black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a day of clouds, and obſcuritie, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 2. a day of heavineſſe and mourning, a ſtormy and watery day: and in a word, ſuch a ſad day to <hi>David,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as if as one man they had combined to revive their <hi>Abner</hi> with their tears, as Chriſt did <hi>Lazarus, John</hi> 11. or if they could not do that for him, yet they would witneſſe to the world their love to him, and how wonderfully they lamented his loſſe. To love a rich man, and a great man living, is no news, <hi>the living dog being better than the dead Lion,</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 4. and moreover every mans affection almoſt extending more, <hi>propter ſua,</hi> than <hi>propter ſe,</hi> for his private profit or preferment, than for any parts or goodneſſe he finds in him, like drones which haunt the Hive for the honny ſake: but to love him dead, when he can do him neither good nor harm, is <hi>rara avis, nigro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:121429:12"/>
               <hi>ſimilima cygno,</hi> a rare quality hardly to be found among the ſons of men: and yet this was <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, <hi>Iſraels</hi> caſe for <hi>Abner,</hi> and ought to be our caſe for our Prince, and great man, that is this day fallen in our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And ſo this leads me to the next particular.</p>
            <p>4ly. The place where he fell, and that is ſaid to be <hi>Iſrael;</hi> he fell not amongſt the barbarous <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Cannibals,</hi> amongſt the inhuman <hi>Switzers,</hi> in the Conqueſt of the <hi>Thuricences</hi> in battel, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1443. or amongſt the <hi>Numantines,</hi> who vowed not to break their faſt, but with the fleſh of a <hi>Roman,</hi> nor drink till they had taſted of the blood of an Enemie; or amongſt the heathen and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed: but in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where God was known in her Palaces, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. 3. but in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> where his wonderfull acts were mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted; but in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a peculiar people cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to himſelf; but in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets taught, and his name was called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Quis talia fando, temperet à lacrimis?</hi> who can reſtrain tears? that where there was ſuch gracious means, there ſhould be ſuch graceleſſe practices, by a brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121429:13"/>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 5. If this had been done at <hi>Rome,</hi> where degrading of Princes, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of heretical Princes, with their whole families, is a warrantable and meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious tenet, the world would not have trembled at it, nor wondered or admired it<hi>:</hi> but to be practiced in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the wonder of the world, for as it is, Deut. 47, 8. <hi>What Nation is ſo great, unto whom the Gods come ſo near unto them, in all that they call unto the Lord for? And what Nation is ſo great, that hath ordinances and Laws ſo righteous?</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this makes <hi>Iſraels</hi> condition, equivalent to <hi>Chorozins</hi> and <hi>Bethſaidaes</hi> Mat. 11. 21. <hi>Wo to thee Corazin, wo to thee Bethſaida, for if the great works which were done in you, had been done in Tyrus and Sidon, they had repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted long agone in Sackeloth and Aſhes.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall be eaſier for <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> at the day of judgement, than for you; than for <hi>Iſrael. Joab</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> his brother were men of War, and ſo the leſſe marvell they neither reſpected the perſon, nor place where they ſhed blood: but the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our Prince, and great man to death, were not only Sword-men, but Gown-men, even wolves in ſheeps clothing: and if God ſpared not the old world, nor <hi>Sodom</hi> nor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121429:13"/>
               <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5, 6. how ſhall they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the judgement of God to come? and, <hi>the judgement of God is according to truth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them that commit ſuch things,</hi> Rom. 2. 2. Wherefore as <hi>Daniel</hi> counſelled King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> 4. 27. Break off thyſins by righteouſneſs, and thine iniquities by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards the poor, that there be a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thine errour; even ſo, my counſel to all <hi>Iſrael</hi> that have had a hand in the Princes death, and great mans fall, is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that we read of, Amos 4. 12. <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet thy God, O Iſrael.</hi> For repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may heal, where thy ſin hath wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>5ly. <hi>Davids</hi> Proclamation throughout all <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> to take notice of his loſſe, and their loſſe; his and their loſſe, as if they had with him loſt the brighteſt ſtar in the Firmament; or had loſt their right eyes, right hands, or their right feet, or as the Church complained, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4 20. <hi>The breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord is taken from us, of whom we ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder his ſhadow we ſhall be preſerved alive among the Heathen.</hi> How hath the Lord darkened the Daughter of <hi>Zion</hi> in his wrath, and hath caſt down from Heaven unto earth the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121429:14"/>
beauty of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> draw near, behold, and ſee what a Prince, what a great man is this day fallen. <hi>Know ye not, that there is a Prince, and a great man fallen this day in</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>1. The cauſes moving <hi>David</hi> to publiſh this Proclamation, were <hi>v.</hi> 37. his Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to clear him in the face of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that he had no hand in ſpilling this innocent blood, finding no fault in the man, of thoſe things whereof others accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, as <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid of Chriſt, although with a better mind, <hi>Lu.</hi> 23. 14.</p>
            <p>2ly. To make <hi>Joab</hi> the more odious to the people for executing ſuch a raſh, and malicious, and unnatural fact. As <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> is ſtigmatized with this brand-mark, lying in his Grave, <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin; and as <hi>Judas</hi> the Traytor with this, <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi> who betrayed his Maſter. So <hi>Joab</hi> hath this ſpot and blot upon his Coat of Arms, to be ſeen &amp; read of all ages: <hi>Joab</hi> that in the time of peace ſlew <hi>Abner</hi> in the Gate, <hi>v.</hi> 27. And for this <hi>David,</hi> and let all <hi>Iſrael</hi> curſe him in the words, <hi>verſe</hi> 29. <hi>Let the blood of</hi> Abner <hi>fall on the head of</hi> Joab, <hi>and on all his Fathers Houſe, that the Houſe of</hi> Joab <hi>be never without ſome that have running Iſſues, or Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:121429:14"/>
               <hi>or that leaneth on a ſtaff, or that doth fall on the ſword, or that lacketh bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3ly. That <hi>Joab</hi> by the ſight of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick mourning, and vent which the King and People gave to their full hearts, might be convinced of his ſin, and ſo brought to repentance. <hi>Know ye not</hi> (and thou <hi>Joab</hi> too) <hi>that there is a Prince, and a great man this day fallen in</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>The Obſervations from what hath been ſaid, are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. That great mens death, and Princes fall, ought to be lamented by all. This <hi>David</hi> confirms both by Precept and Example: and it is ſaid <hi>Praecepta ducunt, Exempla trahunt,</hi> Precepts do ſweetly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure, but examples do violently draw men to obedience. So that if the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be of force to work upon our hearts, and eyes, to weep with <hi>Jeremiah</hi> day and night, for our <hi>Abner;</hi> then look upon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Liſſen to his charge to all the people that were with him, verſ. 31, 32. <hi>Rent your clothes, and put on Sackcloth, and mourn before</hi> Abner, <hi>and King</hi> David <hi>himſelf followed the Beer: And the King lift up his voice and wept beſides the Sepulchre of</hi> Abner, <hi>and all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wept;</hi> and verſ. 33, 34. <hi>The King lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:121429:15"/>
               <hi>over</hi> Abner, <hi>and all the people wept again for him:</hi> As if ſuch a mans death can never be over-lamented. <hi>Know ye not,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid?</hi> as if no man ſhould be ignorant of this his duty to his Prince, to his Country. When <hi>Joſiah</hi> was buried, there was ſo great mone made for him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. 22. that it grew into a Proverb, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>Like the mourning of</hi> Hadadrimmon <hi>in the valley of</hi> Megiddon. Yea when <hi>Jacob,</hi> but a mean man (although father to a Prince) was buried, they made ſo great, ſuch an exceeding ſore lamentation for him, that when the Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, which dwelt in the land, ſaw the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>Gored A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad, They ſaid among them ſelves, Surely this is a great mourning unto the Egyptians,</hi> Gen. 50. 10, 11. Our <hi>Abner,</hi> our <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> our Prince, our great man is fallen, and why ſhould not we do likewiſe? as Chriſt told the Lawyer, <hi>Luke</hi> 10 37.</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe Princes are nurſing Fathers to their people, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 49. 23. <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queens thy nurſing Mothers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now with what a tender love, with what ſtrong affections? and with what vigilant care do Fathers &amp; mothers bear their ſons in their arms, and carrie them on their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121429:15"/>
ſhoulders? as is the Prophets phraſe. Chriſts commandement to the Diſciples of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, with the <hi>Herodians,</hi> was, <hi>reddere Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, quae ſunt Caeſaris,</hi> to give to <hi>Ceſar</hi> thoſe things which are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> Mat. 22. 22. and if we muſt do this to <hi>Ceſar</hi> a Paynim Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, then much more are we bound to give to Chriſtian Kings their due, and what thoſe things are, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 7. 1. Tribute. 2. Obedience. 3. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Firſt Tribute, for their care over us, and great charge in providing for us at home and abroad. Secondly, Obedience, as our Superiours. Thirdly, Honour, as our tender Fathers, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 12. ſo that I may invert Gods own words, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6. A ſon honoureth his father, and a ſervant his Maſter? If they be your fathers, where is their Honour? Surely they are baſtards, and not ſons, that will not honour their fathers, I and ſuch carefull fathers, who wake whiles we ſleep ſoundly, and watch, like <hi>Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> whilſt we ſport our ſelves, and take care for us, when we little dream of their care. The <hi>Chronicles</hi> ſpeak of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, who being ſick and in a trance, that his ſon and heir <hi>Henry</hi> the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> took his Crown from his beds head, and tried how it would fit his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121429:16"/>
own; but his father recovering himſelf, and awaking, and miſſing of it, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the matter, told him, Ah ſon, didſt thou but know how full of cares the Crown is, thou wouldſt not be ſo greedy of it. And it is written of <hi>Eutrapiles,</hi> that his cuſtome was to prefer thoſe to honour and riches whom he moſt hated; thereby to fill their hearts and heads with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cares and vexations, there being more gall than hony in them<hi>:</hi> ſo that as one ſpake worthily of a Biſhop, <hi>Epiſcopatus nomen est laboris non honoris,</hi> the name of a Biſhop ſounds more of labour than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, unto which alludes that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>This is a true ſaying, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man deſire the Office of a Biſhop, he deſireth a worthy work:</hi> Even ſo the Office of a King or Prince, ſpeaks not ſo much his ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity or glory, as his activity for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good; and if this were well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in wiſdomes ballance, Can any Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be ſo unnatural, as not to lament the loſſe of ſuch a father? <hi>Certes,</hi> He that hath not a tear, nay many tears for his fall, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers his foul diſpoſition, and that he hath ſucked unnatural milk (like <hi>Rhemus</hi> and <hi>Romulus)</hi> of whom Hiſtory makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121429:16"/>
that they were nouriſhed up by a ſhe-Wolf. <hi>Know ye not, that a Prince, agreat man, Pater Patriae,</hi> a father of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, a Martyr for his Countrey, is fallen? and do not the <hi>Lamentations</hi> of <hi>Jeremy</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter become us, than the <hi>Canticles</hi> of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon?</hi> Do not <hi>Heraclitus</hi> his tears ſuis better <hi>(huic diei)</hi> to this day, than <hi>Democritus</hi> his laughter? Laugh that will (thinks <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid)</hi> But I will weep till I can weep no more.</p>
            <p>2ly. Becauſe Princes are the Miniſters of God for our wealth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4. <hi>They are as Shepherds over the flock of Chriſt,</hi> Num. 27. 17. <hi>They are as Bucklers and ſhields unto the people,</hi> Pſal. 47. 9. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder whoſe ſhadowing boughs our neſts are built,</hi> Ezech. 31. 3, 6. They are as watchmen over a City, as the foundation to an houſe, as the walls to a Vineyard, as Pilots to a ſhip, and as the Chariots and horſemen of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Now if the Watchman ſleepeth, the foundation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayeth, the walls be broken down, the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot dieth, and the Chariots and horſemen be ſnatched and taken away, hath not the City, the houſe, the ſhip, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> that is in it, great cauſe to ſcreek and ſcream, and roar, and blubber their cheeks with tears, for ſuch a loſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121429:17"/>
3ly. Becauſe if the Title of father, which is an amiable Title, or Miniſter, which is a ſerviceable Title, cannot draw water out of the hard rock in <hi>Horeb,</hi> and your ſtony hearts, then lo they are called angels, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 17. and the ſons of God, which are Titles of honour indeed, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 82. 6. to be the ſon of God is the nobleſt Pedigree in the world: to be as the Angels of God, is the higheſt promotion in heaven, and of them it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>Are they not all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter for their ſakes which ſhall be heirs of ſalvation?</hi> I read of divers properties of Angels, which may allude to good Kings.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Dirigere gradientes,</hi> To guide and direct men in the right way, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 20. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I ſend mine Angel before thee, to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee to the place which I have appointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly, <hi>Confortare deficientes,</hi> To comfort the broken hearted, and to relieve thoſe that are in want. <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 17, 19. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God called unto <hi>Hagar</hi> in diſtreſſe, and ſhewed her a well of water, whereby ſhe and her child were preſerved from death, and 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 29. 5, 6. The Angel of God brought bread and water to nouriſh <hi>Elija<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in his diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121429:17"/>
3ly, <hi>Flagellare praevaricantes,</hi> To ſcourge thoſe that do amiſſe: thus the Angel of the Lord ſmote in the Camp of the <hi>Aſsyrians,</hi> one hundred fourſcore and five thouſand in one night, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 35. and 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 3. 26. We find how <hi>Heliodorus</hi> was beaten with ſore ſtripes for robbing the Temple, that at his return he certified his Maſter, that if he had an enemy traytor, he ſhould ſend him to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and from thence he ſhould receive him well ſcourged, if he eſcaped with his life. <hi>Cautiores exemplo vos.</hi> If one Angel of God could do ſuch execution upon malefactors, how ſhould ye be afraid to do any thing to grieve him, when he hath mo than twelve legions of Angels to fight his battels againſt offendors? <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 53.</p>
            <p>4ly, <hi>Gratificare orantes,</hi> To offer up the prayers of the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. 3.</p>
            <p>5ly, <hi>Juvare certantes,</hi> To give aid to the ſervants of the living God againſt their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; and ſo when the Aramites compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Samaria</hi> with a great hoſt, and the Prophets ſervant was at his wits end, not knowing what to do, or whither to turn him, preſently at <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s prayer his eyes were opened, and he looked and beheld the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121429:18"/>
mountain was full of horſes and Chariots, round about <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2 Kings 6. 17. Here ye have heard of the office of Angels for the good of man, eſpecially for them that fear God, and Kings with Princes were ordained to the like purpoſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> by godly example, good Laws, and faithfull labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the Goſpel under them, to lighten men to <hi>Canaan</hi> above, for</p>
            <q>Regis ad exemplum totu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> componitur orbis.</q>
            <p>2ly, To relieve thoſe that are in want, Thus the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners to fling out money to the poor. 3ly, The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4. <hi>They bear not the ſword for nought; for they are the Ministers of God to take vengeance on them that do evil,</hi> 4ly, Righteous lips are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Kings, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 13. and ſo ſtand in the gap, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> between God and his people, to make their atonement for them. 5ly, To vindicate the cauſe of the innocent from the oppreſſour, and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers. To this effect ſpeaks <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 29. <hi>A King that judgeth the poor in truth, his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever,</hi> and <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. 28. and for this light to be put out and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121429:18"/>
extinguiſhed, this oyl to be poured on the ground, this ſword to ruſt, this innocency to be ſmothered in duſt and aſhes, this judge of the poor, fatherleſſe and widow, to be condemned, and this Angel to fall, Let us not any more cry out with the woman of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> 2 Sam. 14. 4. <hi>Help O King,</hi> but help O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for a Prince, and a great man is fallen this day in thee O <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4ly. Becauſe people without a Prince, are like thoſe <hi>Acephali,</hi> a body without a head, and ſheep without a ſhepherd, as Orphans Fatherleſſe, as Servants without a Maſter, as the world without a Sun. If the eye or head be cut off, ſurely the body will periſh. If there be no ſhepherd, the ſheep lie open to ſpoil by the greedy wolf and Jeſuite. If the world loſeth his Sun, all things wither to nought; and if the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant be robbed of his Maſter that feeds him fully, cloths him richly, and rewards him liberally, can their ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s be dry to think of their loſſe? <hi>Magis c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rendo quam fruendo,</hi> The Sheep, the Servant, the body will know and feel their miſery ſooner by the want of their Prince, than they were ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their own happineſſe in him. Had I wiſt will not ſerve turn, to ſay they were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121429:19"/>
deceived, to ſay they were not ſenſible of <hi>Joab</hi>'s juggle, will not avail them in the day of wrath, no more than their unjuſt gotten riches ſince, by <hi>Abners</hi> fall, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11. 4. And ſeeing one Prince, one great man will not be ſuffered to reign over them, as they in the Goſpel ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 14. How juſt will it be with God, as the wiſe man ſpeaks, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 2. <hi>For the tranſgreſsion of the Land, many ſhould be the Princes thereof,</hi> whoſe leaſt finger ſhould be heavier than the others loins, as <hi>Rehoboam</hi> told the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites;</hi> and for gentle rods they ſhould be chaſtiſed with ſcourges, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 14.</p>
            <p>5ly. Princes ſeldom fall alone, but their Lord-like Train will as well follow them to the grave, as to the palace. If the tree be ſtubbed up at the root, the top branches muſt fall with it; the Lord avert this ſad preſage, if it be his bleſſed will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> Is for our Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>1. To lament over, and for our <hi>Abner.</hi> As the <hi>Turks</hi> have a Proverb unto this day, when they would expreſſe their grief, in the privation of any comfort, Great ſuch a one is dead, as if all their hopes were bedded with him, and all their joyes were nipped in the bud. And as <hi>Phinehas</hi> his wife hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121429:19"/>
that the Ark of God was taken, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 21. preſently fell into travel, calling hir Sons name <hi>Ichabod,</hi> for ſaith ſhe, <hi>The glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael. Even ſo, every true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> may ſpeak, <hi>Ichabod,</hi> our glory is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from us. <hi>Abner</hi> is fallen, great <hi>Abner,</hi> and not more great than good; Of whom it may be ſaid, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 41. 38. <hi>Can we find ſuch a man as this?</hi> and yet this <hi>Abner,</hi> this great man is fallen: the Lord be good unto our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> falls not preſently after him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If your <hi>Abner</hi> were ſo great, ſo good, why did not God ſuffer him to grow to a good old age, as he once promiſed <hi>Abraham? Gen.</hi> 15. 15. Nay, why did God ſuffer <hi>Joab</hi> to mow him down like graſſe, before his eye was ſatisfied with ſeeing, his ear with hearing, and his heart with luſting? <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 1. 8. Ah certainly, <hi>latet anguis ſub herba,</hi> there was ſome Pad hidden under this ſtraw, Some <hi>Achans</hi> wedge of gold, Some abominable execrable thing in him, that God brought him down ſo ſuddenly, ſo wonderfully, as it is ſaid of <hi>Jeruſalem, Lam.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is not for duſt and aſhes to enter into, <hi>arcana Dei,</hi> Gods ſecrets, or dive into Gods Cabinet counſel, leſt whilſt we ſeek
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121429:20"/>
to know thoſe things that are not revealed' we ſind not the comfort of thoſe things that are reveiled. It was wittily anſwered by one that was asked what God did before he made the World: makes this reply, He made Hell. for ſuch curious Inquiſitors as thou art; <hi>quae ſupra nos, nihil ad nos,</hi> thoſe things that are above our ſphere, belong not unto us to ſearch into: Peeviſh curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in man below, is deteſted by God above. As the Maſter of the houſe ſaid to his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. 14. So I ſpeak to thee, Friend, take that which is thine own, and go thy way, and let the reſt alone.</p>
            <p>2ly, Who art thou O man that conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt againſt God, or pleadeſt with God? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 20. Wilt thou take Gods glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and give it to another? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 8. Wilt thou wreſt the ſword out of the Lords hand, and maintain juſtice in thine own? Shew me thy warrant from Heaven for this? Shew me any Law of God, or any Law of man for this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 3. 33. Did not the Lord command <hi>Saul</hi> to ſmite <hi>Agag</hi> King of the Amalekites? and when <hi>Saul</hi> had ſpared his life, did not <hi>Samuel</hi> hew him into pieces?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:121429:20"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But our <hi>Abner</hi> was no <hi>Agag,</hi> our <hi>Joab</hi> no <hi>Samuel,</hi> and ſo I proceed.</p>
            <p>3ly, <hi>Iſa</hi> 57. 1. <hi>The righteous periſheth, and no man conſidereth it in heart, and merciful men</hi> (and Kings too) <hi>are taken away, and no man under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4ly, God might ſuffer <hi>Abner</hi> to fall for the greater aggravation of <hi>Joab</hi>'s condemnation.</p>
            <p>5ly, Suppoſe our <hi>Abner,</hi> our Prince, our great man, had ſin in him, as there is no man that ſinneth not, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 Kings 8. 46. and to the like effect ſpeaks <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. 8. yet Religion, yet Charity thinketh no evil, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. that he was not guilty of ſo ſoul a crime, that nothing could expiate his ſin, but his Fall.</p>
            <p>2ly, It teacheth us, that it is a great ſhame for any of our eyes to be dry in ſuch a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral loſſe, and publik calamity. <hi>Jacob</hi> wept and mourned for his <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and would not be comforted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. 35. how much more cauſe have we to mourn for the loſſe of our father, our nurſing father? It is obſerved, that the love of Parents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends and flows, with a greater ſtream to their children, than childrens love aſcends upwards to their Parents, and this God
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121429:21"/>
ſhews, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49. 15. <hi>Can a father forget his child, or a woman not have compaſsion on the ſon of her womb?</hi> but he ſaith not, Can a child forget his father? as if that were too frequent, too common, and lay at every mans door: but <hi>ſpero meliora de vobis,</hi> I hope better things of you, and that ye have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better things, and your duty better, than to ſet light by your father, <hi>Deut.</hi> 67. 16. We take much notice of thoſe whoſe conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſo ſeared, and hearts hardened, that have not a tear at their fathers grave; and God and angels will take notice of us for ſtupidity and blockiſhneſſe, if we will not weep for our <hi>Abner,</hi> our Prince and great man that is fallen.</p>
            <p>3ly, If prayers and Supplications ought to be made for all men, but eſpecially for Kings and all that are in authority, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1. then conſequently it muſt follow, that their deaths ought to be lamented more than other mens, and if ſo, then</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Is for reproof.</p>
            <p>1. If thoſe that rejoice and glory in their ſhame, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 19. whoſe end without great Repentance will be their damnation. One boaſteth that he ſubſcribed to the lions death, another that he tried the lion, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121429:21"/>
that he ſentenced the lions damme, another that he ſlew the lion, another that he ſhared of the lions skin; but if there be a <hi>wo unto them that ſpeak good of evil, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of good, which put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for ſowre,</hi> Iſa. 5. 20. then as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, Brethren in iniquity,</hi> Gen. 49. 6. <hi>Let not my ſoul enter into their ſecret, and my glory be not joyned with their Aſſembly; for an horrible curſe and wo, like the ſin of Cain, lieth at their door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly, Of thoſe that had the leaſt hand in, or approved of <hi>Abners</hi> fall. Certes many men with <hi>Pilate,</hi> will ſeem to waſh their hands clean from his blood, becauſe they were no principal actors in it, but <hi>qui non vetat peccare, quum poteſt, iubet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, He that is not with me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is againſt me,</hi> or he that hinders not a foul fact, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of it, is as guilty as the principal in it. <hi>Abner</hi> is fallen, by whom and whoſe means? the ſcruple is reſolved, <hi>verſe</hi> 30. of this Chapter: ſo <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> his brother ſlew <hi>Abner, Abiſhai</hi> being privy to the murther, and not preventing it, is counted by the Spirit of God, as deep in blood, as the bloody executioner of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121429:22"/>
Treaſon, <hi>Joab</hi> himſelf; <hi>David</hi> killed not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> but the men of <hi>Rabbab:</hi> yet becauſe he plotted and conſpired againſt his life, and was well pleaſed with his death, <hi>Nathan</hi> tells him point-blank, and in plain terms, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12 9. <hi>Thou haſt killed</hi> Uriah <hi>the Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite with the ſword, and hast ſlain him with the ſword of the children of</hi> Ammon<hi>: Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſword ſhall never depart from thine houſe. Ahab</hi> was not acceſſary unto <hi>Naboth</hi>'s ſtoning, but his wife <hi>Jezabel,</hi> who made uſe of his Seal unto the Elders and Nobles that were in his City, that they might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of life and Vineyard<hi>:</hi> yet he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of what was done, and rejoycing in his ſpoil and prey that he had taken, <hi>Elijah</hi> the Tiſhbite meets him, and upbraids him of cruelty, covetouſneſſe, and blood, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 19. <hi>Haſt thon killed and alſo taken poſſeſsion? therefore in the place where dogs lick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the blood of</hi> Naboth, <hi>ſhall dogs even lick thy blood alſo.</hi> And in this ſence, <hi>Saul</hi> bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſad condition, and acknowledged his unworthineſſe and unfitneſſe to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel to the Gentiles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he perſecuted the Church of God, and had a hand in <hi>Stevens</hi> death, not as one that murthered him, as a cut-throat, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121429:22"/>
and applauded them that acted that villany, as his own words beſt ſpeak it, <hi>Acts</hi> 22. 20. <hi>Lord, when the blood of thy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> Steven <hi>was ſhed, I alſo ſtood by and conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his death, and kept the clothes of them that ſlew him.</hi> Now the Marginal Note ſaith, this is properly ſpoken, for <hi>Steven</hi> was mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered of a ſort of rude rakehels, not by order of Juſtice, but by open force, and he liking of what was done, and lulling, and ſpurring them forward unto it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts himſelf a chief inſtrument in the conſpiracy of robbing God of a Saint, the Church of a pillar, and the world of a bright ſhining light, which would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened them that fit in darkneſs to the true light, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 9. and ſo to the light of heaven. As the intruders into other mens Rectories plead for themſelves, that they thruſt them not out, when they are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to inherit their poſſeſſions, and eat up the bread that ſhould feed the right owners and their children, approving of the Sequeſtration: even ſo there be, that plead not guilty of <hi>Abners</hi> fall, when in their hearts they cryed <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucifige,</hi> let him die, and ſtroked the contrivers of his ruine: but how one or the other can anſwer their jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121429:23"/>
before God, who judgeth righteouſly, &amp; taketh the affection and will for the deed, I am ignorant, unleſſe it be with ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs, like to him that came to the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding feaſt without a wedding garment, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and ſo partake of his porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and bitter potion.</p>
            <p>3ly, Thoſe that reviled <hi>Abner</hi> living, and detract from him much more being fallen, their greateſt religion is ill byaſſed, which is to ſpeak evil of their Prince. He that is moſt foul mouthed like <hi>Shimei,</hi> is held fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to be a States-man, and have a hand in reformation. When <hi>Paul</hi> had called <hi>Ananias</hi> whited wall, and the ſtanders by check'd him for reviling Gods high Prieſt<hi>:</hi> he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged his errour, ſaying, <hi>I knew not that he was the High Priest, for it is written, thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the ruler of thy people,</hi> Acts 23. 5. from whence may be inferred, that to calumniate him is ſin.</p>
            <p>4ly, This highly reproves thoſe Servants of this Prince, this great man, that helped to pull him down. <hi>Gravior inimicus qui latet ſub pectore,</hi> a boſome enemie is of all the worſt. When <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſtabbed in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate houſe, and ſeeing <hi>Brutus</hi> acting his part amongſt the Conſpirators, it cut him to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121429:23"/>
heart, uſing theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what and thou too my ſon <hi>Brutus?</hi> then fall <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar:</hi> even ſo, for a Prince to bring up birds to pick out his own eyes, and breed vipers to ſting him to death, it cannot but much adde to the bitterneſſe of his fall, and this made <hi>David</hi> to complain ſo ſadly, Pſal. 41. 9. <hi>That his friend, his familiar friend, whom he truſted, which did eat of his bread, lifted up his heel againſt him:</hi> that is, like a wild horſe to kick at him, and trample him under his ſeet. Of all injuries there are none ſtick ſo near to a man, or go ſo near to his heart, as, <hi>bene facere, &amp; male audire,</hi> to do well, and to be rewarded ill, by a Servant, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ingratefull wretches. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his owner,</hi> Iſay 1. 3. and for a man not to know his maſter, and maker, is worſe than brutiſh: and deſerves <hi>nigro carbone notari,</hi> to be branded for a vile man indeed. A houſhold enemie is noted by Chriſt for a ſharp plague, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 36. and yet ſuch is our <hi>Abners</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to fall by ſuch. <hi>Joab, had Zimri peace that ſlew his Maſter?</hi> 2 Kin. 9. 31. then look for no peace living or dying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ. Occidit,</hi> is fallen; from whence may be obſerved, that death is no de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th to them that die in the Lord. It is but as a ſleep,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121429:24"/>
from which they ſhall be awakened at the ſound of the laſt Trumpet. And in this ſence ſaith Chriſt to his diſciples, John 11. 11. <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth, but I go to wake him up.</hi> It is but as a falling to the earth, from whence we through Gods might, recover our ſelves, and riſe again. It is but as <hi>(Requie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium)</hi> a Bed of reſt<hi>:</hi> as <hi>Iſay</hi> ſhews, 57. 2 <hi>They ſhall reſt in their Beds, every one that walketh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him:</hi> and men go not to bed to lie there for ever, but ſome ſhort time. It was ſaid by a Jeſter unto a great man, If I fall, I can riſe again, but if thou falleſt, thou wilt never riſe more; but this holds true of the faithfull in general, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. they ſhall riſe to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life; thus <hi>David</hi> tells not his ſervants, A Prince or a great man is dead, but is fallen, being aſſured that he ſhould riſe again (like <hi>Antheus)</hi> with greater ſtrength, and courage, and honour, and glory, than ever he enjoyed before, like <hi>Damaſcens</hi> wiſe, yet depoſed King, as we read of in M. <hi>Bunnyes</hi> reſolutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> Here is comfort for <hi>Abners</hi> friends, that although his body is ſown in corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, yet it ſhall be raiſed in incorruption. If it be ſown in diſhonour, yet it ſhall be raiſed in glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 42, 43. that although he was conquered by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121429:24"/>
Treaſon, yet he is Conquerour over all his enemies, and greateſt Traytors, death, ſin, and Satan; that although he be fallen, yet he is mounted up aloft upon the wings of Cherubims and glorious angels, like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> into the boſome of his father; that although he be loſſe to them, yet their loſſe is his gain; for inſtead of war he finds peace, inſtead of ſorrow, joy unſpeakable, inſtead of vexation of ſpirit, <hi>The things which eye hath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, neither have entred into the heart of man,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 9. inſtead of a corruptible Crown, an incorruptible, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. 25. Inſtead of a Crown of thorns, a Crown of eaſe, inſtead of an earthly Kingdome, a Kingdome which endureth for ever, even the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and of Chriſt, inſtead of earthly treaſures, heavenly, inſtead of buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, reproaches, ſpittings in the face, kiſſes, with ſweet embracings; Inſtead of <hi>Apage, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,</hi> be gone, We will not have this man reign longer over us, welcome, and <hi>well done good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord,</hi> Matth. 25. 23. inſtead of the ſociety of beaſts, ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> fought withall at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the fellowſhip of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Saints and Angels. <hi>Iacob</hi> in his dream
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121429:25"/>
ſaw a Ladder, the foot thereof ſtood upon earth, but the top reached up to heaven, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28 12. and by this Ladder, our <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> our Prince (like an Angel of God) is aſcended up thither. Queſtion not this, O man, whoſoever thou art; for he was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, a living pattern of vertue and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to all. 1 For ſobriety; for who could detect him of drunkenneſſe? 2ly of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for who could blemiſh him of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe? <hi>Poſſe, &amp; nolle, nobile,</hi> What Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle by promotion, or bribes, or command cannot a great man ſcale? and not to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due it to his power and luſt, is Prince-like indeed. 3ly, Of Piety, Religion, being diligent in Prayer, ſincere in his devotions, and admirably attentive in hearing of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and that ſometimes in my eye. 4ly, Of knowledge and learning; witneſs his Book entituled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which few Biſhops with all their learning and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding could outrun, and witneſs his Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with the <hi>Scotch</hi> Miniſter, who ſhall be nameleſs, and whom he ſo foiled by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that whereas before he was his bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enemy in Pulpit, and out of it, he ſet forth unto the world his own recantation, and his Princes vindication to undeceive
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121429:25"/>
his people. 5ly, Of bounty and liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his followers, I, and to ſome ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and undeſerving followers. 6ly, Of patience; for after the example of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 23. <hi>Being reviled, he reviled not a-again:</hi> when he ſuffered, he threatned not, but committed it to him that judgeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly. 7ly, Of magnanimity; being as daring as a lion, as ſome of his own Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains can ſpeak, and would have proved it in red letters, (if he might have been ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) wrote with a pen of iron. 8ly, Of compaſſion; lamenting the loſſe of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as if their blood had been drawn from his own heart. <hi>Iulian</hi> honoured thoſe Souldiers that died in his war and ſervice, but he thoſe that died in the war againſt him. 9ly, Of affection to his wife; ſo that as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of the good woman, I may truly aver of him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. 29. <hi>Many hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands have done vertuouſly, but thou ſurmount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt them all.</hi> 1. For fidelity to her bed, a rare thing to be found in great men. 2. For affability and kindneſs to her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ving her as his own ſoul. 3 For indulgencie over his and her children. Now laying all theſe together, as ſo many ſteps or ſtairs, or ſtakes of the Ladder, doubtleſſe his works
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121429:26"/>
follow him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 13 and he is paſſed and gone to your father, and his father, to his God and your God. Wherefore comfort ye one another with theſe words, 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 4, 18. And as Chriſt ſaid to the daughters of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> Luke 23. 28 <hi>Weep not for him, but for your ſelves,</hi> left as a prey to the wolf, hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying and worrying Chriſts flock.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. <hi>Abner</hi> is fallen. As the Widow of <hi>Zarephath</hi> ſpake to <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. 18. <hi>O thou man of God, art thou come to call my ſins to remembrance, and to ſlay my ſon?</hi> Even ſo, <hi>Abners</hi> fall ſhould put Iſrael in mind of their ſins, which have pulled him down from his Throne, and of a ſudden Repentance, leſt they follow him to the grave. If old <hi>Eli</hi> was puniſhed for the iniquity of his ſons, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 12, 13, 14. then by the ſame rule, a Father of his Countrey may ſuffer for the wickedneſs of his children and people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Hoc die,</hi> This day; from whence I obſerve, that all men have their falling day, The Sun that now ſhines will ſet, the Moon that now is at Full will wain, the ſee that now flows will ebbe. After a Spring will follow an Autumn: after a Summer comes a hard Winter, and after the green blade comes a harveſt. Death thruſts in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121429:26"/>
his ſickle, and the faireſt corn falls to the ground. Wiſe men die, and alſo the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and fooliſh periſh together, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 10. <hi>I ſaid ye are gods, but ye ſhall die like men,</hi> and fall like others, 82. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory of man like the flower of the field, the graſſe withereth, the flower fadeth away,</hi> becauſe the Spirit of the Lord blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon it. Surely all fleſh is graſſe, <hi>omnis Caro,</hi> all fleſh, the fleſh of Princes and great men, ſo well as of the Peaſant and begger. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27. <hi>Decretum eſt omnibus mori,</hi> There is an appointed time for all men to die. All the ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> have had their day. <hi>Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Solemon, Sampſon,</hi> with our <hi>Abner. Know ye not that there is a Prince and a great man fallen this day in</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If God bounds mans life to an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, to a day, then <hi>Ioab</hi> ſeems to fulfill the good pleaſure of God, in giving a full period to <hi>Abners</hi> life: he was but as the <hi>Atropos</hi> to cut the threed of his morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity aſunder, and ſo how could this be ſaid to be ſin in him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Cain</hi> might plead the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in murthering of his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> but how diſpleaſing it was to the moſt high, let
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121429:27"/>
his puniſhment, let his yellings and roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings witneſſe to the world.</p>
            <p>2ly, Although mans appointed time be known to God, yet it is unknown to man: ſo he is called <hi>Palmoni,</hi> which ſignifies a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret number, becauſe he knoweth the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our dayes, which is ſecret and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to us; for as Chriſt ſpake of the end of the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 36. ſo may I ſpeak in this kind, <hi>Of that day and hour knoweth no man:</hi> And ſo it muſt needs follow, that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab's</hi> wickedneſſe was <hi>Monſtrum, horrendum,</hi> moſt hainous and deteſtable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. All men have their falling day. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings, be learned ye Iudges of the earth, ſerve the Lord in fear. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riunt ceiſos fulmina montes,</hi> the higher ye are, the more tickliſh ye ſtand, and the more ready ye are to fall<hi>:</hi> ye ſtand upon ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry places, and are ſuddenly caſt down, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed and periſhed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 18, 19. <hi>Quem dies videt veniens ſuperbum, hunc dies fugiens videt jacentem.</hi> Whom the morning behold ſwelling and ſtrutting like the proud Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, the Evening beheld wallowing in his own blood and gore. <hi>Know ye not that a Prince is fallen this day?</hi> The day of great men is no longer than the poor mans day;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121429:27"/>
and therefore it will be their greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and wiſdome to work out their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whilſt it is day, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 12. Heb. 3. 13. <hi>For the night cometh, when no man can work,</hi> John 9. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Here is inſtruction for inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, to pray with <hi>Moſes,</hi> Pſal. 90. 12. <hi>Lord teach us ſo to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdome,</hi> and there is no wiſdom like to that of looking well to the better part with <hi>Mary,</hi> and gaining of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. It is written of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, that a little pit held him after his death, whom the whole world could ſcarcely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain living, and ſo he was ſtill crowding for more elbow room, according to that of the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Pellaeo juveni vix ſufficit orbis.</q>
            <p>And of <hi>Franciſcus Borgia,</hi> ſeeing a little Tomb and Coffin to contain all the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory, power and magnificence of that great Empreſſe <hi>Auguſta,</hi> that he departed from her Funeral, ſaying, <hi>Mortem Auguſtae ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi vitam attuliſse,</hi> that her death ſhould give him life. Even ſo let the conſideration of the mortality of our bodies, quicken us, and put life into us, to labour for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121429:28"/>
of our ſouls in bliſſe. Let the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of <hi>ſic tranſit gloria mundi,</hi> all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory vaniſheth immediately like flax that is ſet on fire, as the Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies was wont to ſpeak to the Pope, the firſt day of his inauguration, mind us to ſeek after the things above, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1. which fade not nor fail not, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 33. It was the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine, neſcis qua hora veniet, vigila, ut quod neſcis quando veniet, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum te inveniat quum venerit: &amp; ad hoc for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te neſcis quando veniet, ut ſemper paratus ſis,</hi> the which I may interpret by our Saviours own words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 13. <hi>Ye know neither the day nor the hour when the Son of man will come: watch therefore,</hi> that when he cometh he may find you well-doing. And for this cauſe of that day and hour knoweth no man, that every man ſhould watch and be found a people ready prepared for the Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 17. and ſo enter into the Kingdome prepared for them from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the wotld, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 34. When <hi>Pharaoh, Abimelech, Siſera, Herod, Abner,</hi> leaſt dreamed of their fall, then their day was at an end: Let then <hi>Abolibah</hi> learn to be wiſe by the puniſhment laid upon her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Abolah,</hi> for what is ſpoke of <hi>Abner</hi> here,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121429:28"/>
will be verified of all in the ſame ſence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not words, <hi>Know ye not, that a Prince, and a great man is this day fallen in</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 4. In <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Gods Church is not free from ſpots. In Paradiſe there was a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtinging Serpent, in Chriſts boſome a <hi>Juda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> In the faireſt garden <hi>Later anguis ſub herba,</hi> will be ſome venemous creature. <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> was a nurſery of Religion and Prophets: It was the Lords peculiar treaſure, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 5. and Vine, and yet lo this treaſure hath a canker, this Vine a deadly Viper couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under her branches to ſting <hi>Abner</hi> unto death. <hi>Know ye not that a Prince, and a great man is fallen this day?</hi> How? By Treaſon. Where? In <hi>Iſrael.</hi> whom? By <hi>Joab.</hi> I might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my ſelf farther, but <hi>I</hi> will conclude all in a few words.</p>
            <p>The Alluſion.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Abner</hi> died when he leaſt thought of death: even ſo our Prince and great man, is pulled down to his grave in the flower and ſtrength of his years, when he leaſt thought of the turning of the Sun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ceſar</hi> being asked what death he would chooſe, anſwered, no lingring, but a ſudden death,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121429:29"/>
and this our Prince enjoyes, being alive, and dead in a moment; the breath of man can ſcarce pronounce ſo faſt, <hi>Est,</hi> but the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho anſwereth as faſt, <hi>Non est,</hi> he is fallen.</p>
            <p>2ly. <hi>Abner</hi> died a violent death: even ſo our Prince by unmercifull hands on every ſide is bereaved of his life; <hi>Gebal, Ammon</hi> and <hi>Amalech, Edom</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael, Moab</hi> and the <hi>Agarims,</hi> Jeſuites and Zamzummims, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. that is, a people, who called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Rephaims, preſervers or Phyſicians, to heal and reform vices, but played the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils to open a gap to let in all hereſie and abomination, and wickedneſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſſe, and covetouſneſs which is idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; Theſe all of them have taken crafty counſel againſt him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. 3. and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him, and dethroned him, and like <hi>Cannihals</hi> have devoured him.</p>
            <p>3ly. <hi>Abner</hi> was evil ſpoken of by <hi>Joab,</hi> and his innocency tainted and ſpotted by him, and his integrity and beſt meaning miſconſtrued and miſinterpreted, 24, 25. <hi>ver.</hi> Even ſo, our Prince, our great man, was calumniated and reproched in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by rude Souldiers, In the City by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Factious Schiſmaticks, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121429:29"/>
many pratling <hi>Diotrephe's.</hi> In the Countrey, by Copper-Smith <hi>Alexanders,</hi> and giddy-brained <hi>Athenians,</hi> ſtil longing to hear, and tell news, ſucking in all poiſon, and then ſpewing it out to the diſgrace of their Prince. This was Chriſts lot and portion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 3. to <hi>verſe</hi> 12. and certainly (how ever the world deem of it) that ſervant is highly honoured, that is admitted to drink of his Maſters cup. <hi>If they have done theſe things to the green tree,</hi> what may they not, <hi>will they not do to the dry?</hi> Luke 23. 31.</p>
            <p>4ly, <hi>Abners</hi> fall was lamented by all <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> unleſſe it were by curſed <hi>Joab,</hi> and his wicked brood, <hi>verſe</hi> 32. Even ſo our great mans ſubverſion did afford much lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our <hi>Rhama,</hi> where among the more godly and conſtant godly ones, there was weeping, and mourning and howling for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>Abner,</hi> for their Prince, becauſe he was not, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. 18. Perhaps there might be ſome greedy of prey might rejoice in his fall, that they might riſe and ſtep into his ſeat; but as Chriſt prayed for his malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, ſo pray I, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do,</hi> Luke 23. 34. That Crown muſt needs be dear bought, which is purchaſed with blood, and an ill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121429:30"/>
and the loſſe of a ſoul, as <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth ſold his ſoul to the Devil, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance him to be Pope. The <hi>Romans</hi> were wont to begin their Epicedies after the death of their Worthies, with <hi>Auguſtus mortuus est,</hi> the King is dead; the tidings of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> death made a Land flood over all <hi>Rome:</hi> And why ſhould not <hi>Abijahs</hi> ſad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of <hi>Princeps occidit,</hi> our Prince is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, turn our <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>Bochim,</hi> a valley of tears? Unleſſe we have eyes and will not ſee, and hearts that will not underſtand, the which was one of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s plagues, We never had more cauſe to pour out water before the Lord, than this day, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 6.</p>
            <p>5ly, <hi>Abner</hi> falling, <hi>Iſh-boſheth</hi> preſently fell, with thoſe adherents to them both, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 7. Even ſo, our Prince and great man falling, how many hundred Families that are bread at his Table, and were che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by our good <hi>Abner,</hi> were utterly rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? The Peers loſt the honour of their birthright, and ſome of them their lives. The Biſhops, Deans, Arch-Deacons, with the learned Clergy loſt their Livings, and Liberties. The Gentry their Eſtates; and have not all cauſe to cry out, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121429:30"/>
after <hi>Elijah,</hi> when he was taken up into heaven, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 12. <hi>My father, my father.</hi> What ſhall we do? as the ſervant of the man of God ſaid, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 15.</p>
            <p>6ly, <hi>Abner</hi> ſignifies the fathers Candle; and what he was by name, our Prince was by nature, a bright ſhining light and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, as it was ſaid of <hi>John Baptiſt, John</hi> 5. 35. and this Candle being put out, we muſt needs walk in <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is none of the leaſt plagues.</p>
            <p>7ly, <hi>Abner</hi> was gulled of his life under a colour of kindnes, <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>Joab</hi> pretended love, but intended murther. <hi>Mol in ore, verba la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis, fel in corde, fraus in factis,</hi> he had ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in his mouth, but gall in his heart, he ſpake to him peaceably, but ſtruck him to the heart. Even ſo our Prince was fed with golden promiſes, and <hi>Naphthalies</hi> goodly words, that they would make him the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Prince in Chriſtendom, if he would null Biſhops, Confirm the Parliament du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their own pleaſure, Reſign the <hi>Militia</hi> into their hands, which having obtained, and all they could ask, at laſt cut off his head with his own ſword, as <hi>David</hi> ſerved <hi>Goliah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 51. And ſo let us pray,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121429:31"/>
From the Crafty Counſel of <hi>Abithophel,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi>'s railing, &amp; <hi>Shimei</hi>'s curſing,</p>
            <p>From <hi>Iudas</hi>'s kiſſe, and <hi>Joab</hi>'s bloody hands, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all falſe Doctrine and Hereſie,</p>
            <p>From hardneſſe of heart and privy conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,</p>
            <p>From ſudden death and Jeſuitical cruelty, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:121429:31"/>
            <head>Abſaloms <hi>unnatural rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt his father.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">SERM. II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 Sam. 18. 33.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>And the King was moved, and went up to the chamber over the gate, and wept, and as he went, thus he ſaid, O my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſolom, <hi>I would God that I had died for thee,</hi> Abſolom <hi>my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>DIC mihi Muſa virnm,</hi> Tell me of any man (but the ſon of man) that ever was ſo ſoaked in ſorrows, and ſouſed in tears, as <hi>David</hi> was; his whole life ſeemed nothing elſe, (from the Cradle to the Grave) but a map of miſerie; the ground on
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121429:32"/>
which he ſtood, a red ſea of blood, or a wild wilderneſs, full of ſharp briars, and thorns, that pricked and peirced him, which way ſoever he moved; his diet, like <hi>Micai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs,</hi> 1 Kings 22. 27. Bread of affliction; and water of affliction, ſo that he ſaid truly of himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 6. <hi>I am like a Pellican in the wilderneſs,</hi> whoſe nature is to trickle down tears on her bill continually; and in this ſence ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 57. Man is born to ſore travell and trouble, as ſparks flie upward; and this ye ſhall find in the ſurvey of his life. 1. He was a ſhepherd, and he that follows that calling, <hi>duram ſervit ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem,</hi> ſerves an hard Apprentiſhip, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſpeaks and ſhews, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 40. <hi>I was in the day conſumed with heat, and with froſt in the night, and my sleep departed from mine eyes.</hi> 2ly. He was deſpiſed by <hi>Eliab</hi> his eldeſt brother, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 28. 3ly, He was defied by <hi>Goliah</hi> the Philiſtim, <hi>v.</hi> 42. 4ly, He was aſſaulted by a lion and a Bear, <hi>v</hi> 34. 5ly, He was perſecuted by <hi>Saul.</hi> 6ly, Deſpiſed by <hi>Michal</hi> his own wife. 7ly, He was betrayed by the Ziphims, <hi>chap.</hi> 23. 19. 8ly, He was envied by Philiſtims. 9ly, And in a word, to fill up the meaſure of his griefs, his own ſon, his boſome ſon, his <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſon, his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121429:32"/>
darling ſon ſeeks his life and Crown a once; and yet for this bird that would have picked out his eyes, this cuckoe that would have devoured his damme, that bred, and fed, and cockered him, he good man weeps, and in the midſt of his inundation, thus he ſaid, <hi>O my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>I would God that I had died for thee,</hi> Abſalom <hi>my ſon, my ſon.</hi> From whence we learn after his example,</p>
            <p>Obſ. 1. <hi>To love our enemies, to bleſſe them that curſe us, to do good to them that hate us, and to pray for them which hurt us and perſecute us,</hi> Matth. 5. 44. for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 46, 47. <hi>If we love them which love us, what reward ſhall we have? Do not the Publicans even the ſame?</hi> Or if we be friendly to our brethren onely, what ſingular thing do we? Do not even ſinners likewiſe? but to be perfect even as our heavenly father is perfect, but with <hi>Steven</hi> to render good for evil, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 60. but with <hi>David</hi> to mourn and grieve for the loſſe of a Rebel ſon, <hi>Eſt hic labor, hoc opus,</hi> praiſe-worthy indeed, as it is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 3. and Chriſtian-like. I muſt confeſs with Chriſts diſciples, <hi>durus est hic ſerm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that this is a hard ſaying, but <hi>verus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> this is a true ſaying, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 15. for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121429:33"/>
we deny our ſelves, and as <hi>Abraham</hi> was commanded, <hi>exire de patria ſua,</hi> to go out of his Countrey, <hi>Gen</hi> 12. 1. ſo we go out of our ſelves, and caſt off fleſh and blood, we cannot go into Chriſt, or ever come where he is.</p>
            <p>Obſ. 2. <hi>That many are the troubles of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, Pſal.</hi> 34. 19. As the ſtones that were for <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, were ſawen and ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and endured many an hard knock, before they were fitted for that place, and their place<hi>:</hi> even ſo the godly muſt be ſawn with the Saw of Correction, and ſquared with the ax of tribulation, and ſuffer miſerie upon miſerie, before they can become lively ſtones of the ſpiritual buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, whereof Chriſt Jeſus is the head cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone. As the ground is rent under the Plough again, and again, and harrowed, and ſown, and endures many an hard froſt, and cold blaſt, and ſhowers, before the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt cometh<hi>:</hi> even ſo, this is the condition of Gods Holy Land, to be tilled, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, and tumbled about, and water-furrowed, but then comes the Harveſt, and the Wheat is gathered into his Garner, when the chaff is burned with unquencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 12. Afflictions, as it is ſaid
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121429:33"/>
of <hi>Gad,</hi> come by Troop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and as there were many Lepers, and many widows in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Elizeus;</hi> and as it was a mighty hoſt of the <hi>Aramites</hi> compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Samaria,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 14. even ſo the righteous, like the man of God, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with a mighty Hoſt, and Troops, and a multitude of calamities, yet nevertheleſs in all theſe things they are conquerours, through him that loveth them, ſaith <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8. 37. as if he had ſaid, theſe things come not to make us mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but conquerors, and the conqueror leaves alwayes the field with honour and triumph, and joy. <hi>Many are the troubles of the Righteous;</hi> Here is aſharp breakfaſt: but we muſt through many afflictions enter into the Kingdom of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnahas</hi> taught, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 22. there is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Supper and amends for all. I read of <hi>Jovinian</hi> the Emperor, that he had two ſorts of Wine in his Palace, the one ſweet, and the other ſowr, but he decreed, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would taſt of the ſweet, ſhould firſt taſt of the ſowr<hi>:</hi> Even ſo, <hi>Qui vult cum Christo conregnare in Regno Coelorum, debet cum Chriſto compati in valle lachrymarum,</hi> he that will reign with Chriſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121429:34"/>
of glory, muſt firſt ſuffer with Chriſt in this vale of tears, he muſt firſt take up his Croſſe, before he ſhall put on a Crown; Firſt drink Vineger, then Wine<hi>:</hi> he muſt firſt wear a Crown of thorns, and then a Crown of glory<hi>:</hi> and good reaſon for it; <hi>For the Diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant greater than his Lord, Mat.</hi> 10. 24. <hi>But it is enough for the diſciple to be as his Maſter, and the ſervant as his Lord,</hi> verſe 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. That although <hi>many are the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the righteous, yet the Lord is their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer out of them all:</hi> He is their City of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge to ſecure them from the hands of the avenger; he is their ſhield and buckler to defend them; he is that brazen ſerpent, unto which if they look and run, will preſerve them. <hi>Many are the troubles of the righteous,</hi> &amp; they have many as deliverers out of them all; for they that are with them &amp; for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are more than they that are againſt them, as the ſervant of the man of God can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 16. and in the multitude of the ſorrows which they have in their hearts, this is their comfort, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 50. that God is able to deliver them, as the three children ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 17. and pitcheth his Life-guard about them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 7. 91. 11<hi>:</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121429:34"/>
So that they may now ſing with the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124. <hi>If the Lord had not been on our ſide, (may</hi> Iſrael <hi>now ſay) if the Lord had not been on our ſide when men roſe up againſt us, they had then ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled againſt us.</hi> Then the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had drowned us, and the ſtream had gone over our ſoul, then had the ſwelling waters gone over our ſoul. <hi>Praiſed be the Lord which hath not given us as a prey to their teeth. Our ſoul is eſcaped, even as a bird out of the ſnare of the foulers, the ſnare is broken and we are delivered. Our help is in the name of the Lord which hath made heaven and earth.</hi> So that as Chriſt asked the adultereſs, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 10. <hi>Where are thine accuſers?</hi> and ſhe ſaid, they are gone; even ſo, if any ſhall demand, where are the troubles of the righteous? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may be made, they are vaniſhed like miſts at the riſing of the Sun; for the Lord ſcattered them, as he did the Army of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7. 6. Many were <hi>Iobs</hi> affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and as ſharp as any, but the Lord delivered him out of them all, and made his comforts at laſt to exceed his ſorrows at firſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 42. 12. <hi>David</hi> was a figure of Chriſt, and ſo was hedged about with the Croſſe. For 1. As Chriſt was contemned
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121429:35"/>
of his Country men, ſo was he of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. 2ly. As Chriſt fled into <hi>Aegypt</hi> to ſave his life: ſo <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Gath</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his. 3ly, As Chriſt was glad to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive food of women: ſo <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Abigail.</hi> 4ly, As <hi>Herod</hi> perſecuted Chriſt: ſo <hi>Saul, David.</hi> 5ly, As there was a wicked combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Prieſts, Elders, Scribes, Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, Jews, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt Chriſt: ſo the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims, Ammonites, Edomites and Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites were all againſt <hi>David.</hi> 6ly, As <hi>Iudas</hi> one of the twelve Diſciples, and Purſe-bearer to Chriſt, was one of his greateſt enemies: ſo <hi>Abſalom</hi> his own bowels was againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> but God delivered him out of his hands, and rendred the evil he conceived and plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt his father, into his own breaſt and boſom: and for grief thereof <hi>David</hi> ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed forth this heavy lamentation, <hi>O my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had died for thee,</hi> Abſalom <hi>my ſon, my ſon.</hi> In the Text conſider theſe 2 parties treated of,</p>
            <p>1. Of a moſt indulgent, affectionate, kind, and cockering father, that is, King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid; And the King was moved,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2ly, Of an unnatural, unkind, unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ungracious ſon, more cruel than the ſavage Tygre againſt his Sire, and that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121429:35"/>
is <hi>Abſalom,</hi> a King new erected, but is pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of his ſeat before he was fledge, from whence we learn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. Soon ripe, ſoon rotten, as we uſe to ſay, <hi>Ionah</hi>'s Gourd ſprang up ſuddenly in a night, and withered the next<hi>:</hi> even ſo, <hi>Iſrael</hi> had no ſooner proclaimed <hi>Abſalom</hi> King, but the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> mar his pride and depoſe him; and herein is Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe fulfilled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 23. <hi>The bloody and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful men ſhall not live out half their dayes,</hi> And ſo as <hi>Cuſhi</hi> ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 32. <hi>Let all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord my King, and all that riſe up againſt him be as that young man</hi> Abſalom <hi>is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. The ſin of Patricide, even in the very heart, is a monſtrous, abominable and deteſtable ſin to God and man; for the will ſtands for the deed with God. <hi>Fecit quod potuit,</hi> as Chriſt of <hi>Mary Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> goes for current execution. A <hi>Roman</hi> being asked, why amongſt all their good Laws, there was none againſt killling of Parents; anſwered, that there was no true <hi>Roman</hi> ſo unnatural<hi>:</hi> but in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there was an unnatural child ſprung from a good ſtock, that ſeeks his fathers life. He that ſaid, <hi>Ecles.</hi> 10. 20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no, not in thy thought,</hi> ſurely commands <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:121429:36"/>
and every one, not to imagine the leaſt evil againſt his King, father. We ſay of ſome ungracious ſons, they are ſick of their father; and <hi>Abſalom</hi> was troubled with the ſame diſeaſe, but fell ſhort of his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the gallows giving him his full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and for this <hi>David</hi> wept, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>David</hi> let us conſider theſe two general parts.</p>
            <p>1. His Paſſion, <hi>And the King was moved, and went up to the Chamber over the gate, and wept, and as he went, thus be ſaid, O my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſolom.</p>
            <p>2ly, His compaſſion, <hi>Would God I had died for thee, O</hi> Abſalom <hi>my ſon, my ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Paſſion conſider with me theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>1. The force and violence of his paſſion; the which ſtruck him like a dart to the very heart, that he remained for the preſent ſenſeleſs and ſpeechleſs, like him that came to the Wedding-Feaſt without a Wedding garment, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 12. <hi>And the King was moved:</hi> Yea, the Original ſpeaks it much moved; <hi>Leves loquuntur curae, ingentes ſtupent,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> where the waters are ſhallow, there they are rough and murmure, when the deeps are ſmooth and ſilent; the tidings,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121429:36"/>
and like <hi>Ahijahs</hi> heavy tidings to the wife of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 1 Kings 14. 6. of his white boys <hi>Abſaloms</hi> death, overwhelmed his ſpirit, and amaſed his ſoul, as he ſpeaks, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 143. 4. that as if he had been ſmitten dumb, like <hi>Zacharias,</hi> he held his peace, like <hi>Aaron,</hi> when <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abiha,</hi> his ſonnes, were devoured with fire from the Lord. <hi>And the King was much moved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly. His breathing and reviving after his grievous paſſion, as if like <hi>Lazarus</hi> he had been awakened out of his grave, <hi>And he went up to the chamber over the gate and wept;</hi> wherein let us obſerve,</p>
            <p>1. His motion, <hi>And went,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2ly, His action, <hi>and wept.</hi> In the firſt conſider, 1. <hi>Terminum à quo, v.</hi> 24. 2ly, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum ad quem,</hi> as here.</p>
            <p>1. Whither he went; he went up to the chamber, not to frolick it, not to revel it, not to commit adultery as he had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for how ſhould he then make mirth? as it is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21. 10. but to faſt, and to weep, and to mourn, which was Gods call to him in that day, as it is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 12.</p>
            <p>2ly, The place where the chamber was, over the gate. The Kings firſt ſeat was below between the two gates, <hi>v.</hi> 24. a place very
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121429:37"/>
ſuitable to the condition he was in, and the news he received from <hi>Cuſhi:</hi> but then when he heard what God had done to him, he mounts upward.</p>
            <p>1. Either to make his peace with God, that had thus tried his heart and reins, and ſearched him to the quick, in cutting off his darling <hi>Abſalom,</hi> as he had cut off <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> the beloved husband of <hi>Bathſheba.</hi> or,</p>
            <p>2ly, That as he was a King, ſo he might not diſcover ſo much weakneſs in himſelf, that he who could govern a great people, could not guide and govern his own paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Thus as one ſaid, <hi>Difficilius eſt bene regnare quam vincere,</hi> It is a harder matter for a man to reign well, than to win all. Even ſo, <hi>ſeipſum vincere,</hi> for a man to overcome himſelf, and his unbrideled affections, is no eaſie task, although commendable; but how ever, if <hi>David</hi> cannot ſubdue them, yet he is unwilling the world ſhould take notice of his imbecillity, and therefore went up to the Chamber over the gate, or,</p>
            <p>3ly, He was a man of war, and was well acquainted with the bloody event; of war: and ſo as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſpake <hi>chap.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee,</hi> even ſo, for ſuch an one as he to be ſeen to melt for an outſide ſcar,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121429:37"/>
or wound, would have much blemiſhed and ſtained his honour<hi>:</hi> and therefore he weeps in ſecret for his <hi>Abſolom,</hi> as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did for the pride, and captivitie of the people, 13. 17. or,</p>
            <p>4ly. That the world ſhould not take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his too too carnal affection towards his dear Son. It is true, he was his joy, the apple of his eye, and he thought him of all the birds of the neſt the faireſt, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt. Yet in regard of his profeſſion of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, he was unwilling that any ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Carnality, (as in the beſt grain there lurks ſome chaff) and therefore he takes his Chamber to roar out to himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone his ſad grievance. <hi>O Abſolom my Son, my Son Abſolom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. As we have looked upon his motion, <hi>and went,</hi> &amp;c. ſo let us caſt an eye upon his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>and wept.</hi> If he had wept for the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Zion,</hi> or for his ſins, or that God did hide his face from him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30. 7. this had not been blamable<hi>:</hi> but for to weep for the loſſe of ſuch a Son, ſuch a Rebel and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and ſuch an unparalleld Caitiff, this is unexcuſable. From whence we learn,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. The beſt have their failings: for ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 Kin. 8. 46. <hi>There is no man that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121429:38"/>
               <hi>not, and the just man falleth ſeven times in a day.</hi> And ſo we ought to pity, ſupport, and comfort one another, Knowing whereof we are made, remembring that we are but duſt, as God hath compaſſion on us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> That the beſt meat may be our poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if not well Cooked: weeping is good in its own nature, but adulterous weeping ſpringing from carnalitie is ſtark naught. There are four-fold ſorts of tears, according to the ground on which the ſeed was ſowen.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Lacrymae doloris,</hi> grief tears.</item>
               <item>2ly. <hi>Lacrymae compaſſionis,</hi> fellow-feeling tears.</item>
               <item>3ly. <hi>Lacrymae paenitentiae,</hi> repenting tears.</item>
               <item>4ly. <hi>Lacrymae murmurationis,</hi> grumbling or murmuring tears. And ſo of theſe in order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. Grief tears, are thoſe which we ſhed every one in his private and particular croſs and affliction, when any evil befalls us, as we are never unfurniſhed of occaſions from the Cradle to the Grave. Low grounds are commonly moiſt and waterie. <hi>Man that is born of a woman is full of trouble, and miſerie,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job</hi> 14. 1. He comes into the world weeping. He goes forth weeping. He ſows
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121429:38"/>
in tears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. 5, 6. and his <hi>(Exitus)</hi> end is crying, like the <hi>Shunamites</hi> child. <hi>Moſes, in Cunabilis,</hi> in his ſwadling Clouts wept, <hi>Exo.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>Iſhmael, in Infantia,</hi> in his Childhood wept, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 17. <hi>Eſau, in juventute,</hi> in his youth wept, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 38. <hi>Jacob, in Senectute,</hi> wept, 37. 35. that we are little or no time free from mourning. All this ſhews, that as the Sea is alwaies boyling and moving, ſo ſorrow upon ſorrow follows as cloſe at the heels, as one wave purſueth another, and as <hi>Jobs</hi> ſad Meſſengers traced the other. So that in this reſpect we may ſay with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 8. 4. <hi>Quid est homo,</hi> what a miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is man?</p>
            <p>2ly. There are fellow-feeling tears, which is a ſympathizing in our Brethrens calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. As Chriſt our head ſuffers when the Members of his body ſuffer: and as it is in the natural body, <hi>If one Member ſuffer, all ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with it,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 26. As in a throng of people, one treads upon anothers foot, the which cauſeth him to cry out, <hi>Cur me cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as?</hi> why doſt thou tread upon me? The foot was hurt, and not the tongue, and yet the tongue complaineth, by reaſon of that ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſympathie and friend ſhip that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Members. Now as it is in the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121429:39"/>
myſtical body, and natural body, even ſo ſhould it be in the ſpiritual body, weeping for <hi>Joſephs</hi> afflictions ſo well as our own. St. <hi>Paul, Vas electionis,</hi> the choſen Veſſel, did not only by precept, but by pattern teach us our duty in this, 2 Cor. 11. 29. <hi>Is any weak, and I am not weak? who is offended, and I burn not? Brethren, be ye followers of him, and look on them which walk ſo, as ye have them for an enſample,</hi> Phil. 3. 17. Chriſt Jeſus did the like, for he appropriated all the miſchief done to the Church, as done to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Acts 9. 4. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> So that if ye will not be followers of <hi>Paul,</hi> nor of the Saints; <hi>Yet be followers of God as dear Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3ly. There are repenting tears, which are poured forth for our ſins, and for our own, and other mens puniſhments, and chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements by reaſon of them<hi>:</hi> for man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers for his ſins, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 39. If ſin breaks our head, tears lend us a plaiſter to heal where ſin hath wounded, and the more tears, the ſooner the cure is wrought. <hi>Mary Magdalen, Peccatrix,</hi> a ſinner, was ſo prodigal of them, that ſhe waſhed Chriſts feet with her tears; her ſins were many, and her tears did cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond to her ſins, and therefore her Lord
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121429:39"/>
did forgive her all her ſins, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 47. What a ſweet voice was it ſounded in the Palſie mans ears? Mat. 9. 2. <hi>Be of good comfort, thy ſins are forgiven thee.</hi> And that I might hear the like, (I ſpeak from my ſoul) let <hi>Ziba</hi> take all; and let me tell you, the readieſt courſe we can take to obtain remiſſion and forgiveneſſe, is to ſwim to God in a flood of tears, as the Ark was carried to mount <hi>Ararat</hi> upon the waters, where it reſted peaceably, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 4. This was the means which <hi>Peter</hi> uſed to make his atonement with his maſter, after his lying, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and forſwearing of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 75. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> He wept bitterly, and this courſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> took, when the Text tells us, that they poured out water before the Lord, that is, they wept abundantly for their ſins, they were as free of their tears as of water, their heads were full of water, and their eyes as a fountain of tears; they humbled themſelves very low, that God might receive them into favour again. And this was <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe, Pſal. 6. 6. <hi>I cauſe my bed every night to ſwim, I water my Couch with my tears.</hi> And then follows verſ. 8. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from me ye workers of Iniquitie: for the Lord hath heard the voice of my weeping.</hi> It
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121429:40"/>
was a ſweet ſaying of one, Never any came to Gods door weeping, that ever went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſorrowing. The <hi>Ninevites</hi> were a ſinful people, and there was wrath proclamed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and the execution thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced within 40. daies: yet upon their repenting tears, and crying mightily unto God, and turning from their evil waies, God repented of the evil that he had ſaid that he would do unto them, and he did it not, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3. 8, 10. And to this effect ſpeaks <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Oratio deum lenit, ſed lacryma angit: haec ungit, ſed illa pungit.</hi> Prayer is of great force and power with God, for what cannot a fervent praying man do? <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 16. but when tears accompany, and are joyned with prayer, then what can be denyed to ſuch a melting ſoul? The <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 22. and the Father of him that was poſſeſſed with a dumb Devil, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. 24. did both by crying, and tears, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tears, obtain their long wiſhed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and drew pity, and compaſſion, and a compaſſionate pity from Chriſt. In which reſpect, <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid, <hi>Vincunt inviſibilem, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant omnipotentem,</hi> they conquer him that is unconquerable, and bind the almighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God to yield to our requeſts, as we ſee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121429:40"/>
in <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. 28. And ſo ſweetly was it uttered, by a ſweet Divine: Repenting eyes are Cellars of Angels, and penitent tears their choiceſt wine, which the Savour of life perfumes, the taſt of grace ſweetneth, and the pureſt colours of returning innocencie highly beautifieth. And I would God, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, that our hearts were ſuch a <hi>Limbeck,</hi> evermore diſtilling ſo pure a Quinteſſence, drawn out from the weeds of our offences, by the fire of Contrition, that Heaven might mourn at the abſence of ſo precious a water, and earth lament the loſs of ſuch fruitfull ſhowers. We have all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and our ſins are many, and great, and a great many, and ſo we ought with Chriſt, Heb. 5. 7. <hi>to powr out ſtrong cries, and tears, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that is able to ſave us from death.</hi> Every one of us when we come to die, would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go to Heaven: but if we ſo intend in good earneſt, <hi>lacrymae paenitentiae,</hi> repenting tears muſt be our guide thither, as the ſtar was to the wiſe men, to bring them to Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
            <p>4ly. There are grumbling, murmuring, and muttering tears: the which are ſhed in diſcontent, that God ſhould lay this or that evil upon them, or rob them of their <hi>Izaak,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121429:41"/>
               <hi>Joſeph, Abſolom,</hi> joy, or delight of their heart, or pleaſure of their eyes, and of theſe the Sonnes and daughters of men, are more free than the reſt; but ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſay</hi> 45. 9. <hi>Wo to him that ſtriveth with his Maker: ſhall the clay ſay to him that faſhioneth, it, what makest thou? or ſhall man ſay to God, what doſt thou?</hi> O peace, peace O murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul, be whiſt, be ſilent, and murmur not, as ſome of them murmured, leſt thou be deſtroyed of the deſtroyer, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 10. peace, O murmuring ſoul, be dumb, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Lord hath done it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 9. David had tears of all ſorts. 1. He had grief tears for the loſſe of his darling <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> 2ly. He had fellow-feeling tears in his miſery, as knowing that ſo bad a life he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, could have no good end or death, and therefore he wiſheth that he had ſtood in his place, <hi>Would God I had died for thee, Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, my ſon, my ſon.</hi> 3ly. He had repenting tears, being aſſured that his own ſinne, ſo well as his ſons, haſtened him to the grave. 4ly. He had whining, murmuring tears, as may be gathered by his exceſſive impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and immoderate weeping. <hi>And the king was moved, and went up to the chamber over the gate and wept: and as he went, thus he ſaid, O</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:121429:41"/>
               <hi>my ſon Abſolom, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo I paſſe to the next particular in the firſt general point.</p>
            <p>3ly. The effect of his paſſion: <hi>and as he went, thus he ſaid;</hi> wherein let us conſider theſe two particulars,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Quod dixit,</hi> that he ſaid.</item>
               <item>2ly. <hi>Quid dixit,</hi> what he ſaid.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. The veſſel of his body was ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with grief, that if he had not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it vent, his heart would have burſt. But his own words beſt ſpeak it, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39. 3. <hi>Mine heart was hot within me, and while I was mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, the fire kindled, and I ſpake with my tongue. David</hi> was an expert and skilful Muſician, and here he ſheweth it. For, firſt he begins with ſtill Muſick: <hi>And the king was moved.</hi> Then he ſtrikes a note higher: <hi>And he went up to the chamber over the gate, and wept.</hi> 3ly. Then he played upon loud Muſick, and loud Cymbals: <hi>and as he went, thus he ſaid, O Abſalom, my ſon, my ſon Abſalom,</hi> and ſo I am fallen upon the next particular.</p>
            <p>2ly. What he ſaid. A man would have thought that <hi>David</hi> had more cauſe to bleſſe God for his great deliverance from the hands of his enemy, than to whine, and murmur, and weep, and hang down his head like a bull-ruſh: I, but thinks <hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:121429:42"/>
if he were mine enemy, yet he was, <hi>filius meus,</hi> my childe, my ſon. But if he were thy ſon, yet he was caſt into a wretched mould, like one of thoſe that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2, 3, 4, 5. A Lover of himſelf, proud, unthankful, diſobedient to parent, without natural affection, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate, fierce, no lover at all of them which are good, a traitor, heady, high-minded, having a ſhew of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof. I, But ſaith <hi>David,</hi> love covereth a multitude of faults, for he was <hi>filius meus dilectus in quo mihi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placui,</hi> my beloved ſon in whom I was well pleaſed. But if he were thy ſon, and thy beloved ſon, yet why ſhould'ſt thou caſt ſuch a pearl to ſuch a ſwine, and be more prodigal of thy love to him, than to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Adonijah,</hi> and the reſt of thy children, better deſerving? I but ſaith <hi>David,</hi> he was <hi>filius iſte meus,</hi> the prettieſt man that ever eye beheld, there was none in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> like him; and therefore I cannot but ſigh, and ſobb, and eccho forth this ſad lamentation for him, <hi>O Abſalom, my ſon, my ſon Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> From whence we learn,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. That love is blinde, according to that of the Poet,
<q>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:121429:42"/>
                  <l>Quiſquis amot ranam, ranam putat eſſe Dianam.</l>
                  <l>Quiſquis amat ſervam, ſervam putat eſſe Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vam.</l>
                  <l>Quiſquis amat luſcam, luſcam putat eſſe venuſtam</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> beheld his ſon with the eye of fleſh, and blood, but was blind to look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the deformities of his ſoul; his body was not ſo lovely as his ſoul was filthy, and therefore it was a wonder how good <hi>David</hi> ſhould ſo much forget himſelf, (who was a man after Gods own heart, and knew what God affected moſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 26.) to be tranſported with love to the outward man, not regarding how leprous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed the inward man was. Surely <hi>David</hi> for the preſent was not <hi>David,</hi> and as the Philoſopher told his old Concubine, ſo he might have ſaid of himſelf, <hi>Ego non ſum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> the which I may interpret by that which is ſaid of the Prodigal in his ranting and ruffling fit and humour, he was not himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. he was as blind as <hi>Bartimeus</hi> the Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: neither was this his caſe alone, but <hi>Adams;</hi> for he and his wife <hi>Hevab</hi> rejoiced exceedingly in their firſt-born child; but as for their ſecond, they called him <hi>Habel,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:121429:43"/>
which ſignifies vanity, as if he were lightly eſteemed of by them in competition to <hi>Cain:</hi> but whom they accepted, God rejected, and whom they rejected, God accepted; <hi>For God ſeeth not as man ſeeth; for man looketh on the outward appearance, but God looketh on the heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 7. And after the pattern of God himſelf. Parents ſhould love their children for their vertue and godlineſſe, more than for their painted outſide. <hi>Samuel</hi> was a good man and a Prophet, and he was enamoured with <hi>Eliabs</hi> feature and ſtature, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proportion of body, and ſaid, ſurely the Lords anointed is before him, <hi>v.</hi> 6. but how blind he was in judgement and affection, the Sequel ſheweth. For a father not to love his child, is unnatural; for a father to love his body more than his ſoul, is unchriſtian-like; for a father to over-love him, is not to love him, nor himſelf<hi>:</hi> for God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly croſſeth him in his inordinate love. <hi>David,</hi> render a reaſon why thou delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt in <hi>Abſalom</hi> more than in the reſt; wert thou taken with his goodly head of hair? Alas, that is a ſorrie excrement. Wert thou captivated with his fair face? Alas, that the Pox or age quickly defaceth. Wert thou raviſhed with his ſtraight body? Alas,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121429:43"/>
every wrinch decrepits it. Wert thou over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the luſtre and ſplendor of his eyes, as Chriſt was wounded with one of the eyes of his Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 9? Alas, they are haughty, and will ſoon wax dim, and ceaſe to look out at their Windows, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 3. Wert thou delighted in his legs? Alas, as God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 117. 10. <hi>So ſhouldeſt not thou take pleaſure in the legs of a man.</hi> Speak David, ſpeak, what was the object of thy love? and if thou canſt give no better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than theſe, ſurely, thy love to <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> was blind. Beware, leſt any of you (with the <hi>Aramites)</hi> be ſmitten with this blindneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. Carnal Paſſion breaks all bounds of reaſon, and true Religion. If God queſtion <hi>Jonah,</hi> chap. 4. 4. <hi>Doſt thou well to be angry?</hi> he will juſtifie himſelf, and ſtand it out, <hi>I do well to be angry to the death, v.</hi> 9. <hi>Jonah</hi> had pity on a Gourd, and yet he quarrels with God for having pity on <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> and ſhewing mercy to that City, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were ſix ſcore thouſand perſons, that could not diſcern between the right hand and the left. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> What was thy Gourd to a great, ſtately, and eminent City? What was thy Gourd to the treaſures in that City? What was thy Gourd to much cattel in that City? What
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121429:44"/>
was thy Gourd to the men, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in that City? truly but as a ſtraw to the Gold in <hi>Ophir.</hi> Here then paſſion makes thee to break the bounds of reaſon. ut to take one ſtep and meaſure more. What was thy Gourd to all the ſouls in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? and in having more compaſſion on that, than on them, thou breakeſt the bounds of true Religion. <hi>Job</hi> was a good man, an upright and juſt man, and as a lillie among thorns, and an apple-tree among the trees of the Foreſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 2, 3. yet being ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon the heart-vein, he quarrels with every thing ſtood in his way, and was in his eye, he falls out with his mother that conceived him, the midwife that helped to bring him into the world, the night, the light, the day, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. yea with God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. His diſtemper is ſo hot and virulent, and violent upon him, that no cords, or banks or bounds can hold him. <hi>David</hi> that did face a Lion, killed a Bear, conquer the huge Giant, and overcame all his enemies, was overcome and drunken with paſſion for the loſſe of his <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Hence we learn, what Babes, and Weaklings, and Striplings we are, if we looſe our hold from grace; for as by faith,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121429:44"/>
ſo by grace we ſtand, 2 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 1<hi>:</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>2ly, That it is not mans merit, but Gods free mercy ſaves him; <hi>For what is man, that he ſhould be mindfull of him, or the Son of man, that he ſhould regard him? Pſal.</hi> 8. 4. there is nothing in him, (if well canvaſſed) but repining and Rebellion againſt his Maker.</p>
            <p>3ly, That if <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz,</hi> the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and Horſemen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithful have ſuch ſhrewd faults, and foils, and falls, then how horribly and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten do the wicked ſhoot their ſharp arrows, even bitter words, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64. 3. againſt God for their croſſes?</p>
            <p>4ly, In all our afflictions, to follow God with our prayers to ſtrengthen us with ſtrength in our ſouls, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138. 3. that we may poſſeſſe our ſouls in patience, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 19. ſpeaking with <hi>Job</hi> 12. 0. <hi>What? ſhall we receive good from the hand of the Lord, and not evil? Bleſsed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. From <hi>Davids</hi> wonderfull love to his ſon, we gather that Gods love to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren is unmatchable. As 'twas ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 33. <hi>Who can declare his generation?</hi> ſo I may ſpeak in this kind, Who can declare his love to man? Let us take a ſurvey of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far of, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and we ſhall
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121429:45"/>
but admire it, and with <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 17. 6. wonder with admiration.</p>
            <p>1. If we look into his firſt frame; he was created after the image of God, according to his likeneſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 27. and this was a moſt glorious condition, like that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 9. which the tongue of man is not able to expreſſe, nor the heart to conceive of.</p>
            <p>2ly, He delivered into his hand the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over all fiſh, and beaſts, and all fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fowls, and all things, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 28. He was ſole Monarch, and commander in chief of the whole world; there was none could hurt him, till he hurt himſelf by ſin; ſo that like <hi>Iſrael, Hoſ.</hi> 13. 9. <hi>Perditio ſua de ſe,</hi> his deſtruction was from himſelf.</p>
            <p>3ly, After his fall, he raiſeth him again with the promiſed Meſſiah, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. which was a ſure token of his love, to ſend the ſon of his love to pay his debt for him, by cancelling his Obligation, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
            <p>4ly, In Chriſt, to bind up his ſoul in the bundle of life: So that now thou mayeſt ſpeak, <hi>Why art thou ſo heavy O my ſoul, why art thou diſquieted within me? Pſal.</hi> 42. 5. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lamb of God, that taketh away the ſins of the world,</hi> John 1 29.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:121429:45"/>
5ly, That he takes notice of his name, as he did know <hi>Moſes</hi> by his name, and moreover write his name in the Book of Life, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 3.</p>
            <p>6ly, If We look lower, his love is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to mans body; for it ſhall be clothed with glory; <hi>For when Chriſt which is our life ſhall appear, then ſhall we all appear with him in glory,</hi> Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 4.</p>
            <p>7ly, If we look yet lower, his love is ſeen in the bones of man, that he ſhould keep them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 20.</p>
            <p>8ly, If we look yet lower, upon <hi>(partes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementitias)</hi> his excrementitial parts, his love to man is highly diſcovered, as 1. In num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of the hairs of his head, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 30. 2ly, In not ſuffering any of them toperiſh, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 18. 3ly, In treaſuring up our tears in a bottle, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 56. 8. and in regiſtring of them. 4ly, In wiping away all tears from all faces, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 8.</p>
            <p>9ly, In preſerving him in his going out and coming in, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. 8. and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing all his paths, and lying down, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 3. and directing his paths, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> 3. 6.</p>
            <p>1. When man goeth out, he may never come in more; when he comes in, he may
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121429:46"/>
never lie down, or go to bed more; when he goeth to bed, he may never riſe more, as we have plentiful examples of each: Now what a good God have we, that underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to be our Nurſe and Keeper, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver from all evil? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. 7.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Paul may plant, and Apollo water,</hi> and man may eat the bread of carefulneſſe, riſing early, and going to bed late, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127. 2. but unleſs God directs him, &amp; bleſſeth him, he laboureth but in vain, and ſpendeth his ſtrength in vain, like <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 4. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let it be his wiſdome when he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any buſineſſe, or enterpriſeth any thing, to call upon God by Prayer, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him, direct him, and proſper him, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 12. and then without all doubt, he will make thee as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull as him.</p>
            <p>10ly, In giving entertainment to the ſighs and ſobs of a troubled ſpirit. <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not grone, but God heard it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. 24. As the ſin of the old world; ſo the ſighs of the afflicted aſcend up to heaven, and come before God, and are ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accepted, that he ſets a mark on ſuch as mourn for the abominations of the times, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19. 4. and their own miſeries; ſo that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121429:46"/>
we may cry out with <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 11. 33. oh the deepneſs of the riches of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to man. As for the Application, I will refer it to the next point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 4. From the conſideration of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> love to his rebellious and wicked ſon <hi>Abſalom,</hi> I obſerve, That much greater is Gods love to poor ſinners. Hear God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf pleading the caſe or cauſe between him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> The people were bent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. 7. that is, ſet on miſchief, not caring what they did, nor how they provoked him to anger. Now God at laſt is awakened, like a Giant out of wine, with the crie of their ſins; and ſeems to deliberate the matter in theſe words, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up,</hi> Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im? <hi>How ſhall I deliver thee,</hi> Iſrael? <hi>How ſhall I make thee, as</hi> Admah? <hi>How ſhall I ſet thee, as</hi> Zeboim? <hi>mine heart is turned with in me, my repentings are rouled together. I will not execute the fierceneſs of my wrath, I will not return to destroy</hi> Ephraim, <hi>for I am God and not man;</hi> and again, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 20. <hi>Is</hi> Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im <hi>my dear ſon, or pleaſant childe? yet ſince I ſpake unto him, I ſtill remembred him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my bowels are troubled for him; If will ſurely have compaſſion on him.</hi> If the words
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121429:47"/>
be well ſcanned, what love of any father can come near the love of our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? for how doth his heart mourn? how do his mercies over-look our iniquities? how are his bowels troubled? how are his repentingsrouled together? how doth he in the midſt of wrath remember mercy? how doth he a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter all his menacings and threatnings recall our frailties, and his own bleſſed, glorious, and ever renowned attribute (the mercifull God) And ſo ſpare us? <hi>heu quam bonus est deus, quam vilis homo?</hi> O How good is God to <hi>Iſrael?</hi> and how unworthy, and unthankfull, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient is <hi>Iſrael</hi> to this good God? and that we may the better bluſh and be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our ſelves and ſinfull courſes, let us look upon ſome branches of his Love, As,</p>
            <p>1. When we were deadly ſick, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could recover us, but the blood of his beloved and onely begotten Son, then he ſpared not his own Son, but gave him for us all to death, that we might live, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 32.</p>
            <p>2ly, The eminency of his Love ſhines the more clear, if we conſider the perſons upon whom he caſt and beſtowed his Love, and that was upon grievous ſinners, as the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121429:47"/>
Apoſtle ſhews, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 6. for Chriſt, when we were yet of no ſtrength, died for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</p>
            <p>3ly, The unworthineſs of the perſons is aggravated by their loathſome conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being <hi>à capite ad calcem,</hi> from the crown of the head to the ſoal of the foot, full of nothing but wounds and ſores, and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings full of putrified corruption, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Job</hi> in that condition was loathed by his own wife, and friends; and for the King of Kings to be enamoured on ſuch wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Lazaruſſes, Quantus amor?</hi> how great was his Love? The blind, and the halt, and the lame, the ſoul of <hi>David</hi> hated; and who but God, would but have done the like? and therefore the ſtronger tie, and bond to bind us to love him, <hi>Who hath ſo loved us,</hi> as it is, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
            <p>4ly, If our condition had been loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome by divine Providence, it had not been much to be wondered at, that he ſhould love deformed creatures of his own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; but when it came by our making, and marring by ſin, what he had made beautifull, this ſpeaks his goodneſſe indeed.</p>
            <p>5ly, Or for a good man one may die, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 7. but for an open and profeſſed, enemy
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121429:48"/>
who but <hi>David</hi> would die? <hi>Yet when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son,</hi> Rom. 5. 10. We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, and crucified, and killed the Lord of Life, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 15. and the Lord of Life layes down his life, to give us life; and is not this unheard-of love?</p>
            <p>6ly, His love is moſt apparent by the rich purchaſe and price he paid for us; <hi>For we were not redeemed with corruptible things, as ſilver and gold, but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb undefiled, and without ſpot,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 18. All the blood of Bulls and Goats in the world could not help us: but it muſt be the blood of the Lamb of God muſt purifie our conſciences from dead works, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14. and when this Lamb muſt be ſlain to ſave us ſinners, who can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his love to be very great?</p>
            <p>The uſes hereof are theſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. The bountifulneſs, and loving-kindeneſs of our heavenly Father towards us, ſhould lead us all unto repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 4. What could he have done for his vineyard, that he hath not done unto it? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 4. he hath planted it with the beſt plants; he hath watered it, and dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it, and pruned it, and hath beſtowed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121429:48"/>
much labour, and coſt about it, and love upon it, as the Dreſſer did upon the barren fig-tree, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 7, 8. He feeds us, he clothes us, and in a word, bleſſeth us with the bleſſings of his right hand, and of his left, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>And now O man, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee? Surely nothing, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to humble thy ſelf, and to turn from thy evil wayes, and to walk with thy God, Mic.</hi> 6. 8. So that as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>Naaman</hi> ſpake unto him, 2 <hi>King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 5. 13. <hi>If the Prophet had commanded thee ſome great matter, would'ſt thou not have done it? how much rather then, when he ſaith to thee, waſh and be clean?</hi> I ſpeak unto you, if God had required of you, your lands, treaſures, wives, husbands, yea, your <hi>Abſaloms,</hi> ye muſt have parted with them: but he ſoares not ſo high, but contents himſelf with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and that little is, to be grieved with our ſelves, for grieving him; to return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, that he may return unto us, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. 3. and to repent us of all our wickedneſs. He that will grudge God this, deſerves not to be owned for his childe. It was the ſaying of the man of God to the good <hi>Shunamite,</hi> 2 King. 4. 13.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121429:49"/>
               <hi>Behold, thou haſt had all this care for us, what ſhall we do now for thee?</hi> and of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 116. 12. <hi>Quid retribuam domino? What ſhall I render unto the Lord, for all his benefits?</hi> even ſo, let it be our meditation, what we ſhall do for God, that hath done ſuch great things for us? For <hi>where much is given, much is looked for,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 48. Let us then with the <hi>Samaritan</hi> leper, chap. 17. 15. return and praiſe God, and that not only in tongue or word, but in our deeds, and lives, and converſations. Mark the Apoſtles argument, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. <hi>yeare bought with a price,</hi> there is our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers love. Now the ſequel tells us what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on our part to perform; <hi>Glorifie God therefore in your bodies, and in your ſpirits</hi> A ſon honoreth his father, and a ſervant his maſter<hi>:</hi> If he be then our Father, let us honour him: If our maſter, let us fear him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Here is comfort, and Balm of <hi>Gilead</hi> to heal all that are wounded with their ſinnes; for if <hi>David</hi> could forget, and forgive (as we uſe to ſay) all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindeneſs, and wrongs done to him by his unnatural ſon <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and wiſh to die for him, who had as willingly die, as ſee him
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121429:49"/>
live; then out of all queſtion, God hath more yerning, melting, and tender bowels towards them that lie grovling on the earth for their failings. Can <hi>David</hi> ſoal a pardon to his ſon that ſtands up in defiance of him, abuſeth his wives and concubines, rebels, and takes armes to pull him out of his Throne by head and ears? and wil not our heavenly Father receive us to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when we ſhall ſubmit, lament and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail our errours and tranſgreſſions? weep and howl, and beg, and crave forgiveneſs? ſhall <hi>David</hi> look a ſquint, and a to ſide upon the faults of his childe, and only eye him as the fruit of his loins? and will not God caſt all our ſinnes into the bottom of the Sea, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. 19. and not look upon us in our ſelves, but in his Chriſt, in whom he is well pleaſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 17. and with us in him? <hi>Wherefore let us comfort one another in theſe words.</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Is for inſtruction.</p>
            <p>1. Are we ſo dear, ſo tender to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, as the very apple of his eye? <hi>Zech</hi> 2. 8. Doth he take all the wrongs, and appropriate all the injuries done to his ſons, as done to himſelf? <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 4. and ſhall we not beſtir us, when his name is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121429:50"/>
blaſphemed? his ſon reviled? and his word is had in deriſion, or trodden under foot? I read of the dumb Son of <hi>Creſus,</hi> ſeeing one ready to ſtab his Father, cries out, What villain, ſtab my Father? What wilt thon murther my Father? Even ſo, although we be ſilent at our own harms, yet we ſhould be grieved and mourn, and breath out indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt thoſe that highly diſhonour, and trample the blood of his dear ſon under foot, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 2. If we be not baſtards, but the true, Legitimate Sons of God, nothing ſhould affect us ſo much as when his glory ſuffers: like <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Phinehas,</hi> who will ſpare neither head nor tail in the Lords quarrel.</p>
            <p>2ly. This may teach all parents, after the pattern of <hi>David,</hi> to be like minded, and tender-hearted towards their Children. But many of you may ſeem to give me a ſtop, and a <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi> to treat of this, every one thinking his own bird faireſt, and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of it: but then do you not over-love them? for that is as bad a ſin as not to love them<hi>:</hi> and ſee how <hi>David</hi> was whipped for that. And moreover let me tell you, that I have known ſome Fathers as ſalvage, as cruel, as unkind, as unnatural
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121429:50"/>
to their Chickens of their own hatching, and more too, than the Dragons, and fierce Tigers, to their ſeed. Suppoſe they have offended, ſo did <hi>Abſolom.</hi> Suppoſe they are riotous, ſo was the Prodigal, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they are unkind, ſo art thou to thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven. And if thou wilt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them there treſpaſſes, neither will thy Heavenly Father forgive thee thy treſpaſſes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Is for reproof unto thoſe that wax wanton under mercies: becauſe God is good, they will be bad; becauſe he is mercifull, like the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> therefore they will be vitious; becauſe he is flow to anger, therefore they will provoke him every day. And this was <hi>Jeſuruns</hi> caſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 15. He that ſhould have been upright, when he waxed fat, ſpurned with his heel: thou art fat, thou art groſſe, thou art laden with fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: therefore he forſook God that made him, and regarded not the ſtrong rock of his ſalvation. And this is too many of our caſes<hi>:</hi> but as <hi>Moſes</hi> to the people, verſ. 6. <hi>Do ye thus requite the Lord?</hi> ſurely, inſteed of favour, ye ſhall have frowns, and blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſickneſſe, and want, and curſes upon curſes, as ye may read at large, 28. 15,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121429:51"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The father was ſick of this diſeaſe, but by Gods mercy recovered, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 7, 8. the Son falls into it, and dies without mercy, and for him <hi>David</hi> weeps, ſaying <hi>O</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom. And ſo much of this point, <hi>Davids</hi> Paſſion.</p>
            <p>II. The next General to be ſpoken of, is <hi>Davids</hi> compaſſion, <hi>Would God I had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee, Oh</hi> Abſalom; <hi>my ſon, my ſon,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in let us conſider the tenderneſſe of his love to his ſon, and that diſcovers it ſelf by three eminent ſignals.</p>
            <p>1. By preferring his ſafety and life before his own.</p>
            <p>1. His care for his ſafety is diſcovered,</p>
            <p>1. By the Charge he gave the Captains in chief, and the Souldiers under their command, to intreat the young man gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly for his ſake, <hi>verſe</hi> 5. When <hi>Abſalom</hi> was plotting and deviſing miſchief in his bed, and out of it, to bring his father to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, then he good old man is taking care for his welfare. He was of <hi>Themistocles</hi> mind, who had rather forget and forgive an injury, than remember and requite it. Now as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Go ye, and do likewiſe.</hi> To render evil for evil, is Beſtial; to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der good for good is carnal; to render evil
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121429:51"/>
for good is Satanical, and <hi>Abſalom-like;</hi> but to render good for evil, is Spiritual, and <hi>David-like,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly, By his liſtening and inquiring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſons welfare. <hi>Is the young man</hi> Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom <hi>ſafe?</hi> verſe 29. He deals not with the meſſenger concerning the event of the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, or the condition of his friends that hazarded their lives to ſave his, or his ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or falling from the Crown: but the firſt queſtion is about his <hi>Abſalom,</hi> his tongue betraying his heart, that as <hi>Joab</hi> tells him, <hi>chap.</hi> 19. 6. that he was dearer to him than all the reſt.</p>
            <p>3ly, By his immoderate weeping and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of tears he ſhed for his ſon; <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae non habent modum,</hi> weeping keeps no mean, where tears make the muſick. Water is good to waſh, and bath, and cleanſe, but not to drown our ſelves in it: ſeven ſo, tears are good to cleanſe away our inward filth of ſin, but not plunge or drown our ſelves in them by deſpair, or exceſſive mourning; all the time the Army was out <hi>Abſalom</hi> lay cloſe to his heart.</p>
            <p>2ly, He not only cared for his ſafety, but preferred it before his own, <hi>Would God I had died for thee;</hi> that is, O that I had ſtood in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121429:52"/>
               <hi>Abſaloms</hi> place to have born the brunt of the battel, and that the ſame darts thruſt him thorow, had entred into my body, and fallen upon my ſelf.</p>
            <p>2ly, Another eminent ſignal of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of his love to his ſon is taken from the perſon for whom he would have died, expreſſed with an <hi>Emphaſis, thee, thee</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom. For a man to die for a wicked man, a table-enemie, a boſome traitour, a ſon traytor, who but <hi>David</hi> would do it?</p>
            <p>3ly, The greatneſſe of his compaſſion, and tenderneſſe of his affection to his ſon is diſcovered by the ingemination, and trebling and quatrebling, over the words, as if he were not in <hi>joco,</hi> in ſport, but <hi>ſerio</hi> in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and if God had ſo pleaſed, he would have made his word good. <hi>O</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee,</hi> Abſalom <hi>my ſon, my ſon.</hi> And thus Chriſt wept over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to ſhew the bitterneſs of his grief he ſuffered for the deſtruction of that City, he dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth his words, and vents them with a paſſionate O, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 34. <hi>O Hieruſalem, Hieruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered you together, as a hen doth</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:121429:52"/>
               <hi>her brood under her wings, and ye would not?</hi> This repetition of words in holy Scripture, implyes, 1. Either truth, as Verrily, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily; or 2ly Paſſion, as My father, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. 14. or 3ly, Compaſſiion, as <hi>my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had died for thee. Davids love</hi> was either natural, and ſo he ſaith, <hi>my ſon,</hi> or carnal, and ſo he calls him his <hi>Abſalem,</hi> or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and ſo he wiſheth that he had died for him. He was ſo well acquainted with the will of God, by his revealed Word, that he knew ſo bad a life could not have a good end, and that it would be a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his ſoul to go to heaven, that had all his time ſerved the Devil on earth, and therefore of the two, he thought his own caſe beſt, and that he was moſt fit to die, and ſo, if God had ſo pleaſed, choſe to die. <hi>I would God I had died for thee.</hi> From whence we learn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> That death which to the ungodly is the King of terrors, <hi>Job</hi> 18. 14. to the righteous is a welcom gueſt at all times. <hi>Abſalom</hi> may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to die, becauſe the wages of his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs are alwayes ready to be paid him, which is eternal death of body and ſoul for ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23. When good <hi>David</hi> ſhall
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121429:53"/>
willingly reſign up his ſoul into the hands of his Creator<hi>:</hi> for he knows his end will be peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 37. <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> being ready to depart, as old <hi>Simeons</hi> Phraſe is, comforted his friends that ſtood howling about him, with theſe words; <hi>Non mori ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meo, quia bonum habeo Dominum,</hi> I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to die, becauſe I have ſerved a good God. He that fears God ſhall never need to fear death; for Chriſt hath pulled out the ſting thereof, that he may tryumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſingwith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55, 56, 57. <hi>O death where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy victory? The ſting of death is ſin: but thanks be unto God, which hath given me victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons why death is welcome to the godly at all times, are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe it is an end of their ſorrows, and the beginning and entrance into the joy of their Lord, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 23. It is the <hi>Exodus</hi> of their miſeries, and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi> of their comforts: It is as a Bridge over which they muſt paſſe into life (as the Iſraelites muſt go thorow the red Sea) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can get into <hi>Canaan, a Land flowing with milk and hony,</hi> and all good things; wherefore they rejoice to ſee that day (as
<pb n="907" facs="tcp:121429:53"/>
old <hi>Simeon</hi> did) when he embraced Chriſt in his arms, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe they are a people ready prepared for the Lord, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 17. they are not fool-hardy like others, who put far away from them the evil dayes, that they may boldly approach unto the ſeat of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 3. but they are ſtill think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of death, and looking for death, and providing for death, that whenſoever it comes, early or late, at the Cock crowing, at midnight, or the dawning of the day, they may enter into the reſt remaines for the people of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3 Becauſe they have <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz,</hi> faith, and a good conſcience, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them from ſinking under the pains of death. And this made the thief on the Croſſe to die joyfully, believing Chriſts words, that he ſhould that day be with him in Paradiſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. 43. this made St. <hi>Steven</hi> to laugh in death, beholding the heavens opened, and Chriſt ſtanding at the right hand of the Father, ready to receive his ſpirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 55, 56. and this made <hi>David</hi> ſo willing to die for <hi>Abſalom,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he believed that his ſinnes were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:121429:54"/>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Did <hi>David</hi> well to wiſh for death? or to die for his ſonne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. <hi>Mortem optare malum, formidare pejus.</hi> It is not good to wiſh for death, but worſe to fear it: It is an argument of great weakneſs to diſpute with God, much more to quarrel with God, and moſt of all to ſeem to be wiſer than God. We pray, and <hi>David</hi> prayed, <hi>Thy will O Father be done;</hi> and yet here he ſeems to prefer his own will before Gods. <hi>Would God I had died for thee</hi> Abſalom. So that as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>James</hi> 3. 10. <hi>This thing ought not to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly <hi>David</hi> did ſavour much more in this wiſh of fleſh and blood, than of ſpirit; for that altogether ſubmits with patience to ſuffer, and bear what the good pleaſure of the Lord is to bring to paſſe: when the other grumbles, and murmurs, and repines at every thing contraries their humours. This was <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, and was his failing, as the beſt want not theirs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> Speaks the true happy ſtate of a godly man. He will not be afraid of evil tidings: for his heart is fixed, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112. 7. when the wicked, <hi>trepidant ad arundinis umbram,</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the ſhaking of a leaf, and flee when
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121429:54"/>
none purſueth; then the righteous are as bold as a Lion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 1. The very thought of death ſtrikes the ungodly as dead, when they that fear the Lord (like the Swan) ſing the ſweeteſt ſong in death, and the ſong of the Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 20. <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi> The wicked when they are viſited with ſickneſs, which is deaths Paratour to ſummon them into the Court for to give up their great accompt, like the unjuſt Steward, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 2. they roar, and howl, and crie, like the hog, which thinks he is never taken but to have his throat cut<hi>:</hi> when the upright and juſt look up, and lift up their heads with joy, and comfort, for their redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on draweth near, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 28. When the wicked call to the mountaines to fall upon them, and to the hills to cover them, and hide them from the preſence of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 16. The righteous ſhout for joy, like thoſe that divide the ſpoyl, and rejoyce according to joy in harveſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 3. <hi>for they ſhall be gathered like wheat into the Lords Garner, when the chaff ſhall be burned with unquenchable fire,</hi> Mat. 3. 12. And as <hi>Balaam</hi> ſaid, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. 10. <hi>O</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:121429:55"/>
               <hi>that my latter end might be like his.</hi> And ſo thus much of the firſt perſon, ſpoken of in the text, <hi>David:</hi> with his paſſion, and compaſſion.</p>
            <p>2ly. The next perſon is <hi>Abſalom.</hi> And in him let us conſider,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His Name.</item>
               <item>2ly. His Perſon.</item>
               <item>3ly. His Life.</item>
               <item>4ly. His Death.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>1. His Name, and that was <hi>Abiſhalom,</hi> which ſignifies, his fathers peace. He was ſo ſweet a Babe, that his father promiſed himſelf great matters, and hope in him: but he proved the greateſt croſſe that ever he did bear. So that we cannot ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſic natura,</hi> (as <hi>Abigail</hi> did of <hi>Nabal,)</hi> As his name was, ſo was he: For he was a moth, a canker, a thorn in his fathers eye, and the greateſt diſturber of his quiet, and reſt, and eaſe, and peace, that ever he was acquainted with; that he is conſtrained to flee, and ſhift for his life, leſt he be devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Sonnes ſword, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 14.</p>
            <p>2ly. His perſon. And ſo he was the faireſt of ten thouſand: for from the ſole of the foot, to the top of his head, there was no blemiſh in him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 25. He
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121429:55"/>
had a fair body, but a foul ſoul and heart: like the Swan, which hath a white fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but a black skin. Or like <hi>Mauſolus</hi> his tombe, or the painted Sepulchres in the Goſpel, glorious and beautiful without, but full of rottenneſs and ſtinking bones within; Or like a white glove, over a ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hand; Or like the Phariſees in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly were greedy wolves. His garment was made of Linſey-woolſey, which was forbidden in the old Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 11. by woollen is ſignified, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity: by linnen, ſubtilty: and under this weed he had almoſt couzened his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his life, and Kingdome, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did <hi>Eſau</hi> of the bleſſing. From whence we learn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> All is not gold that gliſters, as all are not <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Rom. 9. 10. All is not current coin, that hath the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſtamp; nor all good men, that look demurely, and ſpeak fairly and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, <hi>able to deceive (if it were poſſible) the very elect,</hi> as Chriſt ſpeaks, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. 22. and therefore our Saviours counſell is, <hi>John</hi> 7. 24. <hi>Not to judge according to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance.</hi> What a Saint was <hi>Abſalom</hi> in ſhew? yet what a devil in practice?
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121429:56"/>
and this age is full of theſe <hi>Abſaloms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3ly, His Life; and thus his fair face was daubed, and ſoiled with many a black ſpot; His whole life was tainted with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable blemiſhes, one drawing on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As to inſtance in ſome.</p>
            <p>1. He was a murtherer; and this aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates it ſelf by theſe circumſtances.</p>
            <p>1. A murtherer of his brother <hi>Amnon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 29. who the nearer he was, the dearer he ought to have been<hi>: For no man hateth his own fleſh, but nouriſheth, and cheriſheth it,</hi> Eph. 5. 29. We ſay, that it is an ill bird defiles his own neſt: but we may conclude, that is the worſt bird in the neſt that picketh out his brothers eyes, and ſucks his blood.</p>
            <p>2ly. In that he masked his foul inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the veil of love and kindeneſs. <hi>Abſalom</hi> had a ſheep-ſhearing, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. and a great feaſt towards, and he could not, would not eat his meat alone, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he invites all his brethren to the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet: but as the children ſpake to their mother, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. 40 there was <hi>(Mors in olla)</hi> death in the pot, and <hi>Amnon</hi> muſt pay the reckoning with his life.</p>
            <p>3ly. That he murthered him when his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121429:56"/>
heart was merry with wine: not only la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to kill his body, but his ſoul too; and how doth this curſed act hang like a leproſie upon the skirts of his garments, to make him odious to all ages?</p>
            <p>2ly. He was ambitious.</p>
            <p>1. Of popular applauſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 4. <hi>O that I were made judge in the land, that every man that hath any controverſie, might come to me, that I might do him juſtice.</hi> O brave Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebank, that ſets forth golden wares, and promiſeth mountaines, but hides the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (as the Fiſherman doth his deadly hook under a fair bait) which he intended to give them when he had accompliſhed his deſign.</p>
            <p>2ly. He not only gives the people <hi>(bona verba)</hi> good words to delude them, but courteous deeds, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. And when any came near him, and did him obeiſance, he puts forth his hand, and took him, and kiſſed him. And by this means he ſtole the hearts of the men of <hi>Iſrael, verſ.</hi> 6. and ſo makes way,</p>
            <p>2ly, By his ambition to reach the Crown, <hi>v.</hi> 10. he acts the Devils part, to beguile, to ſeduce, and to drive on his ſelf-ends, for he tranſporteth himſelf into an
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121429:57"/>
Angel of light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 14. and this muſt needs help to make up the meaſure of his wickedneſſe, and ſo bring upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a correſponding puniſhment. His ſin is the greater, becauſe by his example he hath taught others to look up to heaven, to ſmite upon their breaſts, to pray long prayers, to preach, to uſe Scripture-Sentences, when they are acting the moſt deviliſh miſchief, or aſpiring to the Throne.</p>
            <p>3ly, He was a grand hypocrite, and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulata ſanctitas duplex iniquitas,</hi> counterfeit godlineſſe, is double wickedneſſe. The beaſt tells his Father a fair Tale, <hi>v.</hi> 8. Thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant vowed a vow, when I remained exile in <hi>Geſhur,</hi> in <hi>Aram,</hi> ſaying, <hi>If the Lord ſhall bring me again indeed to</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>I will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Oh brave, what? a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wretch and Caitiffe? What? to make godlineſſe a Cloak for his Villanie. What? to make Piety ſerve for a ſhooing horn to draw on his intereſt to the Kingdome. What? to make the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be evil ſpoken of through him and his juggling. Surely, <hi>It were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtone were banged about his neck, and he were cast into the bottome of the ſea,</hi> Matth. 18. 6. but from hence we learn,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:121429:57"/>
               <hi>Obſ. In nomine Domini, incipit omne malum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religion is made a ſtalking horſe to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate all evil. If <hi>Ahab</hi> cannot get <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard by fair play, he will have it by foul, he will proclaim a Faſt, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 9. and two ſons of Belial ſhall be hired to bear falſe witneſſe againſt him, and he ſhall be ſtoned, and then he will be merry, and take poſſeſſion, <hi>v</hi> 16. If <hi>Abſalom</hi> can no other way ſupplant his Father, he inſooth hath a Vow to pay unto the Lord in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron,</hi> and there he will take advantage of the place to mutinie and rebell, and raiſe Forces to drive his Father out of houſe and home, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 16. And this ever was, is, and will be the practice of ambitious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to ſtrain their conſciences, and to make uſe of Religion to ſtirrop them into the Saddle; but my prayer for them ſhall be, that their end may be like <hi>Abſaloms,</hi> and as <hi>Cuſhi</hi> ſaid in the context, <hi>So let all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord my King periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4ly, He was a traytor,</p>
            <p>1. To his brother, in taking away his life: but here he ſeemed to be a pettie trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, becauſe he fell alone.</p>
            <p>2ly, To the people of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyed <hi>Iſrael</hi> into a net, get they out as well
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121429:58"/>
as they could, Fall back, fall edge. So it is ſaid, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 11. <hi>And with</hi> Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom <hi>went two hundred men out of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and followed him in their ſimplicity, knowing nothing:</hi> like many of our Zelots, who were at firſt blindly led, but when they had wel ſmarted for their folly, cried <hi>(peccavimus)</hi> with the Prodigal, they were miſinformed, and gulled, and cheated of their expectation by the Grandees, who ſought themſelves, and not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in one kind, ſo it may be ſaid on the contrary, They ſought yours, not you, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 14. Ours, not us.</p>
            <p>3ly, He was a traitor in <hi>Folio</hi> to his own Father, ſeeking <hi>vi &amp; armis</hi> to depoſe him, I, and to quench his thirſt with his blood. But hold <hi>Abſalom,</hi> for he is thy father. Hold <hi>Abſalom,</hi> he is thy fond and moſt indulgent Father. Hold <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> he is thy old Father, full of gray hairs, the which are bloſſomes of the grave. Hold <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and give a check-mate to thy ambition for a while, and then ride on, and do thy will. Look upon thy brethren and ſiſters, his Wives and Concubines, thy companions with him. Look upon the Virgins in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Prieſts of God,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121429:58"/>
the hazard of War, the ſad effects of the ſword, as Rapine, Famine, Blood, Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if thou haſt not ſold thy ſelf to work wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord, like <hi>Ahab,</hi> or art not given over to a reprobate ſenſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 28. then theſe things cannot but melt thee, relent thee, and dam up thy way from proſecuting thy deviliſh purpoſes any farther. I, but thinks <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that is not the way to the Kingdom and Sceptre, and to reign, and therefore be it never ſo foul, I will thorow it, and as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid, <hi>Vel inveniam, vel fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam,</hi> I will hack and hew it out with my ſword<hi>:</hi> and ſo having gathered together all the men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> and made him ſelf ſtrong for the battel, he prepares to divide the ſpoil. Oh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralleld traytor; for</p>
            <p>1. He ſought the death of the Lords anointed: and that it is aggravated in theſe Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>1. His anointed child: <hi>And right dear and precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints,</hi> Pſal. 116. 15.</p>
            <p>2ly, His Prophet, who was as the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Gods eye, very tender to him, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2. 8. and concerning whom he hath given
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121429:59"/>
ſo ſtrict a chatge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 15 <hi>Touch not mine anointed, nor do my Prophets no harm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3ly, That he was anointed his King, a King of Gods own pointing out, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 12. a King after Gods own heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 14, A typical King of Chriſt; a King-father, and a father to his people, ſo well as to his own children; a nurſing father, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. And for <hi>Abſalom</hi> to rob God and men of ſuch a King, who would not, ſhould not fight it out to the death, like <hi>Zebulun</hi> and <hi>Nephtali, Judg.</hi> 5. 18. to ſave him, but <hi>Abſalom</hi> and ſome of his Faction who love to fiſh in troubled waters? but hence we learn,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> That one ſin, (if not in time ſtifled) makes way for a bigger, as a little wedge doth for a greater. Read backward, and ye ſhall find that his ſin grew like a ſnow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball, to a very great pitch and height, and ſo I may compare it to <hi>Elijahs</hi> cloud, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. 44. the which at firſt ſeemed no bigger than a mans hand, but by and by it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the heaven, or like to <hi>Ezekiels</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>chap.</hi> 47. 3, 4, 5. which came to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, then up to the knees, then to the loins, and afterward waxed ſo deep, that they could not be paſſed ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; or like to that fountain which became a river, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:121429:59"/>
10. 6. and as our Proverb is, Give the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil an inch, and he will take an ell. We read <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 43, 44, 45. of an unclean ſpirit in a man, <hi>Which goeth forth and taketh ſeven other ſpirits worſe than himſelf, and they enter in and dwell there:</hi> Even ſo, if we give way to one unclean ſpirit, one ſin, yea, and as <hi>Lot</hi> ſayd of <hi>Zoar,</hi> a little ſin, we make way for all ſin, that we may ſay, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did of <hi>Gad, A Troop cometh.</hi> As the Sea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the leaſt breach, be it thorow a mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole, preſently grows bigger and bigger upon it, and pours in an inundation to the deſtruction of man and beaſt; and as the Story goeth of Hatchet, which beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a withered bough of an Aſh to make it a helve, inſtantly falls to work, and cuts down the tall Cedar, and ſtrong Oke, and green Elm, and Aſh which ſtood before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; and as <hi>Pompey</hi> marching with his Souldiers to take a great and rich City, and finding the gates ſhut, and the oppoſition ſtrong, he craves leave of the Citizens to give entertainment to ſome few of his wounded and ſickly men, and he would paſſe away without their leaſt diſturbance, the which having obtained, they in the night opened the gates to the General, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121429:60"/>
the ſtronger men, to the ſacking and utter undoing of a famous City. Even ſo, if the Devil can but beg a helve for a hatchet, or make a breach in mans heart to get in his little finger, he will ſtrain hard to make room for his head, and if he can get in his head, he will draw in his whole body, or if he can procure the favour from us to give entertainment to ſome weakling and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſins, then he cries out with <hi>Moah,</hi> now <hi>Moah</hi> to the ſpoil, now Devil to thy prey; and therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> Is for our inſtruction, to kill the Crocodile in the egge, leſt it grow to be a ſerpent, and ſo kill us; to quench the fire whilſt it is but a ſpark, leſt it get head, and ſo conſume us. <hi>Obſta Principiis,</hi> withſtand the beginnings of ſin, leſt they grow to be ſo mountainous, that they cruſh thee down to hell. <hi>Venienti occurre morbo,</hi> faith the Phyſician, Prevent the diſeaſe by taking Phyſick in time, leſt it run on and deſtroy thee before thy time. If <hi>Abſolom</hi> had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this rule, he had never fallen, ſo ſhamefully, ſo ſuddenly (like a child new born) ſo wonderfully like <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Lam. 1. 9.</p>
            <p>2ly, <hi>Abſaloms</hi> Treaſon is aggravated, in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121429:60"/>
that he ſought the death of his father, his father that begat him, and his father that ſo well loved him: He was troubled with a new diſeaſe at that time; for he was ſick of his father, and nothing could cure him, but his removal out of his eye, that he might ſit at Helm, an ſteer the ſhip; from whence we learn,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> That when Kings, Princes, Governors and Magiſtrates ſhall ſuffer ſin to go unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in others, God will make them ſo ſpared, inſtruments to puniſh them. <hi>David</hi> permitting <hi>Abſalom</hi> to run on in ſin, out of one ſin into another, not executing the Law or juſtice upon him, God makes him, (as the <hi>Canaanite</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelite) Num.</hi> 33. 55. <hi>A prick in his eye, and a thorn in his ſide.</hi> We have a Proverb, Save a Thief from the Gallows, and he will hang thee at laſt, if he can. <hi>Amnons</hi> Murther deſerved ſevere puniſhment by the Law of God: but <hi>David</hi> out of fooliſh pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty omitting it, and winking at it, God ſets him home to him at laſt, and raiſeth up the ſon of his bowels and love too, to hunt after his life. <hi>Abſalom</hi> may grieve God, and yet that doth not much grieve <hi>David:</hi> wherefore God takes his own quarrel in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121429:61"/>
hand, and cauſeth him to be the greateſt grief that ever he encountred withall; and ſo hear him roaring and howling forth this ſad lamentation and Dittie for him, <hi>O</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had died for thee, O</hi> Abſalom <hi>my ſon, my ſon.</hi> And ſo I paſſe to the laſt point,</p>
            <p>4ly, Which is <hi>Abſaloms</hi> death. The two Generals, <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Joab</hi> joyned Battel to diſpute the Controverſie about the Crown, and at laſt <hi>Abſalom</hi> being worſted flieth, and flying the Mule came under a great thick Oke, <hi>And his head caught hold on the Oke, and he was taken up between the heaven and the earth, and</hi> Joab <hi>took three darts, and thruſt them thorow</hi> Abſalom, and ſo he died, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. 14. Died between heaven and earth, as unworthy by reaſon of his debauchedneſſe, to go to the one, or to have a burial place in the other: the which is a moſt terrible and fearfull example of Gods vengeance,</p>
            <p>1. Againſt Rebels to their King.</p>
            <p>2ly, Againſt thoſe that are diſobedient to Parents; and yet as bad as he was, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> the King wept for him, ſaying, <hi>O</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had died for thee, O</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſonne, my ſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:121429:61"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Athaliah's</hi> deteſtable Treaſon.</head>
            <head type="sub">SERMON III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 Kings 11. 14.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Athaliah <hi>rent her cloathes, and cried, Treaſon, treaſon.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>VErbum diei in die ſuo,</hi> was the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles charge to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 2. and therefore it ſhall be my practice: for ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 25. 11. <hi>A word ſpoken in ſeaſon, is like apples of gold with pictures of ſilver.</hi> How well then doth this Text match the occaſion of this our meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together at this time? which is to give thanks unto God for the diſcovery of <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dercombs</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:121429:62"/>
deſperate Treaſon, againſt <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector. <hi>Then</hi> Athaliah <hi>rent her cloaths, and cried, Treaſon, treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein let us conſider theſe two general branches.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Athaliahs</hi> action; <hi>Then</hi> Athaliah <hi>rent her cloaths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly. <hi>Athaliahs</hi> paſſiion; <hi>And cried, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt let us conſider theſe two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</p>
            <p>1. The ſubject of her action, her cloaths: <hi>ſhe rent her cloaths.</hi> Ah <hi>Athaliah,</hi> this was a more ſuitable occaſion for thee to follow, the Prophets inſtruction, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 13. in rending thy heart, and not thy garments: But ſhe that had no heart to ſpare infants, like <hi>Herod,</hi> had no heart to repent, and ſo runs on ſtill in revenge. And if ſhe can make man the ſubject of her wrath no longer, her cloaths ſhall feel it, and ſpeak her minde. <hi>She rent her cloaths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly. The time of her rageing, and mad, wilde action, implyed in the firſt word, then. <hi>Then ſhe rent her cloaths.</hi> Then, when ſhe ſaw another ſun riſen up in <hi>Judah</hi> to eclipſe her pride, her glory, and her hauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Then, when ſhe found ſhe could no
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121429:62"/>
longer ſtand, or keep the ſaddle, or wear the Crown, <hi>She rent her clothes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond conſider with me theſe two particulars likewiſe.</p>
            <p>1. The manner how ſhe vents her paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>She cried.</hi> Her dead and ſeared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience now revives, and whiſpers in her ears that ſhe had committed crying ſins, and ſo conſidering how near her door the puniſhment of them was come, as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man amazed, frighted, and ſtartled at it, ſhe cried out for help, when ſhe was paſt cure; <hi>ſhe cried.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly The cauſe of her paſſion, and of her heavy exclamation, in theſe words, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon.</hi> She had committed Treaſon againſt heaven, and the King of heaven, and that never troubled her, which is the greateſt Treaſon of all. She had committed Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in murthering the Kings Seed, and that lieth not nigh her heart<hi>:</hi> but when ſhe ſeeth her full ſea ebbing, her ſun ſetting, her bright day drawn to an end, and ſhutting in, her hour-glaſſe run out, and her doom of death paſſed upon her, <hi>Then ſhe rent her clothes and cryed, Treaſon, Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein let us for the better diſcovery and opening the Text conſider theſe four parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:121429:63"/>
               <item>1. What <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſignifies.</item>
               <item>2ly, Who <hi>Athaliah</hi> was,</item>
               <item>3ly, What her Treaſon was; and that which ſhe complained of.</item>
               <item>4ly, What her end was; and of theſe in order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſignifies, time for the Lord. When the ungodly deſtroy Gods Law, and bring it into utter contempt, then ſaith <hi>David</hi> in this ſenſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 126. It is time for thee Lord to work, that is, to ſend help, either by converting or confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the enemies thereof<hi>:</hi> as God converted <hi>Saul,</hi> but confounded <hi>Herod.</hi> When the wickedneſſe of the Amorites is full, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 16. and the corn ripe for the harveſt, then it is time for the Lord to thruſt in his ſickle. When <hi>Ahaliahs</hi> feathers of pride are full grown, then it is time for the Lord to deplume her, and ſend her as naked out of the world, as ever ſhe came into it. When ſhe was joined to Idols, it was time for the Lord to make her know, that an Idol was as vain a thing, as a horſe, to ſave her from tumbling, and ruine, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33 17. And this time is come, and is made good to a tittle upon her, all crying out with one voice, as they did
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121429:63"/>
againſt <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 22. 22. <hi>Away with ſuch a woman from the earl: for it is not meet that ſhe ſhould live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly. Who <hi>Athaliah</hi> was from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And ſo ſhe was deſcended from high Parentage: for ſhe was daughter unto <hi>Omri</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 Kings 8. 22. and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Ahaziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> and wife to <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>horam</hi> his father. As ſhe came from a high Stock, ſo ſhe ſoared high: and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſatisfie her ambition, but the Scepter and ſway of the Kingdom, and the Crown: and have it ſhe will, <hi>per fas, per nefas,</hi> be it right, be it wrong, rather than ſhe will miſſe of ſo goodly a bait. From whence we may learn,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> That ambitious Spirits will climb over the head of all wickedneſſe, and make it their foot-ſtool to raiſe them to honour. When <hi>Eteocles</hi> and <hi>Polynices</hi> his brother were contending for their Fathers king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with naked ſwords in their hands, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſheath in each others bowels, then <hi>Jocaſta</hi> their Mother ſtepped in between them, mediating for peace and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation upon her bended knees, uſing theſe or the like words: What my ſons, the ſons of my womb, the ſons of my deſires, as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:121429:64"/>
               <hi>Bath-ſheba</hi> the Mother of <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. 1. rather than let my eyes be ſpectators of your ſelves weltring in your bloud, <hi>in me convertite ferrum,</hi> put up your weapons into the womb that did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and bear you. But ſaith <hi>Eteocles</hi> to her, <hi>Pro regno velim patriam, penates, conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem flammis dare: Imperia precio quolibet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant bene,</hi> To gain a kingdom, I would ſet Country, Houſhold-gods, wife, and all on fire, like <hi>Troy;</hi> for Kingdoms and Crowns cannot be purchaſed at too dear a rate. <hi>Abſalom</hi> to ſtep into his Fathers throne, <hi>quid non audet?</hi> what will he not? what dares he not to do? And it was the ſpeech of one in later times, who having by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, diſſimulation, and treachery, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf aloft; That if he fell, all the Commonwealth ſhould fall with him: farr preferring his private intereſt before the publique. And <hi>Athaliah</hi> was caſt into the ſame mould; for neither the frown of God, the curſe of the people, the tears of Innocents, could give a <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> to her wicked deſign ſhe had in hand: but a kingdom ſhe will have, although ſhe buyes it with the loſſe of her ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. As it was ſaid of <hi>Corax</hi> and <hi>Lyſias,</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:121429:64"/>
               <hi>mali <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orvi, malum ovum,</hi> a curſt Crow hath hatched a ſhrewd egge; a crafty Maſter hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed as crafty a ſcholar: Even ſo as <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpeaks, 24. 2. <hi>Like father, like daughter:</hi> a wicked father, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 16. 25, 26. and as vile a child. Of all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> there was not one good: and of all their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren there was not one thoroughly righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Its true there was found ſome good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in <hi>Abijah</hi> towards the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14. 13. but it was but ſome, and that God takes notice of, and that goeth not unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded: but of all the reſidue, we hear no ſuch news, ſo unhappy a thing it is to be the child of a bad father, for ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Pſal.</hi> 18. 26. <hi>With the froward he ſhall learn frowardneſſe, and with the ungodly, ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe;</hi> and ſo I paſſe to the next parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>3ly, What <hi>Athaliahs</hi> Treaſon was, with that ſhe complained of. <hi>Athaliahs</hi> Treaſon was <hi>Monstrum, horrendum, ingens,</hi> ſo heinous, ſo deteſtable, ſo abominable, that heaven could not but mourn over it, the earth tremble at it, and the mountains and hard rocks be moved for it. God could not but loathe &amp; abhor the author of it, Man could
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:121429:65"/>
not but be ſtartled at her inhumane barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, and the Devils themſelves not own it; for when ſhe ſaw that her ſon was dead, ſhe aroſe, and deſtroyed all the Kings ſeed, <hi>verſe</hi> 1. that is, all thoſe that were of the houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> (but one called <hi>Joaſh)</hi> whom <hi>Jehoſheba</hi> ſtole away, and nurſed up pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, <hi>verſe</hi> 2. Alas, What harm had theſe harmleſſe Lambs done? What miſbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour did ſhe ſee in their unſpotted lives, that death muſt preſently remove them out of her ſight? It was <hi>Hecuba's</hi> ſpeech, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſei oultus, amo illos priores, quos tulit quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam juvenis,</hi> that ſhe was in love with the youthfull freſh face of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lovely as the morning, and whoſe cheeks were comely, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 18 and why ſhould not theſe <hi>Athaliah,</hi> give a check mate to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent torrent of thy ſwelling, envenomed rage againſt them? <hi>Athaliah,</hi> look upon the Royal blood ſtreams in their veins. <hi>Athaliah,</hi> look upon their innocency. <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> look upon their ſweet and amiable countenances, and if <hi>Nihil horum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſque movebunt,</hi> none of theſe can move thee to pity them, to ſpare them, to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on them, then let the tender bowel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a mother melt thee; for how will <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:121429:65"/>
moutn for her children when they are not? <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. 18. Thou were once a mother thy ſelf, and let thy own tongue ſpeak, What pangs and throbs (like a ſecond la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) thou enduredſt in thy heart, when thou loſt thy ſon, and therefore let the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereof move thee to have a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling of other womens miſeries; or if that be too weak to refell, repel, and null thy ambitious, high towring thoughts, then call to mind the conſanguinity and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity they had with the ſon of thy love, to quench thy burning thirſt after their blood; or if that be too weak an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to convince thee, then let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thy own ſhame, and the grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and muttering of a diſcontented people fright thee from doing ſuch a curſed act. <hi>Athaliah,</hi> remember that for blood, and ſuch grand wickedneſſe, the Land mourns, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 4. <hi>Athaliah,</hi> remember that a houſe cannot be eſtabliſhed by iniquity, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 11. <hi>Athaliah,</hi> remember what a terrible wo is denounced againſt thoſe that build a Town with blood, and erect a City by iniquity, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Athaliah,</hi> remember the Saints cry day and night unto the Lord, to judge and avenge their blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 10.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:121429:66"/>
and then if thou be not more ſavage than the Bear robbed of her whelps, and given over to a Reprobate ſence to work evil, and all manner of evil in the ſight of the Lord, like thy Progenitors, thou wilt ſtifle this deſign in the birth. I but thinks <hi>Athaliah,</hi> How ſhall I wear the Crown, and ſway the Reaml then? <hi>An.</hi> Impriſon them, and that is cruelty enough toward the heirs apparent of a whole Kingdom. I but thinks <hi>Athali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> they may break priſon, and pull the Crown off again from my head. <hi>An.</hi> Then baniſh them, proclaim them Traytors if they diſturb thy peace, and cauſe the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleters to libel them, diſgrace them, and bring them into an <hi>odium</hi> with their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I but thinks <hi>Athaliah,</hi> they will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes undermining my new, upſtart ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and foundation, and hatching one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or other againſt me, and therefore my ſureſt courſe will be to take offth eir heads; and here ſhe ſets up her ſtaff, fall back, fall edge, this ſhe reſolves to do, be it pleaſing or diſpleaſing to God or man. She intends to make ſure work where ſhe goeth, ſo well as ſhe can: and ſo cuts off all that might lay claim to her uſurped intereſt. And now ſhe conjectures, the Crown is nailed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121429:66"/>
faſt to her head<hi>:</hi> She thinks that her houſe is builded upon a rock that will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her<hi>:</hi> She ſuppoſed like <hi>Babylon,</hi> Iſa. 47. 7. That ſhe ſhall be a Queen for ever, and ſo ſhe ruffles it, and vaunts it, like <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> over his <hi>Babel, Dan.</hi> 4 27. and glorifies her ſelf ſix years together, not fearing or feeling any ſtorm to diſquiet her<hi>:</hi> She ſings a Lullaby to her ſoul, with the rich man, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 19. <hi>Soul take thine eaſe, eat, drink and be merry:</hi> ſhe cries peace, peace, when there was no peace, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 14. for when ſhe leaſt dreamed of it, then her wickedneſſe lay at her door, like a fierce Maſtiff, to rend her into peeces, and rob her, and ſpoil her of all her glory; and the Lord bringeth a Vine as it were out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and raiſeth up an Infant out of the duſt to dethrone her, by name, <hi>Joaſh,</hi> by birth of the line of <hi>Judah,</hi> as he had promiſed <hi>David, That he ſhould not want a man to ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne after him,</hi> Jer. 33. 17. And all this he bringeth to paſſe by weak means, (as when men are loweſt, then he is ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) and loves to be Jehovah-Jereh, ſeen in the Mount; even by <hi>Jehoiada</hi> chief Prieſt, who anoints him, proclaims him King, and the people with acclamations of joy,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121429:67"/>
ſhout, lift up their voices like trumpets, and cry out, <hi>Vive le Roy,</hi> Let the King live for ever, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. <hi>God ſave the King, God ſave the King,</hi> Wherefore</p>
            <p>1. Let no man be ſory, as they that are without hope, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 13 for he is the Almighty God, as he told <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. 1. to do wonders for us, as well as for <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2ly, Let us comfort one another in the meditation of his power; mans neceſſity is Gods opportunity to help, and if his help be deferred for twice ſix years, <hi>Wait, for it ſhall ſurely come, and not stay,</hi> Hab. 2. 3.</p>
            <p>Thus her ſtiff mountain is ſhaken, that ſhe may ſpeak with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 30 6, 7. <hi>In my proſperity I ſaid, I ſhall never be moved, I having made my mountain ſo ſtrong: but thou didſt bide thy face, O Lord, and I was troubled.</hi> Thus the ſcale is tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned, and <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſo net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled at the noiſe, and clamours ecchoed into her ears, that ſhe muſt haſten to ſee what news was ſtirring abroad, <hi>verſe</hi> 13. but her eye no ſooner gave the relation thereof, but her countenance changeth, her fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles like an Aſpen leaf, and her joints are looſed, and her hands ſhake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s with the Palſie troubled: her heart now condemns
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:121429:67"/>
her, the dead ſerpent or viper now flies in her face, like <hi>Pauls,</hi> and her tongue vent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forth her grief, bellowing forth <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon.</hi> How now <hi>Athaliah,</hi> is it Treaſon for <hi>Joaſh</hi> to reſume his Birthright? How now <hi>Athaliah,</hi> is it become Treaſon for the heir to uſe means to ſit in his own Throne? How now <hi>Athaliah,</hi> ſhall the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Traytor complain of Treaſon? if Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as indeed thou calleſt the omnipotent Juſtice it ſelf) be ſo hatefull to thee now, why didſt thou not abhor it at firſt? Why didſt thou learn others the Trade of high Treaſon; and why didſt thou manage it with an irrelenting heart, and ſtrong hand againſt others? Look up, now, and ſee how juſt God is maintaining the cauſe of the righteous, according to that of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 37. 25. <hi>I have been young, and now am old, yet I ſaw never the righteous forſaken.</hi> Look up now and bluſh, to ſee upon what a ſandy foundation thou didſt build thy neſt; and how thy truſt is but as a Spiders Web, <hi>Job</hi> 18. 14. and thy confidence cut off. Look upon the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> and behold how ſoon their hearts are turned from thee: and they that were accuſtomed to make the air to ring with their Hoſannaes, now cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121429:68"/>
               <hi>crucifige,</hi> and they that uſed to cry God ſave the Queen, now cry God ſave the King, and laugh at thy out-cry, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon;</hi> from whence we may gather,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. <hi>De male quaeſitis vix gaudet tertius haeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Goods, and poſſeſſions, and Kingdoms ill gotten, ſeldome hold out to the third generation; our eyes have read of and ſeen ſuch changes in our time, and <hi>pluris eſt ocula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus teſtis unus, quam auriti decem,</hi> what our eyes have been ſpectators of, carries more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain credit with us many degrees, than what we hear, and therefore I ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my ſelf herein. <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſpeaks e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough this truth whoſe eyes did ſee her riſing and ſetting, her mounting up, and falling down<hi>:</hi> for wickedneſſe overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the finner, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 6. and therefore <hi>Stringat tenuis mea littora puppis.</hi> Let others ſail in the middeſt of the ſwelling Ocean, and climb high, yet my deſire ſhall be to go by the ſhore ſide<hi>: For a little that a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man hath, is better than the Revenues of the wicked,</hi> although they be large, and great, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37. 16. Becauſe there is a moth, and a cancker, and a <hi>Jonah's</hi> worm in them, to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121429:68"/>
blaſt them, and ſmite them, and deſtroy them. Have ye not read, nor heard of, nor ſeen one by fraud, and lying, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and ſwearing, and forſwearing ſtep into the Regal Chair, and his ſon to keep it warm for a ſhort time after him, and then the old Propheſie, and this Doctrine to be verefied, <hi>Nullus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. According to that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 21. 30. <hi>There is no wiſdome, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor Counſel againſt the Lord. Athaliah</hi> thought that ſhe had made all cock-ſure: but how eaſily and ſuddenly doth the Lord defeat the counſel of <hi>Ahithophel?</hi> How quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth the Lord break her arm of fleſh? and how inſtantly doth the Lord turn all her wiſdome into fooliſhneſs? as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>I will deſtroy the wiſdome of the wiſe, and caſt away the understanding of the prudent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. Is, that although the Lord be ſlow, yet is he ſure, although he hath lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den feet, yet he hath iron hands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 9. although he ſuffers the wicked to reign long in their wickedneſs, yet at laſt he puls down the mighty from their ſeat, as <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of our Lord ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 52. &amp; brings them to a ſharp account for all. <hi>Athaliah</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:121429:69"/>
ſteered the Ship, governed the Kingdome, ſate faſt in the ſaddle ſix years together, that men began to think it impoſſible for her Chariot-wheels to be overturned and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown: but then when ſhe and others leaſt dreamed of ſuch a change, God makes himſelf known in <hi>Iudah,</hi> and his works in <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 76. 1. and caſts her out of the Throne, and ſtripps her of all her pomp.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 4. There is no conſtancy nor ſtability to be found in earthly things. They are like the <hi>Heliotropium,</hi> which opens and ſhuts, like unto the ſea, ebbing or flowing, like unto the Moon, waxing and waining, like unto the Journall of the Iſraelites, ſometimes ſweet, ſometimes <hi>marah.</hi> If there be joy in the morning, there is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in the Evening. If the Skie be one day clear, it is ten to one, but the next it is cloudy and wateriſh. If <hi>Athaliah</hi> now pricks and trims up her ſelf, and ſmiles and laughs, by and by ſhe is at her wits end, crying out, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon,</hi> and herein is that fulfilled in her, which Chriſt ſpake, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 5. <hi>Wo he to you that now laugh; for ye ſhall wail and weep:</hi> and this Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould afford us much wiſdome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:121429:69"/>
1 If honour, or riches encreaſe upon us, not to ſet our hearts upon them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 10. for alas, they are but for a ſhort ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid of the pleaſures of ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 25. and either we muſt leave them, or they will leave us, and ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 23. 5. Wilt thou caſt thine eyes upon it which is nothing? for they take their wings like an Eagle and flie away. Proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his brags, ſaid, <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould ſerve him?</hi> I, <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> is it ſo? Is thy heart ſo lifted up againſt thy Maker? Surely, if thou wilt not know God in thy proſperity, thou ſhalt be made to confeſſe him and his power in thy adverſity. If thou wilt not hear <hi>Moſes,</hi> thou ſhalt hear the Red ſea preaching thy deſtruction, and ſo with the glory of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he ſinks like Lead under the returning waters, <hi>Exod</hi> 5. 2. 14. 27, 28. <hi>Herod</hi> vaunted himſelf upon his Throne, and thought like <hi>Babylon,</hi> that he was, and none elſe lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, but the next news we hear of him is, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 10. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eſt?</hi> Where is he? for he is eaten up of worms, <hi>Acts</hi> 12 23. <hi>Haman</hi> was fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licking at Queen <hi>Eſthers</hi> Banquet at Noon, but hanging on the Gallows befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e night, <hi>Esth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> 7. 10. Great <hi>Frederick</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ror,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:121429:70"/>
was at laſt brought ſo low, that he became an humble ſuter to his ſervants for a ſinging mans place in the ſame Cathedral Church which he had builded, and yet went without it. <hi>Nero</hi> one while plaid the Devil, 1. In cauſing <hi>Rome</hi> to be fired. 2ly, Playing upon the harp all the time it was burning. 3ly, Singing the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Troy</hi> over it. 4ly, Perſecuting the Saints. 5ly, Tyranniſing over his own Subjects. 6ly, Slaying his own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Agrippina,</hi> cauſing her to be ripped up that he might ſee the womb wherein he was conceived; but at laſt his own people, not able to endure any longer his unparalleld cruelty, drave him out of his Kingdome, and purſuing him, ſlew him like a mad dog. That famous Captain <hi>Bellizarius,</hi> who ſo ſucceſſively prevailed in all his Battels, at laſt he had his eyes put out like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and he was ſeen begging by the high way ſide, in this Language, <hi>Date unum obulum Bellizario,</hi> give a half penny for Gods ſake to poor <hi>Bellizarius.</hi> Thus we ſee what pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull moveables earthly things are, conſtant in nothing but inconſtancy. Thus we ſee how tickliſh this ſea of glaſſe upon which the children of men ſtand, is: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:121429:70"/>
               <hi>David</hi> from this Conſideration draws this Concluſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 10. <hi>Yet a little while, and the wicked ſhall not appear, and thou ſhalt look after his place, and he ſhall not be found.</hi> If thou lookeſt for mighty <hi>Nimrod</hi> the great hunter before the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. 9. If thou lookeſt for perſecuting, painting <hi>Jezabel,</hi> thou ſhalt find nothing but her skull and feet, and palms of her hands, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9. 35. and if thou lookeſt for K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng-killing <hi>Athaliah,</hi> ſhe is vanished like a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, which appeareth but for a little time, <hi>James</hi> 4. 14. and ſo I end this point in the words of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 146. 3. <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor the Son of man; for they cannot help: put not your trust in riches; for they are uncertain,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6. 17. and deceivable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 22. Put not your truſt in earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things; for they are as unconſtant as the wind, and vanity, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of vanities, yea, and all things are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1. 2. ſaving onely the fearing of God, and the keeping of his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: but if ye will truſt in any thing, let it be,</p>
            <p>2ly, In atchieving the true honour, and ſuch treaſures as fail not, reſerved in the heaven for you, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 33. It was the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:121429:71"/>
               <hi>Vale,</hi> farewel Speech, that Cardinal <hi>Wolſey</hi> gave unto the world in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighths dayes, being to ſuffer death, Well ſaith he, if I had been as carefull to ſerve my God, as I have been to ſerve my Prince, I ſhould never have come to this. Even ſo, if we will be careful to ſerve God, then when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> &amp; ſuch miſerable comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as <hi>Job</hi> calls them, ſhall forſake us, then when our earthly pleaſures, and treaſures, and honours ſhall deny us, and leave us, then God will fail thee never, ſaith <hi>David, When thy father and mother ſhall forſake thee, then the Lord will gather thee up,</hi> Pſal. 27. 10. <hi>When the wicked ſhall not be ſuffered to dwell in the Land, the righteous ſhall never be removed,</hi> Prov. 10. 30. When the Crown of pride ſhall be pulled from the head of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then the Lord will honour thoſe that honour him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30. and we ſhall find the comfort of all when we come to die. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liah</hi> had no fear of God before her eyes: ſhe kicked againſt the pricks, and ſtrived againſt the ſtream, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 5. ſhe lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on a brok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſtaff, ſhe rejected the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt herſelf, like the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, and the expounders of the Law, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 30. and what was the iſſue of this? ſhe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:121429:71"/>
fell like Lighting from heaven, and once beginning to fall, never reſted till ſhe came to the ground, like a ſtone tumbled down a hill. I will end this point in the words of <hi>Auguſtine, Mundus tranſit, &amp; concupiſcentia ejus: quid vis? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum amare temporalia, &amp; tranſire cum tempore, an Christum amare, &amp; in aeternum vivere;</hi> the world paſſeth away, and the glory thereof: now chuſe whether thou wilt follow, and love temporal things, which will die with thee, or Chriſt, and live eternally?</p>
            <p>3ly, Seeing there is no conſtancy and ſtability to be found in earthly things, <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 12. Ye have heard what God did to <hi>Pharaoh, Herod, Nebuchadnezzar, Korah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for their Rebellion; <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, Ahab, Jeroboam, Iezabel,</hi> for their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; <hi>Troy, Niniveh, Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrhe, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> now lying in duſt and aſhes, one ſtone not being left upon another. Now ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>All theſe things came upon them for enſamples, and to admoniſh us to provide againſt our changes ſhall come,</hi> as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did againſt a dearth. It is a great leſſening of our grief when nothing befalls us, but what we looked for, for
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121429:72"/>
fore-warned, fore-armed to bear it, <hi>Praemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, praemunitus.</hi> What made <hi>Iob</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror over all his ſorrows, that preſſed upon him like armed men, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 11. but his wife forecaſt of the brittle condition of all ſublunaries? ſo are his words, <hi>chap</hi> 3. 25. <hi>The thing I feared is come upon me, and the thing that I was afraid of is come unto me.</hi> If his poverty, ſores, ſcabs, running iſſues, contempt of his wife; forſaking of his friends, ſcorn of his ſervants, deriſion of his enemies, loſſe of his children, had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts Propheſie come upon him as a ſnare, that is ſuddenly and unloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 35. they could not but have brake his heart: but muſing and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating beforehand upon the alterations of all things, and expecting the worſt, he ſtood in the door to welcome them, and his godly patience drave them out again, finding a full ſupper after a ſharp and ſhort dinner. As God ſpeaks of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32. 29. <hi>Oh that men were wiſe, then they would conſider this: they would remember their latter end:</hi> Even ſo ſpeak I in this kind, <hi>Oh that men were wiſe,</hi> then they would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this, they would conſider that riches have their end, pleaſures their end,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121429:72"/>
Kingdoms their end, honours their end, and man himſelf his end, and ſo not labour for the meat which periſheth, but for that meat which hath no end, enduring unto everlaſting life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 27.</p>
            <p>4ly, Here we learn, that it will nothing profit a man to gain the whole world, and at laſt loſe his own ſoul, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26. <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> wore the Crown, ſwayed the Kingdom, trimmed up her ſelf with Peacock feathers, and we ſay, Gay feathers make gay birds. Her Princes did her homage, her Servants went and came at her command, her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants cried before her <hi>Abrech,</hi> in ſign of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as was done unto <hi>Joſeph, Gen.</hi> 41. 43. She had ſtately houſes, fruitfull vineyards, pleaſant gardens, and orchards, with trees of all fruits: Shee had Beeves and Sheep in abundance, ſilver and gold, and the chief treaſures of Kings and Provinces<hi>:</hi> She had Men-ſingers, and Women-ſingers, and the delights of the ſons of men: She was great, and whatſoever her eyes and heart deſired, was not with-held from them, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpake of his outward felicity, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet as <hi>Haman</hi> ſaid to his wife <hi>Zereſh,</hi> and his friends about him, ſhewing them the glory of his riches, the multitude of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121429:73"/>
and how the King had promoted him above all: <hi>What do all theſe things avail me, ſo long as I ſee</hi> Mordecai <hi>the Iew ſitting at the Kings gate, not bowing his knee unto me?</hi> Even ſo, What do all theſe things before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned avail <hi>Athaliah,</hi> ſeeing her ſoul ſhall go to hell? ſhe made but a ſorrie exchange of heaven for hell, of joy for ſorrow, of things eternal for tranſitorie, of eaſe for endleſs pains and torments, as the rich Gallant tells you, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 23.</p>
            <q>Felix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</q>
            <p>Happy are ye if her harms can teach you Wiſdome to beware of her ſins, and all ſins whoſe end is bitterneſſe, as <hi>Abner</hi> told <hi>Ioab</hi> of the ſword, and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23.</p>
            <p>5ly, If there be no conſtancy in earthly things, then let us follow Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 30, 31. <hi>Weep as though we weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, rejoyce, as though we rejoiced not, buy, as though we poſſeſſed not, uſe the things of this world, as though we uſed them not.</hi> The dogs of the River <hi>Nilus</hi> drink running, leſt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt they ſtay to take a full draught, they are ſnatched into it, &amp; devoured by the Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codiles are there watching for their prey.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:121429:73"/>
Even ſo let it be our wiſdom to take a little ſup of theſe outwards, leſt while we load our ſelves with thick clay, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 6. and ſtay to take a full draught of them, we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the helliſh Scorpion. <hi>Agurs</hi> por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the beſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 8, 9. <hi>Neither pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nor riches, but food convenient for us. Pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas durum telum, &amp; neceſſitas cogit turpia.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and need conſtrains many a man to do naughty things, contrary to his nature, as ſteal, and proſperity makes him to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 12. and kick againſt God, like the foal that hath ſucked his fill, againſt his Dam. Thus did <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſerve God, and therefore no marvel her Fall was great: And this leads me to the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>4ly, What her end was. We ſay, <hi>Mali principii, malus exitus,</hi> an ill beginning is commonly accompanied with as bad an end, and ſad concluſion<hi>: For can we look to gather grapes of thorns, and figs of thiſtles? Luke</hi> 6. 44. <hi>Certainly, whatſoever a man ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that ſhall he alſo reap,</hi> Gal. 6. 7. <hi>Athaliah</hi> her ſelf ſpeaks this truth; for ſhe ſowing to the fleſh reaped tares and tears<hi>:</hi> ſhe ſowed ill ſeed, and found a bad harveſt, ſhe laid her foundation in blood, and bleeds
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121429:74"/>
for it at her death: as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake to <hi>Agag</hi> King of the Amalekites, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 33. <hi>As thy ſword hath made women childleſs, ſo ſhall thy mother be childleſſe among other women.</hi> Even ſo may I ſpeak of <hi>Athaliah</hi> in this kind: As ſhe let the Kings ſeed bleed to death, ſo <hi>Iſrael</hi> did mete her meaſure for meaſure, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 1. and paid her home in her own coin. As ſhe would ſhew no mercy, ſo ſhe found no mercy, and as ſhe would not ſpare nor have pity nor compaſſion, like the evil ſervant, <hi>Matth</hi> 18. 33. So <hi>nec pretio, nec pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> by bribing, or prayers, or tears, or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of her hands could ſhe purchaſe the leaſt drop of water, like the rich man for his hard heartineſſe to <hi>Lazarus, Luke</hi> 16. 21. or dram of pity; <hi>For they laid hands on her, and ſhe went by the way, by which the horſes go to the houſe of the King, and there was ſhe ſlain;</hi> She made a pit and digged it, and is fallen into the pit that ſhe made, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 15. from whence we may learn theſe obſervations, according to a threefold Proverb.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. Pride will have a fall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. Harm watch, harm catch.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Qualis vita, finis ita.</hi> As we live, ſo we die; and ſo of theſe in order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. Pride will have a fall; and in this
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121429:74"/>
ſenſe ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 16. 18. <hi>Pride goeth before a fall, and an high mind before deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the 29. 23. <hi>The pride of a man ſhall bring him low,</hi> and <hi>chap.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>When pride cometh, then cometh ſhame,</hi> wherefore <hi>Mary</hi> in her <hi>Magnificat</hi> ſings, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 51, 52. <hi>He hath ſcattered the proud in the imaginations of their hearts, and hath put down the mighty from their Seats. Moab</hi> ſhall be as <hi>Sodome,</hi> and the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> as <hi>Gomorrha:</hi> even the breeding of Nettles, and ſalt-pits, and a perpetual deſolation: This ſhall they have for their pride, becauſe they have magnified themſelves, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2. 9, 10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 10, 11. Our firſt Parents were created in a moſt glorious condition, but were not contented with it, but aſpired ſtill higher, and would be as God, and ſo were caſt out of Paradiſe, and became mortal: and this they had for their pride. <hi>Jezabel</hi> flaunted it, painted, and attired her ſelf moſt gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and thought none like her, but ſhe at laſt was thrown out of the window, and eaten of dogs, as <hi>Herod</hi> was of worms, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9. 36. and this they had for their Pride. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> fluttered his wings over great <hi>Babel, Saying, Is not this great Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel that I have built by the might of my power,</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:121429:75"/>
               <hi>and for the honour of my Majeſty? But while the word was in the Kings mouth, a voice came down from heaven, ſaying, O King, to thee be it spoken, thy Kingdom is departed from thee, and they ſhall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling ſhall be with the beaſts of the field, and thou ſhalt eat graſſe as the oxen,</hi> Dan. 4. 27, 28, 29. And this he had for his pride, and was ſo well tutored in his humiliation, and in the Croſſe-houſe, which is the beſt School-houſe, for <hi>Schola crucis, Schola lucis,</hi> that he ſpake truly, <hi>v.</hi> 34. <hi>The Lord abaſeth all thoſe that walk in pride. Zenacherib</hi> in the pride of his heart blaſphemed the living God, ſaying, that he ſhould not deliver <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> out of his hands; but he found and felt his power in ſending him home with ſhame by weeping-Croſſe, and then and there was ſlain by his own ſons, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 37. and this he had for his pride. <hi>Athaliah,</hi> proud <hi>Athaliah,</hi> bloudy <hi>Athaliah,</hi> took ſo wonderfull a fall, that ſhe could never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it; as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 32. Time would be too ſhort for me to tell you of the ſtately Builders of <hi>Babel,</hi> of <hi>Sheba,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Bichri,</hi> of <hi>Adoniah,</hi> of <hi>Benba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad,</hi> and of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> with their ends, all of them confirming and ſtrengthening the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121429:75"/>
point in hand, Pride will have a Fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But I am free from this ſin, and ſo far enough from the puniſhment of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are four kinds of proud men, and it is ten to one, if thou beeſt not within the compaſs and liſt of ſome of them.</p>
            <p>1. Arrogant, attributing every good thing in themſelves unto themſelves, and not unto God, when ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Every good giving, and every perfect gift comes from above, and down from the father of lights.</hi> This is pride againſt God, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery of God, to take his glory, and clothe our ſelves with his honour, which the Creator will never ſuffer in the creature.</p>
            <p>2ly, Preſumptuous, acknowledging that God is giver of their grace, but upon their own merit, whereas of what little worth that is, the Prophet ſhews, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 7. 8. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us belongs open ſhame and confuſion of face, and all our righteouſneſſe is as filthy clouts, and menſtruous rags,</hi> Iſa. 64 6.</p>
            <p>3ly, Boaſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of eminency, which indeed they have not; every man naturally is in love of himſelf, <hi>Narciſſus</hi> like, and thinks better of himſelf than others do, or he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves; ſelf-love is <hi>morbus communis,</hi> an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical diſeaſe: whereas if he hath eminent
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121429:76"/>
parts and gifts, they are but lent or given unto him, thereby the more fully and freely to glorifie the donor of them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou oughteſt not to boaſt, or to be proud of them; for ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>What hast thou, that thou hast not received? If thou have received it, why rejoyceſt thou, as if thou hadſt not received it?</hi> Theſe are like <hi>Theudas, Acts</hi> 5. 36. boaſters of themſelves to be ſome body, when they are as empty Casks, full of nothing but air.</p>
            <p>4ly, Deſpiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of others, like the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee of the Publican, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 1. and of all or moſt of theſe <hi>Paul</hi> propheſied, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1, 2. <hi>In the laſt dayes ſhall come perillous times; for men ſhall be lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, high minded,</hi> &amp;c. and a haughty eye and heart is one of the ſix things the Lords ſoul abhorreth. Satan is a cunning Fiſher-man, and hath of all ſorts of nets to catch the ſons of men. If he cannot catch one man with pleaſure, he will catch him with covetouſnes<hi>:</hi> If he cannot catch another with covetouſneſſe, he will catch him with wine and ſtrong drink: If he cannot catch another with wine and ſtrong drink, he wil catch him w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> carnal pride<hi>:</hi> If he cannot catch him with carnal pride, he will
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:121429:76"/>
catch him with ſpiritual pride, and then he is ready for a fall, and a dangerous fall; <hi>For God reſists the proud, Iam.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>and proud in heart are an abomination to the Lord, and ſhall not be unpuniſhed, Prov.</hi> 16. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Here is matter of humiliation: for what is there in man that he should be proud of?</p>
            <p>1. If we conſider him in his firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, then as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaid, he was framed, <hi>in imis terrae partibus,</hi> in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure cloſet of nature, and the Centre of the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 15.</p>
            <p>2ly, For his Conception, the Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt tells us, he is conceived in the foul Chanel of nature.</p>
            <p>3ly, For his Pedegree and goodly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, which our Gallants ſo much brag and boaſt of, <hi>Iob</hi> tells us, <hi>chap.</hi> 17. 14. <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is our father, and the worm our mother, and ſiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4ly, If we conſider the feature of his body, <hi>Calvin</hi> tells us, he is <hi>ſex pedum vermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus,</hi> a very vermine, a Sink of unclean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe.</p>
            <p>5ly, For his fair face, a painted wall, which every ſtorm of ſickneſs defaceth and deformeth; and in this ſenſe ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 31. 30. <hi>Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:121429:77"/>
6ly, For his dainty diet, the Pſalmiſt tels us, 102. 9. <hi>That aſhes be as his bread, and tears his drink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7ly, For his coſtly lodging; and that is ſaid to be in <hi>myerie clay and in an earthly houſe.</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 1.</p>
            <p>8ly, For his reputation, the Apoſtle tells us, that he is <hi>the ſcum, and off-ſcouring of all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 13.</p>
            <p>9ly, For his deſert and merit, <hi>Daniel</hi> tells us, chap. 9. 7. <hi>it is but ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10ly, For his ſubſtance, <hi>it is but dust, and graſs,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 24.</p>
            <p>11ly, For his glory, <hi>Iſay</hi> tells us, ch. 46. 6. <hi>It is but as the flower of the field.</hi> Now lay all theſe together, <hi>Et quid ſuperbis terra et cinis,</hi> poor creature, what matter canſt thou pick, or cull, or glean for thy pride? or may not theſe ſeveral confiderations afford thee ſtore of matter to humble thee, and to teach thee to walk humbly before thy God, and man? and this is that the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of us all, as the Prophet tells us, <hi>Micah</hi> 6. 8.</p>
            <p>2ly, Here is matter of Humiliation for us in reſpect of ſpiritual gifts; for God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth no kinde of pride in man. If God
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:121429:77"/>
hath been more prodigal and liberal to thee than others, this ought not to be a means to exalt thee above them, or to deſpiſe them, but to binde thee to the more obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and thankfullneſs unto him: for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 48. <hi>where much is given, much ſhall be required;</hi> as the good man look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for more encreaſe, and better improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from him that had five Talents, than from him that had but two, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 15,</p>
            <p>3ly, Here is matter of humiliation for a proud man in reſpect of his end. As the poor man and the rich came the ſame way into the world, ſo both go the ſame way out; and then after a while, turn over their aſhes, and the wiſeſt of men cannot diſtinguiſh them; what are the bones of the greateſt Potentates better then, than the meaneſt beggers lying in the grave?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Is for information, that pride was mans undoing ſin. It was the firſt ſin that ever was in the world, and it will be the laſt that ſhall be deſtroyed in us. And when from ſuch a bitter root ſhall branch all kindes of wickedneſs, we may conceive it to be a deadly ſin.</p>
            <p>2ly, When other ſins begin to die, then ſecret pride gets ſtrength in us. <hi>Ex remediis</hi>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:121429:78"/>
               <hi>generat morbos,</hi> even vertue is the matter of this vice<hi>:</hi> in ſuch ſort, that a man will be proud, that he is not proud; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it concerns us to be very watchfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our own hearts, that it get no footing in us, or if it hath broke in at our doors, like a thief, not to reſt till we have purged our hearts of this uncleaneſſe and enemy.</p>
            <p>3ly, That howſoever all ſin may be ſaid to be in the Devil, <hi>ſecundum reatum,</hi> yet on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pride and envy is in him <hi>ſecundum affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum;</hi> he is guilty of all ſin, as tempting men to every ſin, but pride is his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fault, his darling, his <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaks, his character: ſo that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily muſt it follow, that proud men bear his ſtamp, his image, and do <hi>(patrizare)</hi> reſemble their father the Devil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Is for reproof. It was the Speech of one, I never ſaw a wiſe man proud, nor a proud man wiſe, and <hi>Verus est hic ſermo,</hi> It is a true ſaying, for</p>
            <p>1. A true wiſe man, is an humble mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, and he walks ſafely in the vallies, when he that climbs up to the tops of the mountains is ſubject to falling.</p>
            <p>2ly, A proud man cannot be wiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not learned to know God,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:121429:78"/>
nor himſelf, which is the beginning and middle, and end of wiſdome. He knows not God that can abaſe him: and he knows not himſelf how ſoon he may be humbled, and of what brittle metal he is made of, nor ſordid, ſo well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the meaneſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Harm watch, harm catch, with what meaſure m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ete ſhall be meaſured to them again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 2. <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> is Gods Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21. 24, 25. <hi>Eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, wound forwound:</hi> and this is made good in <hi>Athaliah:</hi> her meaſure was blood, and ſhe is repaid in blood, that ſhe might ſpeak with <hi>Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezek, Judg</hi> 17. <hi>As I have done, the Lord hath rewarded me;</hi> As without mercy I ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not innocents, ſo was I not ſpared by my people, although I entreated them, as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks of his wife, <hi>chap.</hi> 19. 17. <hi>Babylen</hi> was mercileſs and cruell, and therefore a proportionable puniſhment is proclaimed againſt her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 6. <hi>Reward her, as ſhe hath rewarded thine,</hi> and ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>Every man ſhall receive according to his works,</hi> not only <hi>ad aequalitatem, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litatem,</hi> for equality, but quality: And thus it was the ſaying of a Reverend man, that he never committed that ſin in his life, but that the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:121429:79"/>
Lord met with him in the ſame kind for it, and paid him in the ſame Coin. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> cauſing the male children of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to be drowned in a River, was at laſt drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with all his Hoſt in the Red Sea, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. 28. <hi>Gideon</hi> ſlaying the Seventy Elders of <hi>Succoth</hi> with unreaſonable and unmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torments, had his own ſeventy ſons murthered by the hands of <hi>Abimelech</hi> his Baſtard, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9. 5. <hi>Haman</hi> prepared a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows to hang <hi>Mordecai</hi> thereon, but his foot is taken in the ſame ſnare he laid, and he ſuffers on it, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 7. 10. <hi>Darius</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors that conſpired <hi>Daniels</hi> death, are torn into pieces by the Lions they had provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to devour him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 24. <hi>David</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs</hi> wife, had his own wives defloured by his own ſon <hi>Abſalom</hi> in the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 22. <hi>Bajazet</hi> the firſt, who reſolved in the pride of his heart, that if he ſhould conquer <hi>Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain,</hi> to carry him in an iron Cage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his whole Kingdom in Triumph, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcome was ſerved in the ſame kind by <hi>Tamberlain.</hi> The Tyrant <hi>Maxentius</hi> was overthrown in the ſame Bridge which he craftily built as a ſnare for the deſtruction of <hi>Constantine,</hi> and ſo his miſchief retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121429:79"/>
upon his own head, and cruelty fell upon his own pate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 16. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth was poiſoned at Supper with the ſame wine which he had prepared as a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly draught for his familiar friend Cardinal <hi>Adrianus,</hi> his ſervants by Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence miſtaking the bottle. The Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites burning with the fire of Luſt, were burned with fire from heaven, they finned againſt nature, and were puniſhed againſt nature, fire deſcending upon them, whoſe property is to aſcend. The dancing daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Herodias,</hi> who preferred <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> head before half her fathers Kingdom, going over a frozen River, the Ice brake, and falling into it, had her head cut off without any other harm to her body, as Hiſtory reports. So that we may conclude the generality of this point in the words of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 9. 15, 16. <hi>The Heathen are ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down in the pit that they made, in the net that they hid is their foot taken. The Lord is known by exeecuting judgement, the wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands,</hi> Higgaion, Selah; that is, take notice of it, mark it very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, conſider this in thine heart; for it is worthy to be noted.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon hereof is, to prove unto us
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121429:80"/>
the attributes of God, as I will ſhew you in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is omniſcient; for no man can conceive the leaſt miſchief in his heart againſt another, but the Lord knoweth it, and ſeeth it: <hi>For he that made the eye, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee? Pſal.</hi> 94 8. and in this ſenſe ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> to Chriſt <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 27 <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt all things,</hi> and knowing of them he can the better p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent them, and diſpoſe of the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he is omnipotent, <hi>in catching the wiſe in their own craftineſſe, and the counſel of the wicked he makes fooliſh,</hi> Job 5. 13 He is not onely omniſcient, but omnipotent, in turning things upſide down, as he beſt pleaſeth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he is a moſt juſt God in repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil with evil; evil in intention, with evil in execution. <hi>The wicked have drawn their ſword and bent their bow to ſlay ſuch as be of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right converſation;</hi> but herein his Juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is made known, that he cauſeth their ſword to enter into their own heart, and their bows to be broken, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 12, 13, 14, 15. If men were not as blind as Bats and Owls, that can ſee little or nothing in the clear light, they might perceive Gods Juſtice in
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:121429:80"/>
our latter times upon many that had a bloody hand in their Maſters death: Some hanging themſelves, ſome being beheaded, and ſome dying mad, and ſome falling to ſhame, and in falling into the pit that they made for one far more righteous than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That he is a moſt true and faithfull God, and keepeth his promiſe and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for ever, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 9. his promiſe is, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 2. <hi>With what meaſure men mete, it ſhall be meaſured to them again,</hi> and this is made good upon <hi>Saul, David, Athaliah;</hi> and ſo I paſſe to the Uſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. May ſerve to convince the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Atheiſt, that there is a God. <hi>Thales Mileſius</hi> conſidering, <hi>plantas humiditate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcere, ſiccitate marceſcere,</hi> concluded that there was an over-ruling power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; even ſo the Conſideration</p>
            <p>1. Of the diſapointing mens hopes, and bringing them to nought.</p>
            <p>2ly, Of bringing the miſchief which they imagined, upon their own heads, is ſufficient argument to declare unto us, and reſolve us there is a God, and there is none like unto God, that can do ſuch great things<hi>:</hi> ſo that we may ſing with <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:121429:81"/>
and the <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 15. 11. <hi>Who is like unto thee O Lord, among the gods? Who is like unto thee, ſo glorious in holineſſe, fearfull in prayſes, doing wonders?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Is according to that of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the people, <hi>Num.</hi> 32. 23. <hi>Be ſure your ſins will find you out.</hi> Who would have thought that <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſleeping ſo ſecurely in the bed of her fornications, lined and ſtuffed with ſuch bloody feathers, and boulſtered with ſo much wickedneſſe (ſo many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſhould be awakened out of it, and called to the bar of Divine Juſtice, and then and there ſentenced to death? but when ſhe ſleeped, the Lord watched her down-lying and upriſing, he compaſſed all her paths, he ſeal'd up her iniquities in a bag, <hi>Job</hi> 14 17. and breaks it open to her deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Now, <hi>Mutato nomine, de vobis Fabula narratur,</hi> what is recorded of her, will be verified of you in the end, and therefore ſearch out that <hi>Achan</hi> ſin, and turn that <hi>Hagar</hi> out of doors, leſt it trouble you, and find you out, and turn you ont of Gods favour, and bring you to ſhame. <hi>Oh that men were wiſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32. 29. <hi>then would they conſider and underſtand this, that their ſins will find them out,</hi> and ſo the conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:121429:81"/>
and underſtanding thereof would teach them to ſtand in aw, and not dare to ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 4. I read of a Philoſopher that took up a Stage in an eminent market, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>ſe velle vendere ſenſum,</hi> that he would ſell underſtanding to any that ſtood in need of it: the King of that Countrey being informed thereof, ſends meſſengers with ſtore of gold in their hands to purchaſe it: the Philoſopher writes in a little Paper theſe words, <hi>In omnibus quae facturus es, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per reſpice finem, &amp; cogita quid poſſit tibi acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> that is, In all things thou goeſt about, think alwayes what the end will be, and what may befall thee in the end: and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering of it to them, adviſed them to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it to their Maſter, and to tell him that it was full worth his mony: the which the King receiving, cauſed it to be written in golden letters over his Chamber door: now after a little time, ſome diſcontented people hired a rude, lewd fellow to ſtab the King, and going about his work, with a heart full of miſchief, and reading this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription, his countenance changed, and falls trembling, and ſhaking, as if he had an ague fit: the which being perceived, and he examined, confeſſed the whole matter,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:121429:82"/>
and what diverted him from it. Even ſo, if men would but ſeriouſly conſider, that with what meaſure they mete, ſhall be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured to them again, or that nothing ſurer than their ſins would find them out, or that the end of ſin and wages of ſin is death, <hi>Rom</hi> 6. 23. How would this Meditation ſtop the current of their vile affections, and divert them from ſinning? It was an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Speech of one, <hi>Cave quid agis; te vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det Deus.</hi> Beware what thou doeſt; for God ſeeth thee, and all things are naked and open to his eyes with whom thou haſt to do, ſaith <hi>Paul, Heb.</hi> 4. 13. and <hi>Homer</hi> ſpeaking of a Frog and a Mouſe, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſharp conteſtation and bitter Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, the party grieved tells the other, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God had a reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging eye to right him: even ſo, if men would but remember whatſoever they are about or doing, God looked upon them, and had a revenging eye to requite it in the ſame meaſure and nature, it would ſtifle all treaſon againſt heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. This may teach us, that ſeeing with what meaſure we mete, ſhall be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured to us again, to walk circumſpectly and warily, not as fools, but as wiſe, <hi>Eph.</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:121429:82"/>
5. 115. the Law of God and nature ſhould be our rule to ſquare our lives, and all our actions by, and that is, <hi>Quod tibi non vis, alteri non feceris,</hi> to do as we would be done unto, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 12. and ſaith <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 6. 16. <hi>To as many as walk according to this rule, peace ſhall be upon them, and mercy, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the true</hi> Iſrael <hi>of God. Whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap,</hi> Gal. 6. 7. <hi>He that ſoweth righteouſneſs, ſhall receive a good and ſure reward,</hi> Prov. 11. 18. <hi>But he that ſoweth iniquiry ſhall reap affliction, and the rod of his anger ſhall fail,</hi> chap. 22. 8. God hath a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold meaſure.</p>
            <p>1. Either a meaſure of glory, and that is for thoſe that abound in the works of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 58.</p>
            <p>2ly, A meaſure of wrath and ſorrow, and that is for thoſe that plough iniquity, and ſow wickedneſs, <hi>Job</hi> 4. 8. and with this meaſure did God mete <hi>Athaliah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. Is, <hi>Qualis vita, finis ita,</hi> As we live, ſo commonly we die, as we ſpeak in another kind, <hi>Mali principii malns exitus,</hi> an ill beginning hath an ill end<hi>:</hi> even ſo, an ungodly life is accompanied uſually with a ſad death. Look upon <hi>Haman,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Judas,</hi> caſt an eye upon <hi>Julian</hi> the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:121429:83"/>
grand Apoſtate, who died curſing and ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, crying out in defiance of Chriſt, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti Galilaeo,</hi> O thou Galilean, thou haſt conquered and overcome me. Turn over the Chronicle of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and thou ſhalt find, that as ſhe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ank living in the noſtrils of the people, for her idolatry, pride, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of anothers Crown, blood-thirſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo in her death ſhe was abhorred by all, and had not power to cry out with <hi>Peter, Lord ſave me,</hi> or with the Publican, <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> The Husbandman can tell us, that which way the tree lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that way it will fall if it be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by art; and I have often obſerved in viſiting the ſick, that as the Proverb is, <hi>quod in corde ſobrii, id in lingua ebrii,</hi> what lies cloſe hid in the heart of a ſober man, is revealed by his tongue when he is drunk: even ſo, as men lean and are affected living, ſo their hearts and tongues run of it dying; and what hopes can there be, that they who had not God in all their thoughts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. 4. when they were in health, ſhould go to God when they are dead?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> As the tree ſtandeth, ſo it falleth, and ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 11. 3. As the tree doth fall, ſo in the place that the tree falleth,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:121429:83"/>
there it ſhall lie: So that this doth much concern us to denie ungodlineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and worldly luſt, and to live ſoberly, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and godly in this preſent world, looking for that bleſſed hope, and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that glory of that mighty God, and of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 12, 13. labouring to fall to the South of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and not to the North of his Juſtice. Death is not ſo fearfull and terrible in it ſelf, as is the ſting of it, which is ſin, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 56. And therefore let it be our care to be every day weakning, and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out this ſerpents ſting, that we may with old <hi>Simeon depart in peace, Luke</hi> 2. 29. <hi>And bleſsed ſhall be the dead that die in the Lord, for their works follow them, Rev.</hi> 14. 13. Thus ye have heard, 1. what <hi>Athaliab</hi> was. 2ly, What her Treaſon, and 3ly, what her end was. <hi>She rent her clothes, and cryed Treaſon, Treaſon: and was ſlain by the way, which the horſes go to the Kings houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121429:84"/>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:121429:84"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
            <p>O Thou mighty, Almighty Creator, and Preſerver of men, We thy poor Creatures protected this night from Fire, Sword, Sickneſſe, Death, and thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold evils that might have befallen us, and overtaken us, by reaſon of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of our ſins (for man ſuffers for his ſins) cannot but aſcribe all praiſe with the Samaritan Leper, due unto thy holy name, for this unſpeakable mercy of thine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us miſerable ſinners, unworthy to taſt of the leaſt drop, much leſſe that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of thy love, daily ſtreaming and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home to our doors, to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our ſouls. <hi>For what is man that thou art mindfull of him, or the Son of man that thou ſhouldest regard him?</hi> there is nothing in man but deſerves open ſhame and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:121429:85"/>
of face continually. Wherefore we deny our ſelves, and all our own unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, as filthy clouts, and menſtruous rags, and flee unto thee in thy Chriſt, that in him, by him, and through him, both now and ever, we may be acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord, our ſtrength, and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. And as thy mercies have been great towards us this night paſt, ſo we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to continue the ſame mercy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us this day, and ſo to the end of our dayes. Defend us from our Ghoſtly and bodily enemies: Shield us with thy grace, that we fall not this day into any manner of evil of ſin, that we may never grieve thy good Spirit any more by ſin, and ſo prevent another day the evil of puniſhment for ſin. Direct us in thy mercie in our going out. and coming in, that whatſoever we ſhall take in hand, it may proſper, like <hi>Joſeph:</hi> O proſper thou our handie work upon us. Inſtruct us in the heavenly wiſdome, that above all things we may be wiſe unto the ſalvation of our poor ſouls<hi>:</hi> And teach us with the night paſt to caſt away all the works of darkneſſe, and of the Devil, and with the day, to walk honeſtly, as children of the light, and of the day. Teach us
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:121429:85"/>
by our walking and wandring up and down from one place to another, ever to remember that we are but Pilgrims and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journers here on earth, and ſo to fix our hearts and eyes homeward, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and upon that reſt remains to the people of God. Teach us by every thing we take in hand, to do all to the glory of God, by whom we live, move, and have our being. To this end guide our eyes, that they behold no more vanity, Guide our ears, that they let in no more folly. Guide our tongues, that the name of God be no more blaſphemed amongſt us. Guide our hearts, that they ſuggeſt and act ſuch things as are pleaſing to the Lord. Guide our hands, that they may be more quick and lively in doing Gods buſineſſe, than our own Guide our feet, that we may run in the wayes of thy commandments, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the death. Lord ſo guide us in our hearts, bodies, minds and affections, that above all things we may apply our ſelves to glorifie thee on earth, that at laſt we may be glorified by thee in the Kingdom of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And ſeeing thou haſt made man for thy glory, give us of thy grace, that we may ſerve thee to thy glory. Give us inſtead of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:121429:86"/>
hearts of ſtone, hearts of fleſh, and hearts of wax, that they may be alwayies pliable to ſerve thee our Maker and Redeemer. Give us a true ſight and light into all our ſins, and a true Repentance for our ſins, yea even a loathing of our ſelves for all the evils which we have committed in all our abominations againſt our kind God: that our ſins may be put away when the time of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, and the glory of his power. Give us a true taſte of the joyes above, that we may with <hi>Davids</hi> hunted hart, pant af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Rivers of living water, and long to be with Chriſt, our Love, our Head and Captain of our ſalvation. Quicken us in the wayes of godlineſſe, that we may ſerve thee with alacrious and chearfull ſpirits. Enflame our hearts with an holy zeal to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy Law, thy word and thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that it may be as meat and drink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, alwaies to do thy will. And as we have given up formerly our Members, as weapons of unrighteouſneſſe unto ſin: ſo henceforward ſtrengthen us with thy holy Spirit, that we may give up our Members, as weapons of righteouſneſſe to ſerve the everliving God<hi>:</hi> not labouring ſo eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:121429:86"/>
ſo earneſtly, ſo heartilie, ſo greedilie, after that bread and meat which periſheth together with us, as after that bread which endures unto everlaſting life: <hi>For what will it profit a man to gain the whole world, and at laſt loſe his own ſoul?</hi> Our ſouls they were and are dear unto thee, and they coſt the ſon of thy love, thy onelie begotten ſon, and thy beſt beloved ſon, thy ſon in whom alone thou art well pleaſed, the deareſt price of his deareſt blood: how then ought they to be dear unto us? and how can we better ſhew that they are dear and precious unto us, than by ſeeking the good of them more ferventlie, than after anie thing elſe whatſoever? O Lord grant, that we may not onlie know what is good, but that we may do that which is good<hi>: For they that know their Maſters will, &amp; do it not ſhall be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with many stripes. Except the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid) builds the houſe, they labour in vain that build it, Except the Lord keepeth the City, the watchman waketh but in vain.</hi> Paul <hi>may plant, and</hi> Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo <hi>may water,</hi> but all is in vain without thy bleſſing: let therefore thy good bleſſing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company all our ſpiritual &amp; bodilie labors, that all things may work together for thy glorie, and for the beſt unto them that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:121429:87"/>
love thee, and deſire to fear thy name. Lord be with us this day, quicken us unto every good work, ſtand by us, reſtrain the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of our own natures, quench the fierie darts of that wicked one, that they may not prevail againſt us in this world, and ſo be never able to witneſſe againſt us in the world to come. And all this we beg of thee for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, in whoſe name we conclude our Prayers in that abſolute manner and form, which he hath taught us.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Our Father which art in heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer for Noon day.</head>
            <p>IT was <hi>Davids</hi> practice, Evening, and Morning, and at Noon, to pray; and that we may be followers of him, having him for an enſample, to walk according to his rule, that we may obtain peace and mercie, as the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, we thy poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Bleſſed Lord God, do humblie caſt our ſelves down at thy feet and footſtool, begging of thee, that as thou art the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which leadeſt thy people in
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:121429:87"/>
and out like a flock of ſheep; ſo thou wouldeſt be pleaſed to lead us into the green paſtures, there to feed us with ſpiritual and corporal food, whereby bodie and ſoul may be fed fullie, comfortablie, and with comforts everlaſting. O thou ſhepherd of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> among the manifold chances and changes of this uncertain life, defend us from <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> that neither inward nor outward enemies hurt us not: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, that ſin nor Satan prevail not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us Direct us in the narrow way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and amendment of life, that when our day ſhall end, we may enter in at the ſtraight gate, and ſo enjoy the Ancient of daies. Rowz up our dull ſpirits, that we may run in the waies of thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſo obtain that Crown of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which the Lord our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall give unto thoſe that love him, and call upon his name. The night is paſt, and the bright day come, Grant us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grace to walk as children of light, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilie, unblameablie, unſpottedlie, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault in thy ſight. Grant that with the Morning we may look freſh in grace, and with the Noon grow to a fulneſſe of grace, and with the Evening lie down in
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:121429:88"/>
grace, that the God of grace may receive us into his tuition and favour. We have enjoied a comfortable morning, O thrice bleſſed be thy name for it<hi>:</hi> but we might, and all that we have might have been conſumed into duſt and aſhes, hadſt not thou of thy goodneſſe preſerved us; ſo that who can think? who can ſay it is in vain to ſerve the Lord? But now who can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe himſelf one hour more? much leſſe an Evening, if thou ſhalt hide thy face, and withdraw the light of thy countenance from us: and therefore we crave of thee to ſuccour us, to guard us, to continue thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe towards us, and to guide us to our reſt. Our enemies are many in this our vallie of tears, that it is of the Lords mercie, that we have not long ſince been conſumed; our ſtrength to withſtand them very weak, like a reed to the great Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than; Our friends to help us, are like <hi>Jobs,</hi> miſerable comforters; our footing on this ſea of glaſſe, very ſlipperie<hi>:</hi> but when all our other truſt, is but as a ſpiders web, this is our comfort in our afflictions, that although our father and mother, and all the world forſake us, yet the Lord will then gather us up, and will not leave us
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:121429:88"/>
comfortleſſ. Wherefore in all humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of all thankfulneſs due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, vve offer up unto thee our ſelves, our ſouls and bodies, a quick and living ſacrifice, that the God in whom we live, move, &amp; have our being, may be glorified in and by our being. This is our day: therfore it is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whilſt it is called to day, to ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and call upon him whilſt he is near. This is our day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are to work: and ſo let it be our ſole wiſdome to work out our ſalvation, leſt the night come and overtake us, when no man can work. This is our day; and how ill doth it become us to trewant, and loiter it away, like thoſe that ſtood idle in the market place? or to riot it, and revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, eating and drinking, and curſing <hi>Abimelech?</hi> leſt we be in hell to morrow, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and howling, and roring, with <hi>Dives,</hi> Devils, and damned ones. Let the Sun which cometh as a Bridegroom out of his chamber, and rejoiceth to run his race, Ever teach us to be active in ſpiritual duties, and heavenlie exerciſes. Let the Sun which encreaſeth from glorie to glorie, teach us to encreaſe in vertue, goodneſſe, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: adding to vertue knowledge, to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:121429:89"/>
knowledge temperance, to temperance pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, to patience brotherlie kindneſſe, and ſo one grace to another, that we may be complete Chriſtians, like unto our head, and Lord, and Maſter. Let the morning inſtruct us to remember our Creator in the daies of our youth. Let the Noon tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour us to be ſtrong in the faith. Let the Evening admoniſh us to think of the end of our life, and ſhutting in of our daies. Let all teach us ſo to number our daies, that we may applie our hearts unto wiſdome. Let a waterie daie ever mind us of the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, afflictions and troubles attend us in this life. Let a pleaſant day mind us of the pleaſures to come, when theſe are faded, and forgotten. Let a ſhort daie mind us of the ſhortneſſe of this life, which is but as a ſpan long, and ſwifter than a Weavers Shuttle. Let a long daie mind us of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of life, either in bliſſe or bane, and ſo read us a continual Lecture, to labour for that meat which endures unto everlaſting life, and not after that bread which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth with us; the which that we may do, the Lord grant unto us, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, our bleſſed Saviour and redeemer, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:121429:89"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the Evening.</head>
            <p>I <hi>Will lay me down and alſo ſleep in peace, for thou Lord makest me dwell in ſafety,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> Now good God grant, that as we lie down in thy love, ſo we may riſe by thy power, and glorifie thee for thy mercy.</p>
            <p>O moſt gracious God, and in thy ſon Jeſus Chriſt, our loving Father, we miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinners, duſt and aſhes, worms and not men, do proſtrate our ſelves before the footſtool of thy Throne of grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee, that ſeeing thou haſt made the night for man to reſt, ſo well as the day for him to labour; ſo that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be pleaſed to bleſſe us this night, and keep us from fire, ſword, ſickneſſe, death, and thoſe manifold evils may befall us, and overtake us by reaſon of our manifold ſins and wickedneſſes. Thou art about their beds, and giveſt thy Angels charge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them that ſeek unto thee for ſuccour: thou knoweſt their down-lying, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing, and art near unto thoſe that call upon thee in truth and ſyncerity of heart<hi>:</hi> wherefore graciouſly, good God, ſpread
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:121429:90"/>
thou the wings of thy loving kendneſſe, and favour over us this night, and let not this houſe be as a tomb and Sepulchre ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted over our heads: let not our beds be as our graves, our blankets as the mold of the earth, and our ſheefs, as our winding-ſheets: but let them all ſerve to miniſter comfort and refreſhment to our wearied bodies and ſenſes, that the day following, we may be the better enabled to ſet forth thy praiſe, and thy glorie. Let not our ſleep be inſatiable, according to the deſires of the fleſh, but onely ſo, as that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive our dull and heavy drooping ſpirits, and make them active in thy ſervice, and in the works of our calling. Teach us by our unclothing, and uncovering of our ſelves, and caſting away our garments from us, continually to think of caſting away every weight, and caſting off that old man which is corrupt through his deceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble works. Teach us by our nakedneſſe when our garments are from us, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to think of harmleſneſſe and innocency of life: endevouring our ſelves daily to live void of offence towards God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man. Teach us by going out of our warm clothes into our cold beds, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:121429:90"/>
to think on a change of life, how that we ſhall one day leave this ſinfull world, and paſſe into another, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to our ſeveral works. Teach us by our ſleep, continuallie to think on death, and by our waking from ſleep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, continually to think of reſurrection of life; how that we ſhall one day wake, and riſe out of the duſt of the earth, and behold our God, not with other, but with theſe ſame eyes. O let everie thing be our inſtruction to ſhew us the right way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and everlaſting bliſſe. Father, bleſſe us bodily, yea and bleſſe us ſpiritually: give unto our bodies a happie reſt in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whenſoever, as we know not how ſoon, thou maieſt call them out of this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful world; and ſay unto our ſouls, that he was the redemption thereof, and paid the ranſom of them with his deareſt blood, that under the ſhadow of his wings, we may flie to thy heavenly Sanctuary. Father, bleſs us inwardlie, and bleſſe us outwardly: bleſſe us inwardly with all theſe graces which are fit and needfull for our ſeveral places, conditions and callings; and bleſſe us outwardlie, with all thoſe things we want, and ſtand in need of, as health,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:121429:91"/>
ſtrength, eaſe, wealth; bleſſe us likewiſe in everie thing belongs unto us, that they yielding forth their ſtrength, and encreaſe unto us, we may yield forth unto thee our God the ſtrength of our obedience, praiſe and thanksgiving. O father, thou art great, and therefore to be feared: thou art good, and therefore to be praiſed: according therefore to thy greatneſſe, and according to thy goodneſſe, be thy praiſe: and we entreat thee to continue this thy loving kindneſſe to us unto our lives end, and to life eternal. And that we may obtain this mercy, we beſeech thee to give us grace to walk worthie of thy mercies, that we may find and feel the fruits of thy favour bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in our ſouls. O give us grace that we may look unto our feet, that we walk no more in the waies of diſobedience, whereby we ſhould offend and grieve the good Spirit of ſo Good a God, and ſo loving a father; for our own Conſciences tell us, <hi>That what couldest thou have done more for thy vineyard?</hi> and the plants of thy vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard? and ſuch vile, ſinfull wretches, that thou haſt not done unto us? and yet what could any ſtubborn and ſtiffe-necked gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration have done more to provoke thee to
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:121429:91"/>
anger, wrath, and ſore diſpleaſure, than we have done? But Lord, call not thou our ſins to thy remembrance: lay not thou our ſins to our charge; for if thou ſhouldeſt be but ſtrict to mark wherein we have done amiſſe, who ſhould be able to ſtand in thy ſight? Wherefore for thy mercie ſake ſpare us, for the multitude of thy tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake have compaſſion on us, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, forgive us all that is paſt, how many, how great, how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, how crying ſoever our ſins have been, and ſtrengthen us with ſtrength from above, that we may ſpend the reſidue of our lives in thy ſervice, whollie reſigning up our ſelves unto thee, fearing of thee, &amp; keeping of thy Commandement, labouring, &amp; indevouring, to live as much hereafter to thy honour, as ever we have heretofore done to thy diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. And for as much as thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to be mindfull of the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> we beg of thee to be good to all thy poor afflicted ones<hi>:</hi> work in them a true inſight into all their ſins, and a true Repentance for their ſins, and a ſtrong faith to believe that their ſins are pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the blood of that immaculate Lamb: Lord, if it be thy will, let them live to
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:121429:92"/>
praiſe thee, and for the comfort of thoſe that belong unto them: but if thou in thy ſecret counſel haſt decreed them for death, grant that although their bodies return to the earth, yet their ſpirits may return to their Maker. And preſerve thou our lives, and healths unto us, not that they may, be a means to follow our former wantonneſſe with the greater greedineſſe, but that we may be the better abilicated to ſet forth the glorie of our moſt Glorious God. Bleſſe thoſe of our neareſt relation: bleſſe them and us, and all of us, with inward and outward, with ſpiritual and corporal health and wealth, that we may glorifie thee our God with both all the daies of our lives. Bleſſe thy poor <hi>Zion:</hi> deliver thy <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of all his troubles. Make not us who were once thy <hi>Beulahs,</hi> thy <hi>Hephzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bahs,</hi> thy joy, thy delight, now to become <hi>Loammies, Loruhamaes,</hi> a deſpiſed and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken people. Make not us who were once <hi>Naomies,</hi> a pleaſant ſeed, now to become <hi>Marahs,</hi> a ſeed drunken with bitter waters of a full cup wrung out unto us. Make not us, who were once as <hi>Abigails,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers joy, now to become <hi>Benonies,</hi> the ſons of our mothers ſorrows. O let not this
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:121429:92"/>
be publiſhed in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor proclaimed in <hi>Askalon,</hi> leſt the uncircumciſed take up this Proverb againſt us, <hi>Go ye unto</hi> Shiloh, go ye unto <hi>England,</hi> and ſee how their Sun is ſet, their pride abaſed, and their pomp vaniſhed, becauſe they would not hear and obey, nor regard the voice of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah. O for thy Chriſts ſake be pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thy ſervants that call upon thy name, as <hi>Herod</hi> was with the men of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Zidon</hi> for <hi>Blastus</hi> his ſake and mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and as thou art wonderfull in thy name, ſo be thou wonderfull in thy works, and command at length deliverances for thy <hi>Jacob.</hi> Bleſſe our Supreme head: <hi>Let every mountain and hill that is exalted againſt it be made low:</hi> let the crooked be made ſtraight, let the rough be made plain: oh let the zeal of the Lord God of Hoſts in his good time perform all this. Call home all thoſe that have erred like loſt ſheep, and are deceived: open their eyes to ſee the truth, direct their hearts to walk in that truth, that walking in the old way, which is the good way, they may at laſt come to him, who is the way, the truth, and the life. Sanctifie this nights reſt unto us. Grant that our ſleep it may be ſweet, for the refreſhing of our
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:121429:93"/>
wearied ſenſes, that the day following we may be the better ſtrengthened to ſet forth the honour of our God. Give thy angels charge over us this night; for they alone are well kept whom thou keepeſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into thy hands both now and ever, with bleſſed <hi>Steven,</hi> do we commend all our ſpirits. Theſe O father, and all other things thou in thy infinite and all-ſeeing goodneſſe ſhalt better ſee to be requiſite, either for our ſelves, or for any other, we humbly beſeech thee to grant them unto us, not for our own ſakes; for we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelves unworthy to gather up the crumb; that fall from thy table: wherefore we beg them for thy Chriſts ſake, in whoſe name we conclude our prayer in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect form which he hath taught us, ſaying, <hi>Our father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121429:93"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
